<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><!--
        **DO NOT MANUALLY EDIT THIS FILE**  
        its generated automatically with XSLT
        -->
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>ATB People (27 June 2022)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>blah blah</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
              sources: 
              <list>
                  <item>Teams spreadsheet: Ographies/b1_bor_masterlist_220413 - spreadsheet derived from encoded books xml</item>
                  <item>Teams biographies docx: BoR and Bk1 biographies (latest version)</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p>
            NOTES: 
            
            bios are still work in progress and a bit messy in places because reasons.
            
            ID construction based on name initials:
              use full [std] initials where known
              for married women include maiden surname initial if known
              if firstname [or surname for that matter] unavailable use x
              add number to ensure uniqueness
            [working IDs; may be changed at a later stage]
            any "tbd" IDs need to be verified
            
            updated to match KDL model
            
            TODO various...
            
            xslt:
              maybe if-else for empty tags (most roleName are empty)

            data:
              roleName, forename, need finessing. esp @type=...
              birth and death date formatting; baptism/burial types
              haven't yet done anything about bio sources
              wikidata linkage to do once name tagging and internal linkage is completed
              listRelation - also once name tagging and biographies are complete
             
          </p>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date when="2022-06-27"/>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <listPerson>
            <person xml:id="awt1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Alice</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Thornton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Alice Wandesford Thornton</persName>
               <birth>13 February 1626</birth>
               <death>buried 1 February 1707</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Alice Wandesford (1626-1707) was born to Christopher Wandesford – later Lord Deputy of Ireland – and his wife Alice Osborne in Kirklington, North Yorkshire on 13 February 1626. She was their fifth child of seven, and their youngest daughter. The family relocated to Dublin in the 1630s when Wandesford's friend and mentor Thomas Wentworth, 1st Lord Strafford, became Lord Deputy of Ireland. Wandesford succeeded Wentworth in 1640 but died that same year. On the breakout of the Irish Rebellion in 1641 the Wandesford family fled back to England, living in Cheshire for some time before slowly relocating back to Alice's mother's jointure property at Hipswell in 1644, during the Second War of the Three Kingdoms. , and the family located back to Yorkshire during the Civil War. She married William Thornton of East Newton in 1651, and they had nine 9 children, three 3 of whom survived to adulthood: Alice (Nally), Katherine and Robert. Alice wrote three autobiographies ('Books of my Life') and a Book of Remembrances. She died in 1707 at East Newton and wasis buried at Stonegrave on 1 February 1707..</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cw1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Christopher Wandesford</persName>
               <birth>24 September 1592</birth>
               <death>3 December 1640</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Christopher Wandesford (1592-1640) was the eldest son and heir of Sir George Wandesford and Catherine Hansby; Alice Wandesford Thornton's father. He was born at Bishop Burton, East Riding, on 24 September 1592. He attended Clare College, Cambridge but was required to return home on his father's death to provide for his siblings. He married Alice Osborne and they had seven children, five of whom survived childhood. He was MP for Yorkshire in the 1620s, and in 1633 relocated the family to Dublin, Ireland, to serve as Master of Rolls under his childhood friend, Thomas Wentworth 1st Earl Strafford, who had been made Lord Deputy of Ireland. On Wentworth's death in 1640 Wandesford was briefly Lord Deputy before he died at 48 years old on 3 December 1640.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rl1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Roger</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Lasselles</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Roger Lasselles</persName>
               <birth>1557</birth>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Roger Lasscelles, or Lascelles (1557-1630),  was rector of Kirklington from 19 May 1590 until his death in July 1630. He baptised Alice Wandesford Thornton at Kirklington in February 1626.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="awn1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Norton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Anne Wandesford Norton</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>buried 23 December 1683</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Norton (xxxx-1683) was the daughter of Sir George Wandesford and Catherine Hansby; was Alice Thornton’s aunt. She married Maulger Norton on 4 March 1622. They had five children; three sons and two daughters. She was buried on 23 December 1683.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Olive</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Best</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Mallory</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mrs Best</persName>
               <birth>baptised 5 December 1594</birth>
               <death>buried 16 June 1654</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Olive Mallory Best (1594-1654), baptised 5 December 1594, was the daughter of John Mallory and Anne Eure. She became the second wife of Thomas Best of Middleton Quernhow, M.P. for Ripon on 17 January 1619. She had a twin sister, Jane. She died without issue and was buried on 16 June 1654.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="st1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Sarah</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Tomlinson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sarah Tomlinson</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sarah Tomlinson was a servant in Alice's household.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cw2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>1st Baronet of Kirklington</roleName>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Christopher Wandesford</persName>
               <birth>2 February 1628</birth>
               <death>23 February 1687</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Wandesford (1628-87), 1st Baronet of Kirklington, was the son of  Sir Christopher Wandesford and Alice Osborne, and was born on 2 February 1628; Alice Wandesford Thornton's younger brother. He married Eleanor Lowther on 30 September 1651, and they had 12 children. He became family heir on his brother George’s death in 1651 and was made Baronet on the Restoration of Charles II in 1660. He was elected MP for Ripon in 1679 and again in 1680. He died in London on 23 February 1687.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Baxter</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mr Baxter</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Baxter of Kent hosted Alice and Christopher Wandesford, then children, and their maid Sarah, to aid their recovery from smallpox. The Wandesford family were living in London at the time.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xl1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lady</roleName>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Leveson</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Dudley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Lady Leverton ?</persName>
               <birth>1598</birth>
               <death>1674</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Lady Katherine Leveson (1598-1674) was the daughter of the illegitimate son of the Elizabethan courtier Robert Dudley, also called Robert Dudley, and his first wife Alice Leigh, born 1598. She married Sir Richard Leveson of Shropshire, elected MP for Newcastle-under-Lyme in 1640. She died in 1674 without issue, and endowed almshouses and an education fund which survives to this day at Temple Balsall.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tw1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir, 1st Lord Raby; 1st Earl of Strafford</roleName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wentworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Thomas Wentworth, earl of Strafford</persName>
               <birth>13 April 1593</birth>
               <death>12 May 1641</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Wentworth, 1st Lord Raby, 1st Earl Strafford (1593-1641), was Lord Lieutenant of Ireland 1633-40. He was born on 13 April 1593 to William Wentworth, a Yorkshire landowner, and Anne Atkinson, their second and eldest surviving son and heir. He was a childhood friend of Christopher Wandesford, Alice's Thornton's father, both being educated by the Dean of Ripon. His first marriage to Margaret Clifford took place in 1611, she died childless in August 1622. He married Arabella Holles in February 1625, then had a son and two daughters. After her premature death on 6 October 1631 he married Elizabeth Rodes in 1632 and had another son and a daughter. In 1633 he was made Lord Deputy of Ireland and relocated to Dublin, with the Wandesford family in tow as Christopher was made Master of the Rolls. He was recalled to England in 1639, fell out of favour with the King, impeached and executed on 12 May 1641.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="aw1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lady</roleName>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Watson</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wentworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Lady Anne Wentworth</persName>
               <birth>October 1627 (1629?)</birth>
               <death>2 January 1696</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Lady Anne Wentworth (1627-96) was the eldest daughter of Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl of Strafford and his second wife Arabella Holles, born in October 1627. A childhood friend of Alice Wandesford Thornton's's in Dublin, she married Edward Watson on 24 November 1654 and they had two sons and two daughters. She died on 2 January 1696.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="aw2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lady</roleName>
                  <forename>Arabella</forename>
                  <surname type="married">McCarthy</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wentworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Lady Arbella Wentworth</persName>
               <birth>1630</birth>
               <death>1689</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Lady Arabella Wentworth (1630-89) was the daughter of Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl of Strafford and Arabella Holles. A childhood friend of Alice Wandesford Thornton's 's in Dublin, she married Justin MacCarthy, 1st Viscount Mountcashell, who was about 13 years her junior. She died in 1689 without issue.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jw1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Wandesford</persName>
               <birth>c. 1632</birth>
               <death>2 December 1664</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Wandesford (c. 1632-1664) was the fourth, but third surviving, son of Christopher Wandesford and Alice Osborne;, and the brother of Alice Wandesford, born c. 1632.Thornton. He was educated at Bedale, Chester and Richmond Schools before entering Christ's College, Cambridge (1649-51). Becoming ill at Cambridge, according to Alice in reaction to the death of their brother George, he moved to London. He was elected MP for Richmond in 1661, and  after he successfully petitioned the election of Joseph Cradock, disqualified on account of being an ecclesiastic. He died in his lodgings at Richmond on 2 December 1664, of an ague.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fk1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Frank</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Kelly</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Frank Kelly</persName>
               <birth>c. 1634</birth>
               <death>1643</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Frank Kelly (c. 1634-43) was an orphan boy taken into the household of Sir Christopher Wandesford in Dublin, after Wandesford had encountered him while playing bowls on the green. According to Alice he was about 9 when he died of small pox at Chester after the family had fled Ireland, meaning he was born c. 1634.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="td1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Thomas Danby</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>14 June 1645</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Danby of South Cave (d. 1645) was the second son of Thomas Danby of Braworth. He was involved in a court of chivalry case in 1638 against John Bates of York, whom Danby claimed had verbally abused him and denied his gentility. He fought for the Royalists during the Civil War and was killed at the Battle of Naseby on 14 June 1645.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xm1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                  <forename>Richard(?)</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Mahum</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mr Mahum</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dr Mahum, described by Alice as her 'old doctor', may be the same Richard Mahum who witnessed her mother's will in 1659.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="kwd1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Danby</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Katherine Wandesford Danby</persName>
               <birth>1615</birth>
               <death>10 September 1645</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Wandesford Danby (1615-45): eldest child of Christopher Wandesford and Alice Osborne; older sister of Alice Thornton. Born in 1615, she married Thomas Danby, who was in the service of the Lord Deputy of Ireland, in July 1630. She was pregnant 16 times but suffered 6 stillbirths, and of the couple's 10 baptised children 8 were boys and 2 were girls. She died on 10 September 1645 at the family estate at Thorpe Perrowher house in Thorp of postpartum complications, as a result of childbirth. She was bBuried at Masham 11 Sept. 1645.the next day.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fd1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Francis</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Francis Danby</persName>
               <birth>3 September 1645</birth>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Francis Danby (born 3 September 16451645-xxxx) was the y; youngest son of Thomas Danby and Katherine Wandesford, born on 3 September 1645 at Thorpe Perrow; Alice Wandesford'sAlice Thornton's nephew. Named after his brother born in 1640 who died as a baby the previous year,in July 1645, his mother Katherine died from post-partum complications a few days after his birth.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="en1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename>Edmund</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Edmund Norton</persName>
               <birth>1622</birth>
               <death>29 November 1648</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edmund Norton (born 1622-48)):; second son of Maulger Norton and Anne Wandesford; Alice Thornton's 's cousin. He aAttended Cambridge University and was admitted to Gray's Inn in 1645/46. He served as a colonel of dragoons under John Mallory during the He married Jane Dudley, and d. Died of a pleurisy at York on 29 Novemberin 1648.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="td2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename>Toby</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Dudley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Toby Dudley</persName>
               <birth>1597</birth>
               <death>1661</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Toby Dudley (b. 1597-1661) was the oldest son and heir of Ambrose Dudley of Chopwell, Northumberland. He married Jane Blackiston, and they had one child, Jane. He was buried at Ryton in 1661.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jdn1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Jane</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Norton</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Clavering</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Dudley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Jane Dudley Norton</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>1672</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Jane Dudley Norton (xxxx-1672) was the daughter and sole heir of Toby Dudley of Chopwell. She married Edmund Norton on 10 February 1647. He died in 1648. Her second husband was Robert Clavering who she married at Ebchester on 15 July 1651. They had three 3 children, a son and 2 daughters. She died in 1672.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cs1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>King Charles I</roleName>
                  <forename>Charles</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Stuart</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Charles I</persName>
               <birth>19 November 1600</birth>
               <death>30 January 1649</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles I of England (born 19 November 16001600-49), born 19 November 1600 to James I and VI and Anne of Denmark, was King of England, Scotland and Ireland from 1625, was and the reigning monarch for the first 23 years of Alice Thornton''s life. He was executed on 30 January 1649.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jn1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Julian</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Julian Norton</persName>
               <birth>6 January 1632</birth>
               <death>9 April 1649</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Julian (or Gillian)Julian Norton (1632-49), born 6 January 1632, was the daughter of Maulger and Anne Norton (Alice's aunt; Alice Thornton's cousin). She was born in 1632 and so waswas only 17 when she died on 9 April 1649 at her father's house at Richmond.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jn2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Norton</persName>
               <birth>c. 1637(?)</birth>
               <death>1646</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Norton (c. 1637-1646), fourth son of Maulger Norton and Anne Wandesford, Alice Thornton's cousin. He died at his father's residence at St Nicholas, Richmond of a consumption in 1646, aged 9., aged 9.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="eo1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir; 1st Baronet Kiveton</roleName>
                  <forename>Edward</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Osborne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir Edward Osborne</persName>
               <birth>baptised 12 December 1596</birth>
               <death>9 September 1647</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Edward Osborne, 1st Baronet Kiveton (1596-1647) was baptised on 12 December 1596, the son of Sir Hewett Osborne and Joyce Fleetwood. He was brother of Alice Wandesford and the ; maternal uncle of Alice Thornton. He was knighted and created Baronet by James I and was vice president of the Council of the North. He married twice, first, Margaret Belasyse, with whom he had a son, and after her death Anne Walmesley, with whom he had a second son. He died on 9 September 1647, according to Alice Thornton from a surfeit of cold melons..</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gw1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>George</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">George Wandesford</persName>
               <birth>14 September 1623</birth>
               <death>31 March 1651</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Wandesford (born 14 September 1623-51), born 14 September 1623 was Christopher Wandesford and Alice Osborne's eldest son and heir; Alice Thornton's brother. Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl of Strafford was his godfather. He attended Trinity College, Dublin from 1636. Accused of taking part in the battle of Marston Moor in July 1644, his estates were sequestered, and so he moved back to live at Hipswell, his mother's property, before fleeing to France for the remainder of the Civil War. He drowned in the River Swale, Yorkshire, through which he was riding on horseback, on 31 March 1651, on the way to visit his unclecousin William Wandesford. His brother Christopher became heir to the family estate.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ww1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">William Wandesford</persName>
               <birth>baptised 26 August 1605</birth>
               <death>1690</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Wandesford (1605-90) was baptised oin 26 August 1605 at Kirklington, the youngest son of Sir George Wandesford by his second wife, Mary Pamplyn. He was Alice Thornton's half-uncle. He married Rebecca Reade and they had a daughter, Catherine. His brother Christopher  sent him to be an apprentice to a London merchant. He was granted an annuity of £20 for life on 30 June 1637 out of his property at Castlecomer, Ireland and paid yearly at Christ's Church, Dublin. He suffered severe losses during the civil war due to his loyalty to the royal cause, and on 31 July 1646 he declared he had been at Oxford when Castlecomer was held for the king, and that he lent money but had not taken up arms. He was made a gentleman-pensioner by Charles II after the Restoration in 1660 and died in 1690 aged 85.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mny1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Mary</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Yorke</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mary Norton Yorke</persName>
               <birth>baptised 12 July 1635</birth>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Norton (1635-xxxx), daughter and fourth child of Maulger Norton and Anne Wandesford, was baptised at Richmond on 12 July 1635; she was Alice eThornton''s cousin. On 20 August 1651 she married John Yorke, a knight of Gouthwaite, later MP for Richmond (1661-63).  They had four children; three sons and a daughter. She became a widow in 1663; and purchased the manor of Beverley in 1675.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jy1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Yorke</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Yorke</persName>
               <birth>c. 1634</birth>
               <death>1 April 1663</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir John Yorke (c. 1634-63) was the son of John Yorke of Gouthwaite and his second wife, Catherine Daniell of Beswick. He was educated at Queen's College, Oxford, matriculating in 1650. On 20 August 1651 he married Mary Norton, daughter of Maulger Norton and Anne Wandesford. He was knighted by Charles II on his Restoration in 1660, and elected MP for Richmond at the Cavalier Parliament the next year, a position he held until his death near London of a pleurisy on 1 April 1663 aged 29. He held several offices during his time as MP. He is buried in St Chad's Church, Middlesmoor in Nidderdale, commemorated by a Latin inscription.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jl1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir, Sheriff of Cumberland, 1st Baronet Lowther</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Lowther</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir John Lowther</persName>
               <birth>20 February 1606</birth>
               <death>30 November 1675</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir John Lowther, 1st Baronet Lowther (1606-75) and Sheriff of Cumberland was born on 20 February 1606 to Sir John Lowther and his wife Eleanor Fleming. He graduated from the Inner Temple in 1621 and was called to the bar in 1630. He married Mary Fletcher, daughter of Richard Fletcher of Hutton, Cumbria, before 1628; they had 11 children – 5 sons and 6 daughters. His second wife was Elizabeth Hare, by whom he had  four4 children, three 3 sons and a daughter. His daughter Eleanor married Christopher Wandesford, Alice Thornton''s brother. John He was twice elected to the constituency of Westmorland, in 1628-29 (with his father) and in 1660. He fought with thefor the royalists during the Civil War. He died on 30 November 1675 and is buried at Lowther Church alongside his father, commemorated by a Latin inscription.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="elw1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Eleanor</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Wandesford</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Lowther</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Eleanor Lowther Wandesford</persName>
               <birth>baptised 23 March 1633</birth>
               <death>buried 20 December 1714</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Eleanor Lowther (1633-1714) (bap. 23 March 1633 at Lowther) was the daughter of John Lowther, 1st Baronet Lowther and his first wife Mary Fletcher, was baptised on 23 March 1633 at Lowtherr. She married Christopher Wandesford on 30 September 1651 at Lowther, making herbecoming Alice Thornton's sister-in-law. Christopher and EleanorThey had nine 9 children, three 3 sons and six 6 daughters. She was buried on 20 December 1714 at Kirklington.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wt1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">William Thornton</persName>
               <birth>baptised 9 June 1624</birth>
               <death>17 September 1668</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Thornton (1624-68), the son of Robert Thornton of East Newton and his second wife Elizabeth Darley, was baptized at Stonegrave church on 9 June 1624 along with his twin brother Richard.. He had a twin brother, Richard. William married Alice Wandesford on 15 December 1651 at Hipswell. They had nine children, of whom three survived to adulthood. William died at Malton on 17 September 1668 andand was buried on 18 September 1668 at at Stonegrave the next day. William's arms are part of the wall ornament in Stonegrave church, in the North Riding of Yorkshire.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ms1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename>Michael</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Syddall</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Michael Syddall</persName>
               <birth>c. 1614</birth>
               <death>buried 8 January 1658</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Michael Syddall (c. 1614-58) was born at York to William Syddall, a baker, and his wife Margaret. He was admitted to Christ's College, Cambridge in 1631 at the age of 16, graduating with his BA in 1635 and MA in 1638. He married Ellen Hunton, who was the widow of the steward of the late Christopher Wandesford. He was minister at St. Michael's, Kirklington, 1644-49 and vicar of St Anne’s, Catterick, from 1645-58. He was buried on 8 January 1658, and buried in the chancel at St Anne’sCatterick. In his will he left money to build a school and he made William Thornton one of four trustees, alongside Richard Brathwaite, author of The English Gentlewoman (1631). His will invested £45 in founding a hospital and a school, and Michael Syddall CE Primary School in Catterick is named after him. was vicar of Catterick.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Unnamed Thornton daughter ?</persName>
               <birth>27 August 1652</birth>
               <death>27 August 1652</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Alice Thornton's first child, an unnamed daughter, was born on 27 August 1652 but only lived for fifteen minutes and so was not baptised. She was buried at Easby Church the next day. Her unnamed brother who died half an hour after his birth in 1657 was buried next to her.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="atc1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Alice (Nally)</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Comber</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Alice Thornton Comber</persName>
               <birth>3 January 1653/16544</birth>
               <death>20 January 1720/17211</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Alice Thornton Comber (1654-1721), nicknamecalled Nally by her mother, was born on 3 Januaryin 1654 to Alice and William Thornton. She was their second child and one of the three Thornton children to survive to adulthood. She married Thomas Comber, later Dean of Durham, in 1668, by whom she had six 6 children, four 4 sons and two 2 daughters. Nally's marriage to ComberThomas was at the centre of the slanders against the Thornton family spearheaded by Nally's cousin-by-marriage, Anne Danby. Nally was only 14 when she married. Other rumours possibly centred on Nally's mother relationship with Comber, who had been living with the family at East Newton since 1665 when he took up the curacy of Stonegrave. She died on 20 January 1721.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mn1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Maulger</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Maulger Norton</persName>
               <birth>baptised 25 March 1593</birth>
               <death>buried 12 December 1673</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Maulger Norton (1593-1673) was baptised on 25 March 1593 at Wath, the first son and heir of Robert Norton of St. Nicholas, Richmond and his wife Catherine Staveley. He was elected MP for Richmond in the Short Parliament of 1640. He married Alice Thornton's aunt Anne Wandesford, by whom he had 65 children, 43 sons and 2 daughters. He was buried at Richmond on 12 December 1673.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="et1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Elizabeth (Betty)</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Elizabeth Thornton</persName>
               <birth>14 February 1654</birth>
               <death>35 September 1656</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth (Betty) Thornton (1654-56)  was (born on 14 February 1654) was to Alice and William Thornton; theirAlice's third , and second surviving, child. She died on 35 September 1656, aged two, after becoming ill with an ague, and was buried at Catterick..</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ca1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename>Charles</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Anthony</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Charles Anthony</persName>
               <birth>1600</birth>
               <death>1685</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles Anthony (ordained 1636)(1600-85) was educated at Jesus College, Cambridge (BA 1624, MA 1627). He was ordained in 1636, and became was became vicar of Catterick in 1660. He baptised Alice's daughter Elizabeth in 1654. He died in 1685 and was buried at Catterick.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="kb1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mrs</roleName>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Blackburne</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Covell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Katherine Blackburne</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Covell Blackburne was the daughter of Roger Covell and Anne Norton. Roger was later one of Alice Thornton's solicitors. Katherine She married Timothy Blackburnee. She stood in for Alice's mother, who was unwell, at the baptism of Alice's daughter, Elizabeth, in 1654. She was still alive in 1696 when she was named executrix in her mother's will.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="edg1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mrs</roleName>
                  <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Thornton</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Gates</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Darley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Elizabeth Darley Thornton Gates</persName>
               <birth>3 October 1597</birth>
               <death>10 May 1655</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth Darley (born 3 October 1597) was the eldest daughter of Sir Richard Darley of Buttercrambe, Yorkshire and his second wife, Elizabeth Gates. She became the second wife of Robert Thornton (c. 1560-1637) c. 1620 and they had seven 7 children, four4 sons and three 3daughters. After his death she married Gefferey Gates on 26 June 1638 at Stonegrave. Her joint- eldest son William Thornton married Alice Wandesfordesford. She died on 10 May 1655 at Oswoldkirk, from a 'voydance of blood' and was buried the next day at Stonegrave.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gg1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Gefferey</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Gates</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Gefferey Gates</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>18 May 1655</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Gefferey Gates (xxxx-1655) was the second husband of Elizabeth Darley Thornton, whom he married on 26 June 1638 at Stonegrave, becoming and the stepfather of Alice Wandesford's Thornton's husband William Thornton. He died just 8 days after his wife, 18 May 1655, and was buried at St. Mary Lowgate, Hull the same next day.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rt1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Richard</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Richard Thornton</persName>
               <birth>9 June 1624</birth>
               <death>3 July 1656</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Richard Thornton (1624-56), baptised 9 June 1624 was the son of Robert Thornton and his second wife Elizabeth Darley, and the twin brother of Alice Thornton's husband William's husband William Thornton. He died unmarried in Dublin, Ireland of a bloody flux on 3 July 1656. He was buried at St Patrick's Church the next day.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ktp1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Purchase</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Danby</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Katherine Thornton Purchase Danby</persName>
               <birth>12 June 1656</birth>
               <death>17 December 1726</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine (Kat, Katy)Katherine Thornton Purchase Danby (1656-1726) was the fourth daughter of Alice Thornton and William Thornton, and the second of two surviving daughters. She was born on 12 June 1656 at Hipswell and baptised the next daya t Stonegrave. She married Thomas Purchase, rector, by arrangement of her brother-in-law Thomas Comber on 17 December 1682, and after his Purchase's death in 1696 April 1697 she married Robert Danby of Northallerton.. She had seven children by Thomas, four sons and three daughters5 children by Thomas, 3 sons and 2 daughters. She died on 17 December 1726 and was buried at Stonegrave.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="kdb1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Katherine (Kitt)</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Best</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Katherine Danby Best</persName>
               <birth>25 May 1637</birth>
               <death>1688</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Danby Best (born 1637-88) was the daughter of to Katherine Wandesford and Thomas Danby; Alice Thornton's niece. She was born on 25 May 1637 at Richmond. She married Henry Best of Middleton Quernhow, a Gray's Inn bBarrister, some time after 1659, and they had two 2 children, Katherine and Henrya son and a daughter. She was eventually sole heiress to her father,She was her husband's  and was his administratrix on 29 January 1673/4, h. His will giving ave her £2,000. She died in 1688.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Unnamed Thornton son ?</persName>
               <birth>1o December 1657</birth>
               <death>10 December 1657</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Alice Thornton's fifth child (1657), an unnamed son, was born on 10 December 1657, but lived only half an hour after a difficult birth. He was buried at Catterick the same day by Michael Syddall in a grave with his unnamed sister, Alice's first born child who died in 1652..</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rw1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wittie</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Dr Robert Wittie</persName>
               <birth>baptised 14 November 1613</birth>
               <death>October 1684</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Wittie (1613-84) was baptised at St. Mary's, Beverley, on 14 November 1613, the son of George Wittie of Beverley and Anne Howard. He studied medicine at King's College, Cambridge, and returned to his native Yorkshire to practice medicine, first at Hull, and from 1651 at the latest, at York. He treated Alice Thornton and her family for various ailments. Wittie wrote at least two books; 'The Antimonial Cup', on emetics, and 'Scarborough Spaw', which extolled the healing virtues of spas.
 HWittie married Mary Hall (d. 1691/2). In 1675, when his mother died, he was resident in the parish of St. Martin's, Coney-street. On his retirement from active profession he moved to London and was incorporated at the Royal College of Physicians on 30 September 1680. He died in October 1684.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="aow1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Alice</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Wandesford</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Osborne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Alice Osborne Wandesford</persName>
               <birth>1593</birth>
               <death>10 December 1659</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Alice Wandesford was born in 1593, the daughter of Hewett  Osborne of Kniveton and Joyce Fleetwood; Alice Thornton's mother. She became was the second wife of Sir Christopher Wandesford, and by him had seven 7 children, of which five 5 survived to adulthood. She joined her husband in Dublin with her young children in 1633, when he accompanied Thomas Wentworth there and became Master of the Rolls. Widowed in December 1640, she and her children fled an extremely hostile Ireland back to northern England, spending from 1644 until her death at her jointure property, Hipswell Hall. She died on 10 December 1659 after falling ill on 17 November, and was buried at Catterick Church.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ps1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                  <forename>Peter</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Samways</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Dr Peter Samways</persName>
               <birth>1615</birth>
               <death>April 1693</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Peter Samways was born at Eltham, Kent, in 1615, the son of a ‘person about the court.’ He was educated at Westminster School and then Trinity College, Cambridge, where he then became one of the college tutors until 1650. During his residence at Cambridge he contributed verses to the university collections royalist poems.
In or before 1657 he became rector of Malden, Bedfordshire, and in 1659 he was chaplain to Elizabeth, countess of Peterborough. He was presented by Lord Salisbury to the vicarage of Cheshunt, Hertfordshire, from which he was expelled by the parliamentary visitors because he persisted in reading the liturgy of the church of England, when he was also deprived of his fellowship at Trinity.
After the Restoration he was created D.D. at Cambridge, by royal mandate, on 5 Sept. 1660, but he was not reinstated in his benefice at Cheshunt, probably because, on 31 Dec. 1660, he was presented to the rectory of Wath, near Ripon, Yorkshire, worth about 140l. per annum, by the Earl of Aylesbury, in whose family he had spent some time during the rebellion. Soon afterwards he was presented by Charles II to the neighbouring rectory of Bedale, worth nearly 600l. a year. It was during the late 1650s and 1660s that Samways appears in Alice's books, attending the final illness of her mother Alice Osborne in December 1659. According to Alice, he was one of the people taken in by the rumours begun by Anne Danby about her daughter Nally's marriage to Thomas Comber in 1668.
He was a great benefactor to the parish of Wath, where he built and endowed a school. On 27 May 1668 he was collated to the prebend of Barneby in the church of York. He was a staunch supporter of the church of England, and it is recorded of him that he boldly disputed the doctrine of transubstantiation with the Duke of York (afterwards James II). He fell under the displeasure of Bishop Cartwright, then administering the see of York, by refusing to subscribe the king's declaration for liberty of conscience in 1688, and he narrowly escaped a second ejection from his benefices. Samways further aided the cause of civil and religious liberty by publishing a letter, which had a considerable effect in persuading the clergy of his neighbourhood to take the oaths to King William and Queen Mary, and for this service he is said to have received an offer of the bishopric of Bath and Wells which he declined. Among his intimate friends were Dr. Isaac Barrow and Archbishops Ussher and Sancroft. He died at Bedale in April 1693. CRIBBED AND ADAPTED FROM ODNB SO NEEDS MORE CHANGING. OR DO WE JUST CREDIT IT.(1615-93) was born in 1615 in Eltham, Kent. He attended Westminster School and then Trinity College Cambridge, where he gained his MA in 1641. He was ordained Deacon of Rochester in 1643. A loyal monarchist, he was nevertheless presented to the rectory of Wath in the North Riding in 1658 on petition to Cromwell. On the Restoration in 1660 he was created Doctor of Divinity at Cambridge, and was made prebendary of Barneby, York in 1668. A friend of Alice Thornton and correspondent of her son-in-law Thomas Comber, he died on 6 April 1693 at Bedale and was buried in the church there.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jk1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Kearton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Kearton</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>buried 18 August 16641662</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Kearton (xxxx-1664) was born at Hipswell. He received his BA from Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge. He was ordained deacon at York in 1628, and priest in the same place in 1629. He was rector of Richmond 1657-62became rector of Richmond in 1657. Alice Osborne Wandesford wanted him to preach at her funeral service in 1659, and in April 1660 he baptised, and then shortly afterwards buried, Alice Thornton's sixth child, William, at Easby. He died in 1662.He was buried on 18 August 1664 at St. Mary Richmond.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="dcl1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Daphne</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Lightfoot</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Cassell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Daphne Cassell Lightfoot</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Daphne Cassell entered the service of Alice Thornton's mother, Alice Wandesford, unmarried, but soon married  became married to George Lightfoot, also in service to Alice seniorwho was also in her service. The couple had at least one child. She was with Alice's sister Katherine when she died after childbirth in 1645 and prayed with Alice's mother at her death bed in 1659. She and her husband were witnesses to Alice's mothers will. 
Daphne was a close friend and confidante of Alice's throughout the events Alice discusses in her books. She breastfed Alice's child Elizabeth for three months in 1654 when Alice was unable to produce milk. She also helped Alice with the inventory of her house when her husband died in 1668, and was also a staunch defender of Alice'sdefended her and her family staunchly during the rumours that spread about the Thornton-Comber marriage the same year.the Danby scandal which was happening at the same time.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cd2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lord, 1st Earl Holderness</roleName>
                  <forename>Conyers</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Darcy</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Conyers Darcy, Lord Darcy and Conyers</persName>
               <birth>24 January 1598</birth>
               <death>14 June 1689</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Conyers Darcy, 1st  Earl  of  Holdernesse, 8th Lord Darcy de Knayth (1598-1689) was born on 24 January 1598 to Sir Conyers Darcy and Dorothy Belasyse. He was constable of Middleham Castle, Yorkshire, and created Earl of Holdernesse on 6 Decemeber 1682,  with  remainder  to  the  heirs  male  of  his body.. Circa  1619 he married Grace,  only  daughter  and  heir  of  Thomas Rokeby,  of  Skyers,  Yorks. They had six 6 sons and five 5 daughters, only one of the sons, Conyers, surviving childhood, but only one son, Conyers, survived childhood.. He died on 14 June, 1689.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ha1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Hanna(h)?</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Ableson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Hannah Ableson</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Hannah Ableson was a servant in Alice's household.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ra1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir; Lord</roleName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Adair</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Robert Adair</persName>
               <birth>1583</birth>
               <death>1 March 1655</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir  Robert  Adair,  of  Ballymenna and Kinhilt , co.  Antrim(1583-1655) ,  who  waswas born in 1583 to Sir William Adair and  Rosina McLelland. He was  served heir  to  his  father  and  grandfather,  in  the  Scotch  estates on  February 19 1629. He was knighted by Charles I and became a Royalist soldier, before switching to the Scottish parliamentarians and became a major in the Earl of Leven's Horse Regiment.  He married Jane   of  William  Edmondstone, and they had 2 sons and a daughter,  of  Duntreath, co.  Stirling. He died on 1  March,  1655,  and was succeeded by his eldest son.
Adair is mentioned in Thornton's first book by Captain Innes, a Scottish soldier who wished to marry Alice. In order to persuade Alice's mother to agree he offered money</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ga1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>George</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Anderson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">George Anderson</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Anderson, a Scotsman, was a tutor for Alice's brother George in France when he fled there after being sequestered after the battle of Marston Moor in 1644.during the Civil War.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cda1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>KCatherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Armitage</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Catherine Danby Armitage</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>buried 13 January 1666</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">KCatherine Danby Armitage was the oldest daughter and second child of Thomas Danby of Farnley, Leeds and Elizabeth Wentworth. She married Francis Armiytage in, later 1st Baronet,  1629 – he was created Baronet by Charles I in 1641in 1629. They had at least 11 children, five 5 of whom, three 3sons and two 2 daughters, can be identified. A widow from 1644, she attended Katherine Wandesford Danby, her sister-in-law, on her death bed in September 1645. She was buried on 13 January 1666.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wa1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Ayscough</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">William Ascough</persName>
               <birth>9 March 1648</birth>
               <death>buried 20 November 1676</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Ayscough of Osgoodby (1648-76)  was (born on 9 March 1648 to ) was the son of Sir William Ayscough and Judith Burgoyne. He (or perhaps his father) was one of the coffin bearers at William Thornton's funeral in September 1668, and he married Alice Thornton's sister-in-law, Ann (or Dorothy?) Thornton, in 1675/76. He died within a year of marriage and was buried on 20 November 1676 at Thirkleby.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ja1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Captain</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Ashton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Ashton</persName>
               <birth>c. 1614</birth>
               <death>1643</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Captain John Ashton (c. 1614-43), born c. 1614, was the son of Radclyffe Ashton of Cuerdale and Elizabeth Hyde. He married Ann Shuttleworth and they had one son. He was Captain of the Foot during the first English civil war 1642-46.the Civil War. When When Alice Thornton and her family fled Ireland in 1641, it was Ashton who provided them with safe passage back home to Yorkshire from Lancashire. He died at Bristol in 1643 from wounds sustained at the Battle of Edge Hill in October 1642.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xa1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Atie</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Dr Atie</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dr Atie appears briefly in Alice's account of her mother's death, being sent to her, perhaps as a deputy, by Dr Wittie who could not attend her deathbed.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Bathurst</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Bathurst</persName>
               <birth>c. 1596</birth>
               <death>19 April 1659</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Bathurst (born c. 1596)c. 1596-1659) matriculated from Pembroke College Cambridge in 1614 and became a Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians in 1637. He was incorporated at Oxford in 1643, and acted as physician to Oliver Cromwell. He was MP for Richmond in 1656 and 1658. He married Elizabeth Willance on 27 January 1635/36. Alice Thornton's mother sent her son Christopher to Dr. Bathurst at York when he suffered a distemper from grief over his father's death in November 1643, and her brother John was likewise sent to him when he dropped out of Cambridge University and moved to London in a state of melancholy. He died oin 19 April 1659.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mb2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                  <forename>Martha</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Batte</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Martha Batte</persName>
               <birth>before baptised 299 September 1636</birth>
               <death>28 April 1668</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Martha Batte (1636-68) was the daughter of John Batte and Martha Mallory. She was baptised at Birstall, Yorkshire on 296 September 1636. She went to America with her father and brothers where they partook in the slave trade.She and her father and brothers emigrated to a Virginian plantation, where they kept slaves.  
By 1667 she was back in Yorkeshire in the service of the Countess of Sussex at Howley Hall. She was a friend of Alice Thornton's niece-by-marriage, Anne Danby, from their time in Virginia. According to Alice, Anne wanted to prevent the marriage of Thomas Comber and Nally Thornton in order for Thomas to marry Martha. Martha died on 28in April 1668.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="hb1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Henry</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Best</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Henry Best</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>January 1674</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Henry Best (xxxx-1674) was the son of George Best of Middleton Quernhow and Grace Darcy. He married Katherine Danby, Alice Thornton’s niece, after 1659, and was referred to by Alice as 'my nephew Best'. He had two children by Katherine, also called Henry and Katherine. He wasA a barrister at Gray’s Inn, he. He died there 1674.in January 1674.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tb2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Binks</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Thomas Binks</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Binks was a poor man who warned Alice Thornton that Jeremy Smithson was plotting to abduct her after Alice refused his hand in marriage.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Mr</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Binlows</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mr Binlows</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Binlows was one of the ministers attendant at Alice Thornton's mother's funeral in 1659.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb5">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Borlase</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Borlase</persName>
               <birth>c. 1576</birth>
               <death>1648</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir John Borlase (c. 1576-1648) was born c. 157born6 in Cornwall to Edward Borlase and Suszannah Isham. He attended Cambridge University, but did not graduate, and then pursued a military career. He fought extensively in the Low Countries in the early 17th century, becoming master-general of the ordnance of Ireland in 1634, and became Lord Justice of Ireland after the death of Christopher Wandesford in 1640 along with Sir William Parsons. He married Alice Ravis, widow of Thomas Ravis, bishop of London, and they had three sons. He died in 1648.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb4">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Bishop of Derry</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Bramhall</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Bramhall</persName>
               <birth>baptised 18 November 1594</birth>
               <death>25 June 1663</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Bramhall (born November 1594-1663): baptised 18 November 1594, was one of six children of Peter Bramhall of Carleton, Pontefract. He graduated with a BA from Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge in 1612, and was ordained in York in 1615. On 24 June 1618, Christopher Wandesford presented him to the rectory of South Kilvington, near Thirsk. On 10 November he married a clergyman's widow, Ellen Collingwood (née Halley). The couple had 6 children, 3 sons and 3 daughters. Wandesford and Thomas Wentworth helped Bramhall secure the prebend of Huisthwaite, Yorkshire in 1632. He became Bishop of Derry, in Ireland, in May 1634, and was present at Christopher Wandesford's deathbed in 1640. 
After Wandesford's death he was exiled and had returned to his native Yorkkshire by 1642; and was restored in Ireland by Charles II in 1660. He died on 25 Junein 1663.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb6">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Colonel</roleName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Brandlingen</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Cousin Branlen?</persName>
               <birth>c. 1620</birth>
               <death>1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Along with Alice Thornton and Lord Loftus, Cousin Branlen is listed as a witness to the baptism? of Alice Thornton's sister Katherine Danby's first son Francis at Middleham Castle in 1644.Robert Brandling (c. 1620-69) was</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mb1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Mary</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Breakes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mary Breakes</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Breakes was a servant in Alice Thornton's household. Mary was implicated by Anne Danby and others in spreading rumours about Alice and Nally Thornton in summer 1668.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wb1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Brereton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir William Brereton</persName>
               <birth>13 September 1604</birth>
               <death>7 April 1661</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir William Brereton, 1st Baronet, (1604–1661), was an English Puritan who owned extensive estates in Cheshire, and Member of Parliament for Cheshire county at various times between 1628 and 1653. During the First English Civil War, he was commander of Parliamentarian forces in the North Midlands. He married twice; firstly, Susanna Booth, by whom he had four children, 3 daughters and a son; and after her death Cicely Mytton, a wealthy Staffordshire widow, by whom he had two more daughters.
When Christopher Wandesford's family, including a teenage Alice, fled Ireland after his death in 1640 and landed in Cheshire, they were held up on their way home to Yorkshire at Chester due to Brereton's Parliamentary forces. 
When the Civil War ended in 1646, Brereton gave up his local offices, and although nominated as a judge, refused to attend the trial of Charles I in January 1649. He was elected to the Council of State in 1652 and 1653 but rarely attended, living in semi-retirement in London. He resumed his seat for Cheshire when the Long Parliament was reinstated in 1659, until its dissolution in March 1660, and died on 7 April 1661.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tb1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Brockill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Thomas Brockill</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Brockill, or Brockhall, born in Richmond and educated at St John's, Cambridge (BA 1639), was vicar of St. Mary, Hornby, from 1650-69. He was one of the ministers who conducted Alice Osborne Wandesford's funeral service in 1659.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>James</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Brodricke</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">James Brodricke</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">James Brodricke was Alice's brother George Wandesford's footman.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="bb1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Browne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Benjamin Browne</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Benjamin Browne came with Dr Samways to Alice and William Thornton's house at East Newton to take the sacrament in 1662. He was possibly related to Alice Thornton.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Joseph</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Browning</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Joseph Browning</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Joseph Browning was a coachman who was driving a carriage containing Alice Thornton, her parents and siblings in October 1636. They were heading to Kildare, west of Dublin. The carriage was overturned on a narrow pass by a river but mercifully all passengers survived.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb7">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mrs</roleName>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Bucke</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mrs Bucke</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mrs Bucke was possibly a servant in Alice Thornton's household or a local woman, who advised Alice on the pearl in her daughter Nally's eye which appeared after she had recovered from small pox in April 1667.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb5">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Bullock</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Cousin Bullock</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">'Cousin Bullock' is listed as a bearer of William Thornton's coffin at his funeral on 18 September 1668. He was probably a descendant of Launcelot Bullock of Holme and Margaret Thornton, the daughter of William Thornton's great grandmother, making him a cousin-by-marriage to Alice Thornton.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb4">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Burrage</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mr Burrage</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Burrage or Berridge was involved in the murder of Alice Thornton's nephew Thomas Danby, allegedly over a pawned sword, near Gray's Inn, London in August 1667.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb6">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>1st Earl of Ormond</roleName>
                  <forename>James</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Butler</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">James Butler</persName>
               <birth>19 October 1610</birth>
               <death>21 July 1688</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">James Butler (born 19 October 1610) to Thomas Butler and Elizabeth Pointz was an Anglo-Irish statesman and first Earl of Ormond. He married Elizabeth Preston at Christmas 1629, by whom he had ten children; three sons and two daughters surviving to adulthood. He was brought to Ireland by Thomas Wentworth, earl of Strafford as head of government in Ireland in 1633 and was present at the meal where Christopher Wandesford, Alice Thornton's father became unwell in 1640, dying soon afterwards. He witnessed Wandesford's will. He commanded the Royalist forces in Ireland during the Civil War of the 1640s and subsequent Cromwellian invasion, and Alice mentions his becoming Lord Lieutenant of Ireland on the Restoration of Charles II in 1660. He died at his estate at Kingston Lacey, Dorset, on 21 July 1688.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wc1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>1st Duke of Newcastle upon Tyne</roleName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Cavendish</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">William Cavendish</persName>
               <birth>baptised 16 December 1593</birth>
               <death>25 December 1676</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Cavendish, 1st Duke of Newcastle upon Tyne was born in December 1693 to Charles Cavendish and his second wife Catherine Ogle, their second but first surviving son. A writer, courtier and royalist army officer, he led his battalion, the Whitecoats, under the Royalist forces of Prince Rupert at the battle of Marston (Hessom) Moor in 1644. The Royalist army suffered a huge defeat, and the Whitecoats lost some 4,000 troops. Alice notes the tragedy of the loss and their bravery in Book 1. Cavendish died at Welbeck Abbey on Christmas Day 1676.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ksc1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lady</roleName>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Cholmley</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Stanhope</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Katherine Stanhope Cholmley</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>1657</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Stanhope Cholmley was married to Lord Robert Cholmley. Alice lists them, along with others, as friendly and helpful neighbours of the family when they returned to England from Ireland in the early 1640s, staying for some time in Cheshire before heading back to Yorkshire. She died in 1657.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rc4">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lord; First Earl of Leinster</roleName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Cholmley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Robert Cholmley</persName>
               <birth>26 June 1584</birth>
               <death>8 October 1659</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Cholmley (born 26 June 1584) was the son of Hugh Cholmley and Mary Holford. He married Katherine Stanhope. They had no children. He was MP for Cheshire in 1625. Alice lists Lord and Lady Cholmley, along with others, as friendly and helpful neighbours of the family when they returned to England from Ireland in the early 1640s, staying for some time in Cheshire before heading back to Yorkshire. He was made Earl of Leinster in 1646. He died on 8 October 1659.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="uc1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Ursula</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Cholmley</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Ursula Cholmley</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ursula Cholmley (nee Thornton) was the eldest daughter of Robert Thornton and his first wife, Dorothy Metham. She was William Thorton's half-sister. She married Marmaduke Cholmley of Bransby and they had a son and two daughters. Alice Thornton called her 'my sister Cholmley'. William Thornton, on his way home from York to East Newton, stopped at Bransby Hall when he became ill with a palsy in November 1665.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="kc1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Twisleton</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Cholmley</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Stapleton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Katherine Cholmley</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>14 June 1672</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Stapleton (born c. 1607) was the daughter of Henry Stapleton of Wighill and Mary Forster. She married George Twisleton, who died c. 1635, and then married Henry Cholmley. They had one daughter, Henrietta. She was godmother to Alice Thornton's son, Robert, baptised in September 1662. She was buried on 14 June 1672.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jc2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Clotworthy</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir John Clotworthy</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>September 1665</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Clotworthy, 1st Viscount Massereene was an Anglo-Irish politician, son of Sir Hugh Clotworthy and Mary Langford of county Antrim. He was knighted in 1626 and married Margaret Jones, daughter of Viscount Ranelagh. They had one daughter, Mary. He was a presbyterian and opponent of Thomas Wentworth during his time as Lord Deputy of Ireland. He died in September 1665.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tc1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Comber</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Thomas Comber</persName>
               <birth>1645</birth>
               <death>25 November 1699</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Comber (born 1645-99) was the son of James Comber and Mary Burton of Westerham, Kent. He was</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mc1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Mary</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Cotes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mary Cotes</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Cotes was probably a servant in Alice Thornton's household who, with Hanna Ableson, cared for her daughter Katherine in September 1666 when she had the small pox.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rc2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Roger</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Covell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Roger Covell</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>12 July 1664</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Roger Covell was a solicitor based at Fremlington. He was admitted to Inner Temple in 1629 and called to the bar in 1639. He was Alice Thornton's cousin-by-marriage since he was married to Anne Norton (which one?). He also acted as Alice and William Thornton's solicitor: he settled William's estate in 1662. He was buried on 12 July 1664.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jc1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Crathorne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Crathorne</persName>
               <birth>c. 1642</birth>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Crathorne (born c. 1634-xxxx) was the son of Ralph Crathorne and his second wife Margaret Thornton, William Thornton's half-sister. He was a pall-bearer at William's funeral in 1666 along with his brother Ralph.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mtc1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Margaret</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Crathorne</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Margaret Thornton Crathorne</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Margaret Thornton Crathorne was the daughter of Robert Thornton and his first wife Dorothy Metham. She was William Thornton's half-sister. Around 1632 she became the second wife of Ralph Crathorne of Crathorne, and they had three sons.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rc1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Ralph</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Crathorne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Ralph Crathorne</persName>
               <birth>c. 1634</birth>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ralph Crathorne (born c. 1634-xxxx) was the first son of Ralph Crathorne of Crathorne and his second wife Margaret Thornton, William Thornton's half-sister. He married Anne Tunstall, and they had three sons. He was a pall-bearer at his uncle William Thornton's funeral in 1668.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="oc1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Oliver</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Cromwell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Oliver Cromwell</persName>
               <birth>25 April 1599</birth>
               <death>3 September 1658</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Oliver Cromwell (born 25 April 1599-1658), born 25 April 1599, was Lord Protector of England, Wales and Ireland during the Interregnum period of 1649 until his death in 1658. Born to Robert Cromwell and Elizabeth Steward, he was educated at Sidney Sussex College Cambridge and married Elizabeth Bourchier in 1621. They had nine children; five sons and four daughters. He died on 3 September 1658.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rc3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Richard</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Cromwell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Richard Cromwell</persName>
               <birth>4 October 1626</birth>
               <death>12 July 1712</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Richard Cromwell (born 4 October 1626-1712): born 4 October 1626 was the third son, and fourth child, of Oliver Cromwell and Elizabeth Bourchier. On his father's death in September 1658 he was elected Lord Protector of England, a position he held until 1659, when the Protectorate collapsed. He married Dorothy Maijor on 1 May 1649, and they had nine children, only 4 who survived to adulthood. He died on 12 July 1712.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rd2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Daggett</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Robert Dagett</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>19 August 1644</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Daggett of Howe studied at Sidney Sussex College Cambridge then went to Oxford soon after in 1612. He became Rector of Kirklington in April 1639. Alice Thornton and her family stayed with him at Kirklington in 1644, unable to get to York or their home at Hipswell due to the ongoing Civil War. He died shortly after this on 19th August 1644.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="acd1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mrs</roleName>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Danby</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Culpeper</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Anne Culpepper Danby</persName>
               <birth>16 September 1630</birth>
               <death>11 November 1695</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Culpeper was born on 16 September 1630 in Hollingbourne, Kent, to Thomas Culpeper and Katherine St. Leger. to John Culpeper. Circa 1652 she married Christopher Danby, son of Katherine Wandesford and Thomas Danby and Alice Thornton's nephew, making here Alice's niece-in-law. The Culpeper and Danby families were early settlers in colonial Maryland, and, according to Alice Thornton, Christopher's father did not approve of the match. By the time their first son Abstrupus was born in 1655 they had moved back to Yorkshire, and a daughter, Francilia, followed in 1659. By the late 1660s Anne Danby was living with Alice Thornton and her family at East Newton, and in 1668, according to Alice, was responsible for the slanders that had been spread regarding the marriage of Alice's daughter Nally to Thomas Comber, resulting in her being kicked out of the house by William Thornton. She died on 11 November 1695 and was buried at t York.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ad1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Alice</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Alice Danby</persName>
               <birth>22 May 1641</birth>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Alice Danby (1641-xxxx), born 22 May 1641 at Greenwich, was the daughter of Thomas Danby and Katherine Wandesford, and was Alice Thornton's niece.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cd1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Francilia (Celia)</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Goodrich</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Parker</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Celia Danby</persName>
               <birth>1659</birth>
               <death>1696</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Francilia (Celia) Danby, (born 1659-96), was the daughter of Christopher Danby and Anne Culpeper; Alice Thornton's great-niece. Although born and brought up in Yorkshire, she moved back to colonial Maryland where her parents had met, and married Joseph Goodrich in or around 1685. They had two sons before his death in 1694. She married Thomas Parker in 1694 and died around 1696.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cd4">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Christopher Danby</persName>
               <birth>30 July 1632 or November 1633</birth>
               <death>168995</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Danby (1632-89born 1632/33) was the second son of Thomas Danby and Katherine Wandesford born on 30 July 1632 at St-Martin-in-the-Fields, London; and  Alice Thornton's nephew. After his mother's death in 1645 the family emigrated to Maryland and around 1652 he married Anne Culpeper without his father's permission. Christopher and Anne moved back to Yorkshire and had two children, a son and a daughter.  Abstrupus (b. 1655) and Francilia (b. 1659). On his older brother Thomas's murder at Grays Inn in 1667, he became heir to his father's estate, but granted this estate to his son Abstrupus in the same year. He died in 168995.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cd5">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Charles</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Charles Danby</persName>
               <birth>26 June 1643</birth>
               <death>April 16721672</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles Danby (born 6 June 1643-72) was the son of Thomas Danby and Katherine Wandesford, born on 2nd June 1643 at Snape; and Alice Thornton's nephew. He was admitted to Gray's Inn in 166/64, and died without issue in April 1672.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fd2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Francis</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Francis Danby*</persName>
               <birth>164422 March 1640 (or 41?)</birth>
               <death>9 July 16451644</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Francis Danby (1640-45) (born 1644) was the 615th live born child of Thomas Danby and Katherine Wandesford. Born at Middleham Castle, he died shortly after birth. Their next son born the year after was named Francis after him.He was born at Farnley on 22 March 1640 (or is this 1641?) and died on the 9th of July 1645 aged 5 (or 4?). His brother born the next month was named after him.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="med1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Madam</roleName>
                  <forename>Margaret</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Danby</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Eure</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Margaret Eure Danby</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Margaret Danby Eure was the daughter of William, 6th6th Lord Eure and Margaret Denton. She married Thomas Danby, son of Thomas Danby and Katherine Wandesford, in 1659. They had three children. Margaret was Alice Thornton's niece-in-law. Referred to as 'Madam Danby' in Alice's books, it was Alice's intervention in Margaret's conflicts with her sister-in-law Anne Danby that perhaps led to the slanders against Alice and Nally Thornton by Anne Danby in 1668.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="td3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir Thomas Danby</persName>
               <birth>1610</birth>
               <death>5 August 1660</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Thomas Danby (born c. 1610-60) was the son of Christopher Danby of Farnley and Frances Parker. He was knighted Sheriff of York in 1625, and elected MP for Richmond in 1640; banned from sitting in Parliament after 1642 and was fined heavily for his loyalty to Charles. He married Katherine Wandesford, by whom he had sixteen children, ten of whom survived to adulthood. He was Alice Thornton's brother-in-law. After Alice's death in 1645 he relocated to colonial New England where he held lands, moving back to Yorkshire He held lands in colonial New England, in the 1650s. He and died in York on 5 Augustin 1660.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="td4">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Thomas Danby</persName>
               <birth>1631</birth>
               <death>1667</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Danby (born 1631-67) was the oldest son of Sir Thomas Danby and Katherine Wandesford, and; Alice Thornton's nephew. He married Margaret Eure in 1659, and they had three children. In 1660 he became MP for Malton and in 1661-612 he was became the first Mayor of Leeds. He was killed in a tavern brawl in London in 1667, and his brother Christopher became heir to the Danby family estate.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cd3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>2ndnd  Earl Holdernesse; Baron Conyers</roleName>
                  <forename>Conyers</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Darcy</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Conyers Darcy ?</persName>
               <birth>1622</birth>
               <death>13 December 1692</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Conyers Darcy, 2ndnd Earl Holdernesse (born 1622-92) was the son and heir of Conyers Darcy, 1st  1st Earl Holdernesse and Grace Rokeby. He married four times: to Catherine Fane, Frances Howard, Frances Seymour and Elizabeth Frescheville. With Frances Howard he had six 6 children, 3 sons and 3 daughters. Elected MP for Boroughbridge in 1660, becoming a peer in 1680, as Baron Conyers. He died on 13 December 1692.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="dbd1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Dorothy</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Darcy</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Bellasis</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Dorothy Bellasis Darcy</persName>
               <birth>1572</birth>
               <death>11 May 1653</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dorothy Bellasis (born 1572-1653) was the daughter of Henry Bellasis and Ursula Fairfax. She married Conyers Darcy, 4th , 4th Lord Conyers, in 1594, with whom she had 12 children, 6 sons and 6 daughters. She died on 11 May 1653 in Hornby.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="hd1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Henry</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Darcy</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Henry Darcy</persName>
               <birth>1610</birth>
               <death>28 April 1662</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Henry Darcy (cborn c. 1610-62) was the third son of Conyers Darcy, 4thy, 4th Lord Conyers and Dorothy Bellasis. He married Mary Scrope in 1628, and they had 10 children. He died on 28 April 1662, and was buried at St. Olave's, York.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>James</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Darcy</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">James Darcy</persName>
               <birth>August 1617</birth>
               <death>1673</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">James Darcy was the sixth son of Conyers Darcy, 4th , 4th Lord Conyers and Dorothy Bellasis. He married Isabel Wyvill. They seven children, three sons and four daughters. He died in 1673.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fd3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Francis</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Darley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Francis Darley</persName>
               <birth>1605</birth>
               <death>1679</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Francis Darley (born 1605-79) was the son Sir Richard Darley of Buttercrambe, Yorkshire and his second wife, Elizabeth Gates. He was William Thornton's uncle, the younger brother of Elizabeth Darley Thornton Gates. He was an executor of Alice Osborne Wandesford's mother's will in 1659. He died in 1679.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rd1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Richard</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Darley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Richard Darley</persName>
               <birth>c. 1602</birth>
               <death>2 February 1680/81</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Richard Darley (born( c. 1602-81) was the third son Sir Richard Darley of Buttercrambe, Yorkshire and Elizabeth Gates. He was William Thornton's uncle, a younger brother of Elizabeth Darley Thornton Gates. He married Elizabeth Hildyard, the niece of Catherine Hansby, Alice Thornton's great-grandmother. Elizabeth and Richard and they had six children, five sons and a daughter.  He died on 2 February 1680/81.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ddl1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Don de Lan</forename>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Don de Lan</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Don de Lan was a French page in the service of Robert Meredith, Chancellor of the Irish Exchequer. When dining at Sir Robert's in Dublin in 1637, Dan de Lon swung Alice too hard and she fell on the floor.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="etd1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Denton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Elizabeth Thornton Denton</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>14 February 1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth Thornton (xxxx-1669) was the first child of Robert Thornton and his second wife, Elizabeth Darley;, and William Thornton's older sister and Alice Thornton's sister-in-law. She married John Denton, minister of Oswaldkirk, on 8 May 1654 at East Newton. They had 2 sons. She was buried on 14 February 1669.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Denton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Denton</persName>
               <birth>c. 1626</birth>
               <death>January 1414 January 1709</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Denton (born c. 1626-1709) studied at Clare College Cambridge, gaining his MA in 1653. He became minister of Oswaldkirk in 1654. The same year he married Elizabeth Thornton, older sister of William Thornton. He was ejected from Oswaldkirk in 1662 for noncomformity, after which he served as curate at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave, under Alice Thornton's future son-in-law Thomas Comber.  Elizabeth Thornton died in 1669 and Denton remarried. His second wife Elizabeth (surname unknown)  died in 1715. With Elizabeth Thornton he had 1 or two 2 sons, and with his second wife, also Elizabeth, he had two 2 sons and two 2 daughters. He died on January 14 1709 and was buried on 16 January in the north aisle ofat East NewtonStonegrave..</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Denton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Denton</persName>
               <birth>baptised 5 September 1655</birth>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Denton ((born 1655-xxxx) was the son of John Denton and Elizabeth Thornton, baptised on 5 September 1655. He was the cousin of William Thornton. He was baptised at Oswaldkirk, and attended Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge, where he received his BA in 1677.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wd1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>William (Willy)</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Denton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">William Denton</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William (Willy)(nicknamed Willy) Denton was a son of John Denton and Elizabeth Thornton.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd4">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>James</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Dillon</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">James Dillon</persName>
               <birth>c. 1600</birth>
               <death>after 1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir James Dillon (born c. 1600-c. 1669) was the youngest son of Theobald, 1st Viscount Dillon and Eleanor Tuite. An army officer, he became Commissioner of Ireland in 1627, and was elected MP for Co. Westmeath in 1634. Commissioned by Charles I in 1640 to recruit regiments from disbanded soldiers in Ireland, he was said to have been involved in the 1641 plot to seize Dublin castle. He married twice, first Elizabeth Plunkett in the 1630s, with whom he had two children, Ulick and James. Elizabeth died before 1653. His second marriage, in the early 1660s, was to Mary Ridge, a childless widow. He died no earlier thanafter 1669.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd5">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Dodsworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Dodsworth</persName>
               <birth>1617</birth>
               <death>1662</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Dodsworth (born 1617-62) was the son of John Dodsworth of Thornton Watlass and Frances Hutton, was; Alice's Thornton's cousin. : Alice's great-great-grandfather George Bowes of Streatlam was John's great-grandfather. He was also related to Alice by marriage; since he married Frances Lowther, aunt of Alice's sister-in-law, Christopher's wife Eleanor. John and Frances had two children, John and Helen. He died in 1662.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xe1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Edrington</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mr Edrington</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Edrington who attended Alice Osborne Wandesford's funeral may be the vicar of Langton who graduated from St. John's Cambridge in 1644; or a William Etherington who was instituted at St. Agatha's, Gilling, in 1665.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="kf1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mrs</roleName>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Farrer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Katherine Farrer</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Farrer was a friend of Anne Danby whom Anne tried to set up with Thomas Comber to prevent a match with Alice Thornton's daughter Alice (Nally) Thornton. HeAnne Danby'sr letter to Parson Farrer, also mentioned in Alice's books, indicates that Katherine is a relation of his.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gf1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>George</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">FerraroFarrer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">George Ferraro</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Ferraro or Farrer or Ferraro was probably the minister of Thornton Watlass, made rector of St. Mary the Virgin in 1635. He may have studied at Alban Hall, Oxford in 1625 ,or he may have studied at Cambridge.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ef1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Edward</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Fleetwood</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Edward Fleetwood</persName>
               <birth>c. 1534</birth>
               <death>12 October 1604</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edward Fleetwood (c. 1534-1604) was the son of Thomas Fleetwood and his second wife Bridget Spring. He was the brother of Alice Thornton's maternal grandmother, Joyce Fleetwood. He studied at Oxford, and married Christian Wentworth. The couple had at least 4 children. Heand was instituted rector of Wigan in 1571; a position he held until his death on 12 October 1604. He was the brother of Alice Thornton's maternal grandmother, Joyce Fleetwood.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mf1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Miles</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Fleetwood</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir Miles Fleetwood</persName>
               <birth>baptised 1 October 1576</birth>
               <death>8 March 16411641</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Miles Fleetwood of Aldwinkle (1576-1641), was baptised on 1 October 1576. He was the nephew of Alice Thornton's maternal grandmother Joyce, by her brother William Fleetwood and Joan Clifton. He was MP in several constituencies across England in the 1620s and 1630s, and was elected MP for Hindon, Wiltshire, in the Short Parliament of 1640, which he held until his death in 1641. Alice here confuses him with her maternal great-grandfather, Thomas Fleetwood. He died in 1641.on 8 March 1641.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jf2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Jane</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Flouer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Jane Flouer</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Jane Flouer was a servant in Alice's household.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jf1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Frescheville</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Frescheville</persName>
               <birth>16064 December 1607</birth>
               <death>31 March 1682</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Frescheville, first Baron Frescheville (1606-82), was  was the son of Sir Peter Frescheville and his first wife, Joyce Fleetwood. He was Alice Thornton's uncle, the younger half-brother of her mother Alice Osborne Wandesford. He was educated at Magdalen Hall Oxford and the Middle Temple (1624). He married twice; firstly Bruce Nicholls, who died in 1629 without issue and then Sarah Harington with whom he had  three 3 daughters. He was elected MP for Derbyshire in 1628, though this ended a year later when Charles I decided to rule without parliamentabolished parliament. He was Lieutenant of Derbyshire from 1630-42, and then became a Captain in the Royalist army. He was created Baron in 1665 and died without male heir to inherit his baronetcy on 31 March 1682.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pf1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Peter</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Frescheville</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir Peter Frescheville</persName>
               <birth>baptised 14 March 15675</birth>
               <death>7 April 1634</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Peter Frescheville (baptised 14 March 1575-1634): baptised 14 March 1575, was the eldest son of Peter Frescheville of Staveley and his second wife Margaret Kaye. He sat in the House of Commons as MP for Derbyshire in 1601 and in 1621-22, and built Staveley Hall in 1604. He married twice, first Joyce Fleetwood, widow of Hewett Osborne, with whom he had  three3 children, a son and two 2 daughters; and secondly Isabel Neville who died without issue. His marriage to Joyce made him Alice Thornton's maternal step-grandfather. He died on 9 April 1634 and was buried at Staveley.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="sg1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Susanna</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Graham</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Washington</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Susanna Graham</persName>
               <birth>15 January 1618</birth>
               <death>26 February 1699</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Susanna Washington Grahame (born 15 January 16181618-99) was the daughter of William Washington and Anne Villiers, born on 15th January 1618. She married Ranald (Reginald) Graham of Lewisham c. 1640. The couple purchased Nunnington Hall in Ryedale in 1655, and Ranald He became Justice of the Peace of the North Riding of Yorkshire in 1662. This2, and this would have brought herbrought Susanna into the social circle of Alice Thornton, who counted her as a friend. She was godmother to Alice's youngest daughter and eighth child Joyce, born in 1665. She also gave Alice advice on medicine, and sent a carriage to take away Anne Danby from the Thornton house at East Newton to York after the scandal of 1668. She died on 26 February 1699 and was buried in the parish church at Lewisham.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jh1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Joseph</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Hall</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Joseph Hall</persName>
               <birth>1574</birth>
               <death>8 September 1656</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Joseph Hall (born 1574-1656) was the son of John Hall and Winifred Bambridge. He was a religious writer, satirist, and became Bishop of Exeter, and Norwich. He married Elizabeth Winniff in 1603 with whom he had eight 8 children,  six 6 sons and two 2 daughters. He died on 8 September 1656.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xh1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Hubert</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mr Hubert</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Hubert, a man of Skerries, Dublin, sent ships boats to assist the Wandesford family's ship during a perilous crossing of the Irish Sea back to Dublin in 1639. Hubert had previously been helped by Christopher Wandesford as Justice of the Peace, who had decided a law suit in his favour.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ah1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Hutton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Anne Hutton</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Hutton may be the daughter of Thomas Wentworth's sister Margaret and her husband Richard Hutton. Alice describes her as a 'cousin' – a kinship that could be claimed via great-great-grandfather George Bowes, to whom the Wandesfords and Huttons were related.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xi1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Captain</roleName>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Innes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Captain Innes</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Captain Innes is aAn unidentified officer in the Scottish army who was stationed at Alice's mother's property after the battle of Hessom Moor in summer 1644. He pursued Alice aggressively for her hand in marriage and even plotted to abduct her with his men at one point. Possibly the same a John Innis who fought at the Battle of Dunbar in 1650.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rj1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Ralph</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Janson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Ralph Janson</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ralph Janson of Thorpe was present at the wedding of Alice and William Thornton in 1651. He and Alice had previously nearly drowned crossing the Swale on the a journey to Alice's aunt Anne Norton's's house at St Nicholas in 1646.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tj1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Jenney</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Thomas Jenney</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Jenney was implicated in the murder of Alice Thornton's nephew Thomas Danby at Gray's Inn in 1667, but was pardoned and released from jail in October 1667.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jl2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Lambert</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Lambert</persName>
               <birth>7 September 1619</birth>
               <death>1 March 1684</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Lambert (born 7 September 16191619-84) was born on 7th September 1619  was the son toof Josias Lambert and his second or third wife, Anne Heber or Anne Piggott. He was a Parliamentarian general during the English Civil War. He married Frances Lister on 10 September 1639, and they had ten 10 children, three t of whom survived to adulthood. He died on 1 March 1684.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="el1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Ed(ward) (mund)</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Lassells</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Edward? Lassells</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edward or Edmund Lassells was a coffin-bearer at the funeral of William Thornton in September 1668. Alice describes him as a cousin: her paternal aunt Eleanor Wandesford had married George Lassells, and so this Edward/ or Edmund may have been a descendant of theirs. Perhaps the same  An Edward Lassells who was buried on 22 August 1675 at St. Michael- le- Belfrey, York., but there is no firm link.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wl2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Laud</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">William Laud</persName>
               <birth>7 October 1573</birth>
               <death>10 January 1645</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Laud (born 7 October 15731573-1645), Archbishop of Canterbury, was born on born on 7th October 1573 in Reading to William Laud and Lucy Robinson (nee WebbWebb Robinson). He was educated at Reading school and then Oxford University and elected Archbishop of Canterbury in 1633. A royalist, he was executed on 10 January 1645.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rl2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Richard</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Legard</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Richard Legard</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Richard Legard was the second son of John Legard and Elizabeth Mallory. He was related to Alice Thornton via Alice's great-great-grandfather George Bowes, who married Dorothy Mallory. A barrister at Gray's Inn, he was a Royalist captain during the Civil War, and he was godfather to Alice's eighth child and youngest daughter, Joyce, born and baptised in September 1665.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xl2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>General; 1st 1st Lord Newark</roleName>
                  <forename>David</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Leslie</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">General Leslie</persName>
               <birth>1601</birth>
               <death>February 1682</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">David Leslie, 1st 1st Lord Newark (1601-82) was an army officer in the employ of Alexander Leslie, first 1st Eearl Leven. A key figure in the parliamentarian success at the battle of Marston Moor in July 1644, he was stationed in Yorkshire, when Alice Thornton and her mother complained to him about Captain Innes, a soldier who was harassing them due to Alice's refusal to become romantically involved with him. He married Jane Yorke and they had nine 9 children; three 3 sons and six 6 daughters. He died in February 1682.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gl1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>George</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Lightfoot</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">George Lightfoot</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Lightfoot was a servant in the household of Alice Osborn Wandesford, Alice Thornton's mother. He married another of her servants, Daphne Cassell, and they had at least one child. A literate man, he and Daphne were witnesses to Alice senior's Thornton's mother's will in 1659. The couple had at least one child.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="al1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Loftus</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Anne Loftus</persName>
               <birth>c. 1626</birth>
               <death>4 April 1659</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Loftus (born c. 1626-59) was the daughter of Robert Loftus and Eleanor Ruishe, and the granddaughter of Adam Loftus, Lord Chancellor of Ireland (c. 1568-1643). She and her parents lived in the household of Thomas Wentworth, 1st Lord, 1st Earl Strafford, at Dublin inin the late 1630s, when she kept company with Alice Thornton and the Wentworth's h daughters Anne and Arabella. She married Richard Lennard Barrett c. 1653 and had four 4 children, 2 sons and 2 daughters. She died on 4 April 1659.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="el2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>2nd 2nd Viscount Elye</roleName>
                  <forename>Edward</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Loftus</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Edward Loftus</persName>
               <birth>c. 1598</birth>
               <death>11 April 1680</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edward Loftus, 2nd Viscount Elye (born c. 1598-1680) was the second son of Adam Loftus, Lord Chancellor of Ireland and Sarah Bathow. He married Jane Lindley, and through her inherited Middleham Castle, Yorkshire – where Alice Thornton's sister Katherine Danby gave birth to her penultimate child Edward in August 1644. The Loftus, Wentworth and Wandesford families were close associates in Ireland. Edward and Jane had two 2 children, Arthur and Sarah. He died on 11 April 1680.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rl3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Loftus</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Robert Loftus</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>August 1672</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Loftus of Waitwith (xxxx-1672) was present at the wedding of Alice Wandesford and William Thornton in 1651. A self-described 'yeoman', he had four 4 daughters and a son. He may have beenwas an investor in the lead mining and smelting that was taking place in Thorpe Edge. His will, dated 29 August 1672, shows that he owed money to Christopher Wandesford, Alice Thornton's brother.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wl1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Lowcock</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">William Lowcock</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>31 July 1678</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Lowcock (xxxx-1678) was rector of All Saints, Nunnington from 1658 until his death in 1678. He baptised Alice Thornton's son Robert in 1662 at the family home in East Newton.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cm1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>2nd 2nd Baron Enniskillen</roleName>
                  <forename>Connor</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Maguire</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Connor Maguire</persName>
               <birth>c. 1612</birth>
               <death>20 February 1645</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Connor Maguire, 2nd 2nd Baron Enniskillen (born c. 1612-45) was the eldest son of Brian Roe Maguire and Rose ny Neale. He married Mary Fleming and they had several sonsat least one son. He was one of the conspirators in the failed plot to seize Dublin Castle during the Irish rebellion of 1641, and was executed at Tyburn on 20 February 1645.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="hm1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Hugh Oge</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Mac Mahon</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Hugh Oge Mac Mahon</persName>
               <birth>1606/1607</birth>
               <death>22 November 1644</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Hugh Oge Mac Mahon (born 1606/07-44) was a younger son of Brian Hugh Oge Mac Mahon, Lord of Dartrey and Mary O'Neill. He was an Irish conspirator in the failed 1641 plot to seize Dublin Castle during the Irish Rebellion. He was executed at Tyburn on 22 November 1644.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="em1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                  <forename>Edmund</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Mainwaring</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Edmund Mainwaring</persName>
               <birth>c. 1579</birth>
               <death>c. 1643</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edmund Mainwaring (born c. 1579-c. 1643) was the second son of Randle Mainwaring and Margaret Fitton of Over Peover, Cheshire. He matriculated Brasenose College, Oxford in 1594 and All Souls in 1600. He married Jane, and they had three 3 children, a daughter and two 2 sons, who were baptised in York. A civil lawyer, he held various positions before becoming Chancellor of Chester in 1634. He died c.irca 16434.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xm2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mrs</roleName>
                  <forename>Jane</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Mainwaring</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Jane Mainwaring</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Jane Mainwaring was the wife of Edmund Mainwaring. Her birth name is unknown but she is thought to have come from York. She and Edmund married before 1614 had  three3 children, a daughter and two 2 sons.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xm3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Captain</roleName>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Mainwaring</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Captain Mainwaring</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Captain Mainwaring could be William Mainwaring, son of Edmund Mainwaring, killed during the Siege of Chester in 1645; or Philip Mainwaring, son of Randle Mainwaring and Jane Smith, who is referred to as a 'captaine of the horse'. Both were involved in the defence of Chester.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rm1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Meredith</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir Robert Meredith</persName>
               <birth>c. 1597</birth>
               <death>1668</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Meredith (c. 1597-1668) was the son of Richard Meredith, Bishop of Leighlin and Sarah Bathow. He married Anne Usher, and they had three 3 sons. He served as Chancellor of the Exchequer of Ireland. He and Anne had a Greenhills estate in Kildare. He died in 1668.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mm1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Margery</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Millbanke</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Margery Millbanke</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Margery Millbanke was a servant in Alice Thornton's household.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gm1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>General; 1st  1st Duke of Albermarle</roleName>
                  <forename>George</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Moncke</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">George Monck</persName>
               <birth>6 December 1608</birth>
               <death>1 January 1670</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Monck (born 6 December 1608-70) born 6 December 1608 was the fourth son of Sir Thomas Monck, landowner in Devon and Elizabeth Smyth, born 6 December 1608. He married Ann Clarges, and they had 1 son. A colonel in the Royalist army, he landed in Dublin in 1642 to quell the Irish uprising. He died on 1 January 1670.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pn1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Philip</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Nesbit</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Philip Nesbit</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>buried 15 October 1663</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Philip Nesbit (xxxx-1663);, son of Philip Nesbit of York and Elizabeth Hoyle, received his Cambridge BA and MA from Corpus Christi in 1638 and 1641 held the rectorship of Kirklington from 1649-61662. He married Susan Hemmingway and they had six 6 children, four 4 sons and two 2 daughters, five 5 of whom survived childhood. He was removed from the rectorship of Kirklington in 1662 for refusing to subscribe to the Act of Uniformity. He died the next year, according to Alice by 'vomiting up his very excrements', and was buried at St. Martins, York on 15 October 1663.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rn1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Nettleton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Robert Nettleton</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Nettleton was a creditor of Sir Christopher Wandesford, Alice Thornton's father. William Thornton inherited this debt via his marriage to Alice.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cn1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Christopher Norton</persName>
               <birth>c. 1651</birth>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Wandesford (born c. 1651) was the third son of Maulger Norton and Anne Wandesford; Alice Thornton's first cousin.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wn1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">William Norton</persName>
               <birth>c. 1627</birth>
               <death>December 1666</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Norton (c. 1627-66) was the son of Maulger Norton and Anne Wandesford; Alice Thornton's first cousin. A barrister at Gray's Inn, he was murdered in December 1666 in London.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jo1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Ogle</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Ogle</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Ogle was implicated in the murder of Alice Thornton's nephew Thomas Danby at Gray's Inn in 1667, but was pardoned and released from jail in October 1667.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="awo1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Middleton</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Osborne</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Walmesley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Anne Walmesley Osborne</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>buried 20 August 1666</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Walmesley (xxxx-1666) was the daughter of Thomas Walmesley of Dunkenhalgh and his first wife Eleanor Danvers. She married William Middleton and had no issue; on his death she married Edward Osborne, Alice Thornton's maternal uncle, and became his second wife. They had a son, Thomas. She was buried on 20 August 1666.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ho1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Hewett</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Osborne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir Hewett Osborne</persName>
               <birth>baptised 13 March 1567</birth>
               <death>September 1599</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Hewett Osborne (1567-1599) was baptised on 13 March 1567, the son of Sir Edward Osborne and Anna Hewett; Alice Thornton's maternal grandfather. |A landowner and soldier, he married Joyce Fleetwood, and they had a son and a daughter. He owned lands at Kiveton, Yorkshire, but lived in Essex. He died in September 1599.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jfo1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lady</roleName>
                  <forename>Joyce</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Osborne</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Frescheville</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Fleetwood</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Lady Joyce Fleetwood Osborne</persName>
               <birth>1569</birth>
               <death>April 1619</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Joyce Fleetwood (1569-1619) was the daughter of Sir Thomas Fleetwood of The Vache and his second wife, Bridget Spring; maternal grandmother of Alice Thornton. She married Sir Hewett Osborne of Kiveton on 26 December 1588 and they had 2 children, Edward and Alice. Osborne died in 1599, and on 18 October 1604 she married Peter Frescheville, and they had 3 children. She died in April 1619.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cp1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Parkes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Christopher Parkes</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Parkes attended St. John's College Cambridge where he graduated with an MA in 1663. He was vicar of Catterick and minister of the chapel at Hipswell, Bolton-super-Swale and Hudswell.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jp1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Payton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir John Payton</persName>
               <birth>1561</birth>
               <death>19 December 1616</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir John Payton (1561-1616) was  the son of Robert Payton and Elizabeth Rich. He married Alice Osborne, sister of Hewett Osborne; Alice Thornton's maternal great-uncle by marriage. They had 6 sons and 7 daughters. He was twice elected MP for Cambridgeshire, in 1593 and in 1604, and died on 19 December 1616.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wp1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Parsons</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir William Parsons</persName>
               <birth>c. 1570</birth>
               <death>January/February 1650</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Parsons (c. 1570-1650) was the son of James Parsons and Catherine Fenton. He became one of the Lord Justices of Ireland after the death of Alice Thornton's father Christopher Wandesford in 1640 until 1642. He had previously been Surveyor General of Ireland and an MP for County Wicklow. He married Elizabeth Lany and they had 12 children, 5 sons and 7 daughters. He died in January or February 1650 and is buried at St. Margaret's, Westminster.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jp2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Plummer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">John Plummer</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Plummer discovered the body of George Wandesford, Alice Thornton's brother, near Catterick Bridge on the river Swale in 1651.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ftp1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Frances</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Portington</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Frances Thornton Portington</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>buried 11 March 1705</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Frances Thornton (xxxx-1705) was the daughter of Robert Thornton and Elizabeth Darley, and was the youngest sister of Alice Thornton's husband William. She was the third wife of Timothy Portington, who she married on 27 July 1663, and they had 1 son. She was buried on 11 March 1705.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tp1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Timothy</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Portington</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Timothy Portington</persName>
               <birth>c. 1630</birth>
               <death>26 June 1697</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Timothy Portington of Malton (c. 1630-1697) was the son of Francis Portington and Ellen Scarfe. An apothecary in New Malton, he was married three times; to Mary Pye (d. 1654), Mary Ruddock (d. 1662) and Frances Thornton, the younger sister of Alice Thornton's husband William. He had a daughter with Mary Ruddock and a son with Frances Thornton. He died on 26 June 1697.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xr1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Raines</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mr Raynes</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Raines was a man to whom William Thornton was in debt along with his brother-in-law Timothy Portington. He could be John Raynes of Appleton-le-Street, west of Malton, who held the manor of Malton Priory until 1665, or Thomas Raynes, an attorney and Lord Mayor of York in the 1660s.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gr1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>George</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Radcliffe</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir George Radcliffe</persName>
               <birth>baptised 21 April 1593</birth>
               <death>1657</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir George Ratcliffe (1593-1657)  was baptised on 21 April 1593, the son of Nicholas Ratcliffe and Margaret Marsh. He was educated at University College Oxford and entered the bar at Gray's Inn c. 1618. His brief first marriage was to the daughter of John Finch, and his second to Anne Trappes. A cousin-by-marriage through Anne of Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl Strafford, he was part of Strafford's Irish administration 1633-40, and was imprisoned in Dublin Castle after being tried for treason in 1640. George and Anne had a son, Thomas. After his release in 1642 he spent much of his time in the Netherlands, and died in 1657.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mr2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Martha</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Richison</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Martha Richison</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Martha Richison was a witness at Alice and William Thornton's wedding in 1651.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jr1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Jane</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Rimer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Jane Rimer</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Jane Rimer was a midwife who, in 1654, helped Alice Thornton's young daughter Nally through a fit.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ar1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Robinson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Anne Robinson</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Robinson was a maid in the Thornton household whom Alice saved from choking on a goose bone in 1661.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mr1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Matthew</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Robinson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Matthew Robinson</persName>
               <birth>baptised 14 December 1628</birth>
               <death>27 November 1694</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Matthew Robinson (1628-94) was baptised at Rokeby on 14 December 1628, the third son of Thomas Robinson and Frances Smelt. He graduated from the University of Cambridge in 1652 and was appointed vicar of St. Lambert, Burneston in 1651, which he held for 40 years. He married Jane Pickering on 12 October 1657. The marriage had no issue. He died at Ripley on 27 November 1694 and was buried at Burneston.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xr2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Robinson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mr Robinson</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr. Robinson was possibly Thomas Robinson of Easby, who held land in the Richmond area.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rr1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Prince and count of the Palatinate, Duke of Cumberland</roleName>
                  <forename>Rupert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Palatinate-Simmern(?)</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Prince Rupert</persName>
               <birth>18 December 1619</birth>
               <death>29 November 1682</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Prince Rupert of the Palatinate, Duke of Cumberland (1619-82)  was born on 18 December 1619 to Frederick V of the Palatinate and Countess Louisa Juliana of Nassau. One of the main military commanders in the Wars of the Three Kingdoms, he never married, but had 2 children,  a son with Francesca Bard (to whom his marriage is disputed), and a daughter with Margaret Hughes. He died on 29 November 1682.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="aws1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Countess of Sussex</roleName>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Savile</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Overton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wake</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Anne Wake Savile</persName>
               <birth>baptised 19 January 1647</birth>
               <death>1679</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Wake Savile (1647-79) was baptised 19 January 1647, the daughter of Robert Wake of Antwerp and London and Mabel Brokesby. She married James Savile, 2nd Earl of Sussex, and they had a son, James, who did not survive infancy. After his death in 1671 she married Fairfax Overton in April 1674. She died in 1679.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ls1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Laurence</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Sayer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Laurence Sayer</persName>
               <birth>c. 1632</birth>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Laurence Sayer (b. c. 1632) was a member of a recusant family in Worsall, Northallerton, whose estates had been forfeited in the 1650s for his father Laurence Sayer's recusancy and delinquency. Laurence Sayer junior borrowed heavily to buy back the estates. He is possibly the same Laurence Sayer who married Catherine Burdon in 1690, who went on to have a son, Robert.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rs1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Richard</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Shuttleworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Richard Shuttleworth</persName>
               <birth>1587</birth>
               <death>1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Richard Shuttleworth (born 1587-1699) was the son of Thomas Shuttleworth and Anne Lever. In 1607 he inherited Gawthorpe Hall from his uncle Lawrence Shuttleworth. He married Fleetwood Barton with whom he had 12 children, 8 sons and 4 daughters. He may also have married Judith Thorpe.  (Dugdale). A Parliamentarian, he was MP for Preston from 1640-48 and re-elected in 1654 during the Interregnum. He died in 1669.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename>Henock(?)</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Sinkler</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mr Sinkler</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is possibly Mr Sinkler is possibly Enoch or HenockHenock Siynkler, rector of Slingsby, who was educated at St. John's College Cambridge, graduating in 1633 and made curate of Auburn Chapel, Carnaby, East Riding in 1635, a position he held until at least 1638..</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mss1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lady</roleName>
                  <forename>Mary</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Smith</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Smyth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Lady Mary Smith</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Smyth was the daughter of Hugh Smyth of Long Ashton, Somerset and Elizabeth Gorges. She married Sir Thomas Smith of Hatherton, Cheshire, who was mayor of Chester in 1622, High Sheriff of Cheshire in 1623, alderman of Chester and MP for Chester in the Short and later Long Parliaments, 1640-44. Thomas and Mary had 22 children., and had 22 children.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ts1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Smith</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir Thomas Smith</persName>
               <birth>c. 1595</birth>
               <death>c. 1668</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Thomas Smith (born c. 1595-c. 1668) was the son of Thomas Smith of Hatherton,  Cheshire and Anne Mainwaring. Mayor of Chester from 1622 and High Sheriff of Cheshire in 1623, he sat as MP for Chester between 1640-44 in the Short and then Long Parliaments before being barred from Parliament for his royalist support. He married Mary Smyth, and they had 22 children. He died c. 1668.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Smith</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Dr Smith</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dr. Smith was a physician who attended Alice Osborne Wandesford, Alice Thornton's mother, on her deathbed.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="hs1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Hugh</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Smithson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir Hugh Smithson</persName>
               <birth>c. 1598</birth>
               <death>21 October 1670</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Hugh Smithson (c. 1598-1670) of Stanwick St. John, North Yorkshire, was the son of Anthony Smithson and Eleanor Catterick. He was a London merchant, recusant and royalist made Baronet of Stanwick in 1660 by Charles II for his support. He married Dorothy Rawsthorne, and they had four4 sons and two2 daughters. According to Alice Thornton, his oldest son Jerome  plotted to rape her. He died on 21 October 1670.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="js1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir; 2nd Baronet Stanwick</roleName>
                  <forename>Jerome</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Smithson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Jerome Smithson</persName>
               <birth>1632</birth>
               <death>1684</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Jerome Smithson, 2nd Baronet Stanwick (born 1632-84) was the eldest son and heir of Sir Hugh Smithson, 1st Baronet Stanwick and Dorothy Rawsthorne.. According to Alice Thornton, Jerome's father and uncle sought her hand in marriage to Jerome, but on refusal he plotted to rape and abduct Alice when she was living at Hipswell, but a man named Tom Binks informed her of the plot so she could escape. He married Mary Wingate, and they had a son and a daughter. He became 2nd Baronet Stanwick on his father's death in 1670, and He died in 1684.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Smithson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Uncle Smithson</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Uncle Smithson is one of Sir Jerome's Smithson's paternal uncles, Francis, Richard or John. He helped his brother Hugh Smithson in a bid to marry his nephew Jerome to Alice Thornton in the late 1640s or early 1650s.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cs2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>King</roleName>
                  <forename>Charles</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Stewart</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Charles II</persName>
               <birth>29 May 1630</birth>
               <death>6 February 1685</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles Stewart ,(1630-85), King Charles II of England, Scotland and Ireland (born 29 May 1630) was born on 29 May 1630 tthe son and heiro King Charles I and Henrietta Maria. He was King of Scotland 1649-51 and King of England, Scotland and Ireland from the Restoration ofin 1660 until his death in 1685. He married Catherine of Braganza, but had no legitimate issue. He fathered some 9 illegitimate children. He died on 6 February 1689.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Thomson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mr Thomson</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Thomson of Catterick Bridge owned the house where the body of George Wandesford, drowned in the Swale while attempting to cross it on horseback, was laid after its recovery in 1651.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ct1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Christopher Thornton</persName>
               <birth>11 November 1667</birth>
               <death>2 December 1667</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Thornton (1667): the 9th child of Alice and William Thornton. He was born at Newton, 11th Nov. 1667 and baptized on the 12th. He contracted small pox and died on 1 Dec. 1667 and was buried at Stonegrave on the 2nd.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jt1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Joyce</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Joyce Thornton</persName>
               <birth>23 September 1665</birth>
               <death>26 January 1666</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Joyce Thornton (1665-6): the 8th child of Alice and William Thornton. Joyce was born on 23rd September. 1665 at Newton and baptized on the 28th.  She fell ill on 20th January. 1666 with a cold and red spots and died on 26th January. She was bBuried on the 27thth  at in Stonegrave.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rt2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Robert Thornton</persName>
               <birth>19 September 1662</birth>
               <death>4 June 1692</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Thornton (1662-92): the seventh7th child and third3rd son of Alice and William Thornton. He was born on 19 September. 1662 at East Newton. He was educated first by John Denton, then by the reverend John Burton at Sutton-on-n –the-Forest, then entered Sidney Sussex College in April 1680, then University College. In 1687 he became the rector of Oddington but resigned it later that year. In 1691 he took over the living of Boldon in the diocese of Durham but actually resided at the Deanery in Durham with his sister Nally and her husband, Thomas Comber. He caught a cold and died there on 4 June 1692, aged 29. He was buried in the Chapel of the Nine Altars, Durham Cathedral where there is a memorial to him, erected by his sister, Alice Thornton Comber, in XXXX.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rt3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Robert Thornton</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>buried 27 May 1637</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Thornton (XXXX-1637), father of William Thornton. His first marriage was to Dorothy Metham and they had four 4 daughters, one 1 of whom died in infancy. He then married Elizabeth Darley with whom he had William and Richard (twins), Thomas, John, Elizabeth, Mary and Frances7 children, 4 sons and 3 daughters. He was buried at Stonegrave on 27 May 1637.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tt1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Thomas Thornton</persName>
               <birth>1626</birth>
               <death>1685</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Thornton (born 1626-85) was the son of Robert Thornton and Elizabeth Darley, and the younger brother of William Thornton.,  so was Alice's brother-in-law.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wt2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">William Thornton</persName>
               <birth>17 April 1660</birth>
               <death>28 April 1660</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Thornton, son of Alice and William Thornton (1660): their 6th6th child and second2nd son was born and baptized at St Nicholas on 17 April 1660, died on 28 April of the small pox and was buried on the 29th29 April 1660 at Easby, in the same grave as his unnamed sister.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt5">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Tirrill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mr Tirrill</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Tirrill of Hoddesdon was a chief mourner at the funeral of Alice Thornton's brother John Wandesford in 1664.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="bt1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Barbara</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Todd</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Barbara Todd</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Barbara Todd was a maid of Anne Culpeper Danby, Alice Thornton's niece-by-marriage. According to Alice, she was one of the perpetrators of the slanders faced by Alice and her daughter Nally around Nally's marriage to Thomas Comber in 1668.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt4">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mrs</roleName>
                  <forename/>
                  <surname type="birth">Troutbeck</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Mr Troutbeck</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Young Mr Troutbeck was a man who gave Alice Thornton's sick mother advice while Alice was in labour with her daughter Elizabeth in February 1654.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="et2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Queen</roleName>
                  <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Tudor</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Elizabeth I</persName>
               <birth>7 September 1533</birth>
               <death>24 March 1603</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth I (1533-1603) (born 7 September 1533) was Queen of England from 1558 until her death in 1603. Born on 7 September 1533, sThe was the daughter of Henry VIII and his second wife Anne Boleyn, she never married.. Alice Thornton notes that her mother Alice Osborne Wandesford was born during Elizabeth's reign. She died on 24 March 1603.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cw4">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir Christopher Wandesford</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>11 July 1591</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Christopher Wandesford (d. 1591) was the son of Francis Wandesford of Kirklington and Jane Fulthorp; Alice Thornton's great-grandfather. He married Elizabeth Bowes and they had four 4 children; three 3 sons and a daughter. He diewd on 11 July 1591.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cw5">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Christopher Wandesford*</persName>
               <birth>1617</birth>
               <death>1627</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Wandesford (1617-27) was the son of Sir Christopher Wandesford and Alice Osborne; Alice Thornton's older brother. He died age 10 in 1627. Alice's brother born in 1628, later 1st Baronet Kirklington, was named after him.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ww2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">William Wandesford</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Wandesford of Pickhill was the son of Richard Wandesford and Muriel Yoward; and was a cousin of Alice Thornton's father William Christopher Wandesford. He was living in Ireland at the time of Christopher Wandesford's death in December 1640 and was a witness to his will as well as one of the executors of his estate. He married Elizabeth Askwith and they had three 3 sons.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="lw1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Luke</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wastell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Luke Wastell</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death/>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Luke Wastell was the third son of Leonard Wastell of Scorton and Anne Danby of Kirkby Knowle. His brother John was a Parliamentarian and MP for Northallerton. He married twice; first Sarah Laton and then Elizabeth Pattison.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rw2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Webster</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Robert Webster</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>buriedb. 27 October 1667</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Webster of Nunnington was a witness at Alice and William Thornton's marriage in 1651. He was buried at Nunnington on 27 October 1667.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="erw1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lady Strafford</roleName>
                  <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Wentworth</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Rhodes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Elizabeth Rhodes Wentworth</persName>
               <birth>c. 1614</birth>
               <death>10 April 1688</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth Rhodes Wentworth (c. 1614-88) was the daughter of Godfrey Rhodes and Anne Lewknor. In around 1632 sheShe became the third wife of Thomas Wentworth, 1st Lord Strafford c. 1632, and they had two children, Thomas and Margaret. She was also step-mother to Wentworth's children with Arabella Holles. She died on 10 Aprilin 1688.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ww3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>2nd Lord Raby, 2nd Earl Strafford</roleName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wentworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">William Wentworth</persName>
               <birth>8 June 1626</birth>
               <death>16 October 1695</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Wentworth 2nd Lord Raby 2nd Earl Strafford (1626-1695) was born on 8 June 1626 to Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl Strafford and his second wife Arabella Holles, their first child and only son. He married twice; first Henrietta Maria Stanley; and second Henrietta de la Rochfoucauld. He died without issue on 16 October 1695.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pcw1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Philadelphia</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Wharton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Carey</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Philadelphia Carey Wharton</persName>
               <birth/>
               <death>1654</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Lady Wharton was probably Philadelphia Carey (xxxx-d. 1654), was the daughter of Robert Carey and Elizabeth Trevannion. She was a lady-in-waiting to Princess Elizabeth, Queen of Bohemia and married Sir Thomas Wharton of Aske Hall in on 11 April 1611. T and they had two 2 sons, Philip and Thomas. She died at Easby in 1654.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rw3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName/>
                  <forename>Ralph</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Widdrington</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Ralph Widdrington</persName>
               <birth>c. 1614/15</birth>
               <death>10 June 1688</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ralph Widdrington c. (1614/15-88) was the son of Lewis Widdrington of Cheesburn Grange, Northumberland and Anne Lawson. He attended Morpeth School and was then admitted to Christ's College Cambridge in 1632. He was admitted to Gray's Inn in 1641, before being ordained and tutoring at Christ's, where he taught Alice Thornton's younger brother John Wandesford. He became Regius Professor of Greek in 1654. He died at Christ's on 10 June 1688.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cw3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir, 3rd Baronet of Constable Burton</roleName>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wyvill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="pseudo">Sir Christopher Wyvill</persName>
               <birth>baptised 6 December 1614</birth>
               <death>buried 8 February 1681</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Christopher Wyvill, 3rd Baronet of Constable Burton (1614-81), was baptised on 6 December 1614, the eldest son and heir of Marmaduke Wyvill and Isabel Gascoigne. He married Ursula Darcy on 12 December 1636, and the couple had 12 children, ; six6 of whom died before them (two daughters and four sons), and 6 six (three sons and three daughters) survived them. He wrote an elegy for Alice's brother George Wandesford, who drowned in the Swale in 1651. He was elected MP for Richmond in 1659 and returned to the Long Parliament in 1660. He was buried with his wife, who died in 1680, at Masham on 8 February 1681.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
         </listPerson>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
