<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><!--
        **DO NOT MANUALLY EDIT THIS FILE**  
        its generated automatically with XSLT
        -->
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>ATB People (20 October 2022)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>blah blah</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
              sources: 
              <list>
                  <item>Teams spreadsheet: Ographies/atb_people_masterlist_220911.xlsx - spreadsheet derived from books xml</item>
                  <item>Teams biographies docx: BoR and Bk1 biographies (latest version)</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p>
            NOTES: 
            </p>
         <p>
            bios are still work in progress and a bit messy in places. New people in books 2 and 3 have not yet been added, so there are tagged people not accounted for in this file.
            </p>
         <p>
            ID construction is based on name initials:
              use full initials where known
              for married women include maiden surname initial if known
              if firstname [or surname for that matter] unavailable use x
              add number to ensure uniqueness
            [working IDs; may be subject to change]
            
            any "tbd" IDs are waiting to be verified
            </p>
         <p>
            TODO:
              roleName, forename, need finessing. esp @type=...
              bio sources to be added
              wikidata etc linkage to do once name tagging and internal linkage is completed
              listRelation - also once name tagging and biographies are complete
             
          </p>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date when="2022-10-20"/>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change>
               <date>2022-10-20</date>
               <desc>slight revision to schema (persName label); revised format of label names. added EDTF date formatting for births and deaths.</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
               <date>2022-06-27</date>
               <desc>updated to use KDL schema</desc>
            </change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <listPerson>
            <person xml:id="awt1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Alice</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Thornton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Alice Thornton (1626-1707)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1626-02-13">13 February 1626</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1707-02-01">buried 1 February 1707</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Alice Thornton (1626-1707) was born to Christopher and Alice Wandesford in Kirklington, North Yorkshire on 13 February 1626. She was their fifth child of seven and their youngest daughter. She married William Thornton of East Newton in 1651 and they had nine children, three of whom survived to adulthood. She died at East Newton and was buried at Stonegrave on 1 February 1707.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cw1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Wandesford (1592-1640)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1592-09-24">24 September 1592</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1640-12-03">3 December 1640</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Wandesford (1592-1640) was the eldest son and heir of Sir George and Catherine Wandesford. He was born at Bishop Burton, East Riding on 24 September 1592. He attended Clare College, Cambridge but was required to return home on his father's death to provide for his siblings. He married Alice Osborne and they had seven children, five of whom survived childhood, including Alice Thornton. He was MP for Yorkshire in the 1620s. In 1633 he relocated the family to Dublin, Ireland, to serve as Master of Rolls. In 1640 he was briefly Lord Deputy of Ireland before he died on 3 December 1640.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rl1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Roger</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Lasselles</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Roger Lasselles (1557-1630)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1557">1557</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1630-07">July 1630</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Roger Lasselles (1557-1630) was rector of Kirklington from May 1590 until his death in July 1630. He baptised Alice Thornton in 1626.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="awn1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Norton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Norton (1593-1683)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1593">1593</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1683-12-23">buried 23 December 1683</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Norton (1593-1683) was the daughter of Sir George and Catherine Wandesford. She was Alice Thornton’s paternal aunt. She married Maulger Norton on 4 March 1622. They had 5 children; 3 sons and 2 daughters. She was buried on 23 December 1683 at [St Mary’s,] Richmond.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Olive</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Best</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Mallory</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Olive Best (1594-1654)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1594-12-05">baptised 5 December 1594</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1654-06-16">buried 16 June 1654</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mrs Best was probably Olive Best (1594-1654), the daughter of John and Anne Mallory. She had a twin, Jane. Olive became the second wife of Thomas Best of Middleton Quernhow, M.P. for Ripon, on 17 January 1619. She died without issue and was buried at Wath-by-Ripon on 16 June 1654.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="st1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Sarah</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Tomlinson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Sarah Tomlinson </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sarah Tomlinson was a servant in the Wandesford household.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cw2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>1st Baronet of Kirklington</roleName>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Wandesford (1628-1687)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1628-02-02">2 February 1628</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1687-02-23">23 February 1687</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Wandesford (1628-87) was the son of Christopher and Alice Wandesford, born on 2 February 1628 and baptised at Kirklington on 14 February. He was Alice Thornton's younger brother. He married Eleanor Lowther on 30 September 1651 and they had 12 children. He became heir on his brother George’s death in 1651 and was made 1st Baronet of Kirklington on the Restoration of Charles II in 1660. He was elected MP for Ripon in 1679 and again in 1680. He died in London on 23 February 1687 and was buried on 12 March at Kirklington.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <surname type="birth">Baxter</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Baxter </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Baxter of Kent hosted Alice and Christopher Wandesford, then children, and their maid Sarah, to aid their recovery from smallpox in 1631. The Wandesford family were living in London at the time.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xl1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lady</roleName>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Leveson</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Dudley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Leveson (1598-1674)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1598">1598</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1674">1674</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is most likely Lady Katherine Leveson (1598-1674) the daughter of the illegitimate son of the Elizabethan courtier Robert Dudley, also called Robert Dudley, and his first wife Alice, born 1598. She married Sir Richard Leveson, later MP for Newcastle-upon-Lyme, in 1609 at Kenilworth. She died February 1674 at Trentham, Kent without issue, and in her will endowed almshouses and an education fund which survives to this day at Temple Balsall.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tw1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir, 1st Lord Raby; 1st Earl of Strafford</roleName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wentworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Wentworth (1593-1641)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1593-04-13">13 April 1593</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1641-05-12">12 May 1641</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Wentworth, 1st Lord Raby, 1st Earl Strafford (1593-1641), was Lord Lieutenant of Ireland 1633-40. He was born on 13 April 1593 to William Wentworth, a Yorkshire landowner, and Anne, their second and eldest surviving son and heir. He was a childhood friend of Christopher Wandesford, Alice Thornton's father, both being educated by the Dean of Ripon. His first marriage to Margaret Clifford took place in 1611, she died childless in August 1622. He married Arabella Holles in February 1625, then had a son and two daughters. After her premature death on 6 October 1631 he married Elizabeth Rhodes in 1632 and had another son and a daughter. In 1633 he was made Lord Deputy of Ireland and relocated to Dublin, with the Wandesford family in tow as Christopher was made Master of the Rolls. He was recalled to England in 1639, fell out of favour with the King, impeached and executed on 12 May 1641.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="aw1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lady</roleName>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Watson</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wentworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Watson (1627-1696)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1627-10-08">8 October 1627</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1696-01-02">2 January 1696</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Lady Anne Watson (1627-96) was the eldest daughter of Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl of Strafford and his second wife Arabella, born on 8 October 1627 in Finningley, Nottinghamshire. A childhood friend of Alice Thornton's in Dublin, she married Edward Watson on 24 November 1654 and they had 8 children, 4 sons and 4 daughters. She died on 2 January 1696, and was buried at Rockingham.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="aw2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lady</roleName>
                  <forename>Arabella</forename>
                  <surname type="married">McCarthy</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wentworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Arabella McCarthy (1630-1689)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1630-10">October 1630</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1689">1689</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Lady Arabella McCarthy (1630-89), born in October 1630 in London was the daughter of Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl of Strafford and his second wife Arabella. A childhood friend of Alice Thornton's in Dublin, she married Justin MacCarthy, 1st Viscount Mountcashell, about 13 years her junior. She died in 1689 without issue.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jw1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Wandesford (c.1632-1664)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1632~">c. 1632</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1664-12-02">2 December 1664</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Wandesford (c. 1630-1664) was the fourth, but third surviving, son of Christopher and Alice Wandesford; brother of Alice Thornton. He was born c. 1630, and moved to Ireland with the family as a young child when his father became Master of the Rolls. After returning to Yorkshire, he was educated at Bedale, Chester and Richmond Schools before entering Christ's College, Cambridge (1649-51). Becoming ill at Cambridge, according to Alice in reaction to the death of their brother George, he moved to London. He was elected MP for Richmond in 1661, and died in his lodgings at London on 2 December 1664 of an ague.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fk1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Frank</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Kelly</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Frank Kelly (c.1634-1643)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1634~">c. 1634</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1643">1643</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Frank Kelly (c. 1634-43) was an orphan boy taken into the household of Sir Christopher Wandesford in Dublin, after Wandesford had encountered him while playing bowls on the green. According to Alice he was about 9 when he died of small pox at Chester after the family had fled Ireland.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="td1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Danby (c.1617-1645)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1617~">c. 1617</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1645-06-14">14 June 1645</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Danby of South Cave (c. 1617-45) was the second son of Thomas and Elizabeth Danby of Braworth, born c. 1617. He was possibly the same Thomas Danby involved in a court of chivalry case in 1638 against John Bates of York, whom he claimed had verbally abused him and denied his gentility. He fought for the Royalists during the Civil War and was killed at the Battle of Naseby on 14 June 1645.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xm1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                  <forename>Richard(?)</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Mahum</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Richard(?) Mahum (died 1659)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1659">1659</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dr. Mahum (xxxx-1659), described by Alice as her 'old doctor', may be the same Richard Mahum who witnessed her mother's will in 1659.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="kwd1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Danby</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Danby (1615-1645)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1615-10-20">baptised 20 October 1615</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1645-09-10">10 September 1645</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Danby (1615-45) was the eldest child of Christopher and Alice Wandesford; older sister of Alice Thornton. She was baptised on 20 October 1615 at Kirklington. She married Thomas Danby in July 1630, aged 14. She became pregnant 16 times but suffered 6 miscarriages. Of the couple's 10 baptised children, 8 were boys and 2 were girls; 7 of her 10 children survived infancy. She died on 10 September 1645, aged 29, at Thorpe Perrow of postpartum complications. She was buried at Masham the next day.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fd1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Francis</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Francis Danby (born 1645)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1645-08-27">27 August 1645</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Francis Danby (1645-xxxx) was the youngest son of Thomas Danby and Katherine Wandesford, born at Thorpe Perrow on 27 August 1645. He was Alice Thornton's nephew. Named after his brother who died the month before, his mother died shortly after his birth from postpartum complications. He was still alive in April 1672 when he was named in his older brother Charles's will.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="en1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename>Edmund</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Edmund Norton (1622-1648)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1622">1622</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1648-11-29">29 November 1648</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edmund Norton (1622-48) was the second son of Maulger and Anne Norton; Alice Thornton's cousin. He attended Cambridge University and was admitted to Gray's Inn in February 1646. He served as a colonel of dragoons under John Mallory in the Skipton garrison in the 1640s. He married Jane Dudley, and died of a pleurisy at York on 29 November 1648.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="td2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename>Toby</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Dudley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Toby Dudley (1597-1661)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1597">1597</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1661">1661</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Toby Dudley (1597-1661) was the oldest son and heir of Ambrose Dudley of Chopwell, Northumberland. He married Jane Blackiston, and they had one child, Jane. He was buried at Ryton in 1661.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jdn1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Jane</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Norton</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Clavering</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Dudley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Jane Clavering (died 1672)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1672-10-28">buried 28 October 1672</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Jane Dudley Norton Clavering (xxxx-1672) was the daughter and sole heir of Toby and Jane Dudley of Chopwell. She married Edmund Norton on 10 February 1647. He died in 1648. Her second husband was Robert Clavering whom she married at Ebchester on 15 July 1651. They had 4 children, 2 sons and 2 daughters. She was buried on 28 October 1672.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cs1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>King Charles I</roleName>
                  <forename>Charles</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Stuart</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Charles Stuart (1600-1649)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1600-11-19">19 November 1600</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1649-01-30">30 January 1649</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles I of England (1600-49), born 19 November 1600 to James I and VI and Anne of Denmark, was King of England, Scotland and Ireland from 1625, and the reigning monarch for the first 23 years of Alice Thornton's life. He married Henrietta Maria and had 9 children, 4 sons and 54 daughters. He was executed on 30 January 1649.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jn1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Julianne</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Julianne Norton (1633-1649)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1633-01-06">6 January 1633</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1649-04-09">9 April 1649</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Julianne Norton (1633-49), born 6 January 1633, was the daughter of Maulger and Anne Norton; Alice Thornton's cousin. She died age 17 on 9 April 1649 at her father's house at Richmond.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jn2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Norton (c.1637-1646)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1637~">c. 1637</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1646">1646</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Norton (c. 1637-46), fourth son of Maulger and Anne Norton; Alice Thornton's cousin. Born c. 1637, he died at his father's residence at St Nicholas, Richmond of a consumption in 1646, aged 9.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="eo1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir; 1st Baronet Kiveton</roleName>
                  <forename>Edward</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Osborne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Edward Osborne (1596-1647)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1596-12-12">baptised 12 December 1596</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1647-09-09">9 September 1647</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Edward Osborne, 1st Baronet Kiveton (1596-1647) was baptised on 12 December 1596, the son of Sir Hewett and Joyce Osborne; maternal uncle of Alice Thornton. Educated at Trinity College, Cambridge, he was admitted to the Inner Temple in 1620. He was knighted and created Baronet by James I that same year and was vice president of the Council of the North. He married twice, first, on 13 October 1618 to Margaret Belasyse, with whom he had a son, and after her death in 1624, to Anne Walmesley, widow of William Middleton, with whom he had a second son. He died on 9 September 1647 at his house in Kiveton, according to Alice Thornton from a surfeit of cold melons.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gw1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>George</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Wandesford (1623-1651)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1623-09-14">14 September 1623</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1651-03-31">31 March 1651</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Wandesford (1623-51), born 14 September 1623, was Christopher and Alice Wandesford's eldest son and heir, making him Alice Thornton's brother. Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl of Strafford, was his godfather. He attended Trinity College, Dublin from 1636. Accused of taking part in the battle of Marston Moor in July 1644, his estates were sequestered and he moved to Hipswell, his mother's property, before fleeing to France for the remainder of the Civil War. He drowned in the River Swale, Yorkshire, through which he was riding on horseback, on 31 March 1651.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ww1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Wandesford (1605-1690)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1605-08-26">baptised 26 August 1605</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1690">1690</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Wandesford (1605-90) was baptised on 26 August 1605 at Kirklington, the youngest son of Sir George Wandesford by his second wife, Mary. He was Alice Thornton's half-uncle. He married Rebecca Reade and they had a daughter, Catherine. His brother Christopher sent him to be an apprentice to a London merchant, and he was granted an annuity of £20 for life on 30 June 1637 out of his property at Castlecomer, Ireland and paid yearly at Christ's Church, Dublin. He suffered severe losses during the civil war due to his loyalty to the royal cause, and on 31 July 1646 he declared he had been at Oxford when Castlecomer was held for the king, and that he lent money but had not taken up arms. He was made a gentleman-pensioner by Charles II after the Restoration in 1660 and died in 1690.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mny1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Mary</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Yorke</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mary Yorke (born 1635)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1635-07-12">baptised 12 July 1635</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Yorke (1635-xxxx) daughter and fourth child of Maulger and Anne Norton, baptised at Richmond on 12 July 1635; Alice Thornton's cousin. On 20 August 1651 she married John Yorke, a knight of Gouthwaite, later MP for Richmond (1661-63).  They had 4 children, 3 sons and a daughter. She became a widow in 1663 and purchased the manor of Beverley in 1675.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jy1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Yorke</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Yorke (c.1634-1663)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1634~">c. 1634</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1663-04-01">1 April 1663</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir John Yorke (c. 1634-63) was the son of John Yorke of Gouthwaite and his second wife, Catherine. He was educated at Queen's College, Oxford, matriculating in 1650. On 20 August 1651 he married Mary, daughter of Maulger and Anne Norton, and they had 4 children, 3 sons and a daughter. He was knighted by Charles II on his Restoration in 1660, and elected MP for Richmond at the Cavalier Parliament the next year, a position he held until his death near London of a pleurisy on 1 April 1663 aged 29. He was buried at St Chad's Church, Middlesmoor in Nidderdale, commemorated by a Latin inscription.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jl1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir, Sheriff of Cumberland, 1st Baronet Lowther</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Lowther</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Lowther (1606-1675)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1606-02-20">20 February 1606</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1675-11-30">30 November 1675</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir John Lowther, 1st Baronet Lowther (1606-75) and Sheriff of Cumberland was born on 20 February 1606 to Sir John and Eleanor Lowther. He graduated from the Inner Temple in 1621 and was called to the bar in 1630. He married Mary, daughter of Richard Fletcher of Hutton, Cumbria, before 1628; they had 11 children – 5 sons and 6 daughters. His second wife was Elizabeth Hare, by whom he had 4 children, 3 sons and a daughter. His daughter Eleanor married Christopher Wandesford, Alice Thornton's brother. He was twice elected MP for Westmorland, in 1628-29 (with his father) and again in 1660. He fought for the royalists during the Civil War. He died on 30 November 1675 and is buried at Lowther Church alongside his father, commemorated by a Latin inscription.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="elw1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Eleanor</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Wandesford</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Lowther</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Eleanor Wandesford (1633-1714)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1633-03-25">baptised 25 March 1633</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1714-12-20">buried 20 December 1714</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Eleanor Lowther (1633-1714) was the daughter of John Lowther, 1st Baronet Lowther and his first wife Mary, baptised on 23 March 1633 at Lowther. She married Christopher Wandesford on 30 September 1651 at Lowther, becoming Alice Thornton's sister-in-law. Christopher and Eleanor had 9 children, 3 sons and 6 daughters. She was buried on 20 December 1714 at Kirklington.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wt1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Thornton (1624-1668)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1624-06-02">2 June 1624</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1668-09-17">17 September 1668</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Thornton (1624-68), the son of Robert Thornton of East Newton and his second wife Elizabeth, was born along with his twin brother Richard on 2 June 1624 and baptized at Stonegrave on 9 June. William married Alice Wandesford on 15 December 1651 at Hipswell. They had 9 children, of whom 3 survived to adulthood. William died at Malton on 17 September 1668 and was buried at Stonegrave the next day.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ms1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename>Michael</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Syddall</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Michael Syddall (1614-1658)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1614-09-30">baptised 30 September 1614</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1658-01-08">buried 8 January 1658</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Michael Syddall (1614-58) was baptised on 30 September 1614 at SS Martin and Gregory, York, the son William Syddall, a baker, and his wife Margaret. He was admitted to Christ's College, Cambridge in 1631 at the age of 16, graduating with his BA in 1635 and MA in 1638. He married Ellen Hunton, widow of the steward of the late Christopher Wandesford. He was minister at St Michael's, Kirklington, 1644-49 and vicar of St Anne’s, Catterick, from 1645-58. He was buried on 8 January 1658 in the chancel at St Anne’s. In his will he left money to build a school and he made William Thornton one of four trustees, alongside Richard Brathwaite, author of The English Gentlewoman (1631).</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Unnamed Thornton (1652-1652)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1652-08-27">27 August 1652</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1652-08-27">27 August 1652</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Alice Thornton's first child, an unnamed daughter, was born on 27 August 1652 but lived for less than an hour and so was not baptised. She was buried at Easby Church the next day. Her unnamed brother who died shortly after his birth in 1657 was buried next to her.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="atc1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Alice (Nally)</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Comber</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Alice (Nally) Comber (1654-1721)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1654-01-03">3 January 1654</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1721-01-20">20 January 1721</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Alice Comber (1654-1721), nicknamed Nally, was born on 3 January 1654 at Hipswell to Alice and William Thornton. She was their second child and one of three Thornton children to survive to adulthood. She married Thomas Comber on 17 November 1668, by whom she had 7 children (5 sons and 2 daughters), with 2 sons and 2 daughters surviving childhood. Her marriage to Comber was one aspect of the slanders against the Thornton family spearheaded by her niece-in-law, Anne Danby. [add more about her later life: inherits books etc] She died on 20 January 1721 and was buried at Stonegrave.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mn1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Maulger</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Maulger Norton (1594-1673)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1594-03-25">baptised 25 March 1594</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1673-12-12">buried 12 December 1673</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Maulger Norton (1593-1673) was baptised on 25 March 1593 at Wath, the first son and heir of Robert Norton of St. Nicholas, Richmond and his wife Catherine. He was elected MP for Richmond in the Short Parliament of 1640. He married Alice Thornton's paternal aunt Anne on 4 March 1622, by whom he had 6 children, 4 sons and 2 daughters. He was buried at Richmond on 12 December 1673.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="et1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Elizabeth (Betty)</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth (Betty) Thornton (1655-1656)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1655-02-14">14 February 1655</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1656-09-03">3 September 1656</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth (Betty) Thornton (1655-56)  was born on 14 February 1655 to Alice and William Thornton; their third child. She died on 3 September 1656, aged 18 months, after becoming ill with an ague, and was buried at Catterick.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ca1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename>Charles</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Anthony</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Charles Anthony (1600-1685)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1600-11-06">6 November 1600</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1685-06-25">25 June 1685</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles Anthony (1600-85) was born on 6 November 1600 and was educated at Jesus College, Cambridge (BA 1624, MA 1627). He was ordained in 1636, and was became vicar of Catterick in 1660. He baptised Alice's daughter Elizabeth in 1654. He died on 25 June 1685 and was buried at Catterick.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="kb1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mrs</roleName>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Blackburne</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Covell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Blackburne (born 1645)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1645-01-26">baptised 26 January 1645</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Blackburne, baptised 26 January 1645 at Grinton, was the daughter of Roger and Anne Covell of Fremington. Roger would later become one of Alice Thornton's solicitors. She married Timothy Blackburne. She stood in for Alice's mother, who was unwell, at the baptism of Alice's daughter, Elizabeth, in 1654. A widow from 1694, she was still alive in 1696 when she was named executrix in her mother's will.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="edg1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mrs</roleName>
                  <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Thornton</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Gates</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Darley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth Gates (1597-1655)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1597-10-03">3 October 1597</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1655-05-10">10 May 1655</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth Gates (1597-1655) born 3 October 1597 at Buttercrambe was the eldest daughter of Sir Richard Darley of Buttercrambe, Yorkshire and his second wife, Elizabeth. She became the second wife of Robert Thornton (c. 1560-1637) on 6 June 1618 and they had 7 children, 4 sons and 3 daughters. After his death in 1637 she married Gefferey Gates on 26 June 1638 at Stonegrave. Her joint-eldest son William married Alice Thornton. She died on 10 May 1655 at Oswaldkirk, from a 'voydance of blood' and was buried the next day at Stonegrave.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gg1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Gefferey</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Gates</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Gefferey Gates (died 1655)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1655-05-18">18 May 1655</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Gefferey Gates (xxxx-1655) was the second husband of Elizabeth Gates (née Darley, then Thornton), whom he married on 26 June 1638 at Stonegrave, becoming the stepfather of Alice Thornton's husband William. He died just 8 days after his wife, 18 May 1655, and was buried at St. Mary Lowgate, Hull the next day.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rt1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Richard</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Richard Thornton (1624-1656)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1624-06-02">2 June 1624</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1656-07-03">3 July 1656</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Richard Thornton (1624-56), born on 2 June 1624 and baptised on 9 June was the son of Robert Thornton and his second wife Elizabeth, and the twin brother of Alice Thornton's husband, William. He died unmarried in Dublin, Ireland of a bloody flux on 3 July 1656, and was buried at St Patrick's Church the next day.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ktp1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Purchas</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Danby</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Danby (1656-1726)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1656-06-12">12 June 1656</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1726-12-17">17 December 1726</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Danby (1656-1726) was the fourth daughter of Alice and William Thornton, and the second of two surviving daughters. She was born on 12 June 1656 at Hipswell and baptised two days later. She married Thomas Purchas, rector, by arrangement of her brother-in-law Thomas Comber on 17 December 1682. She had 5 children by Purchas, 3 sons and 2 daughters. After Purchas's death in April 1697, she married Robert Danby of Northallerton in 1698. She died on 17 December 1726 and was buried at Stonegrave.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="kdb1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Best</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Best (1637-1688)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1637-05-25">25 May 1637</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1688">1688</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Danby Best (1637-88) was the daughter of Thomas and Katherine Danby; Alice Thornton's niece. She was born on 25 May 1637 at Richmond. She married Henry Best of Middleton Quernhow, a Gray's Inn barrister, sometime after 1659, and they had 2 children, a son and a daughter. She was her husband's administratrix on 29 January 1674, his will giving her £2,000. She died in 1688.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Unnamed Thornton (1657-1657)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1657-12-10">10 December 1657</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1657-12-10">10 December 1657</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">An unnamed Thornton son (1657) was born on 10 December 1657; the fifth child of Alice and William Thornton. He lived only half an hour after a difficult birth. He was buried at Catterick, unbaptised, the same day by Michael Syddall in a grave with his unnamed sister, Alice's first born child who died in 1652.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rw1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wittie</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Wittie (1613-1684)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1613-11-14">baptised 14 November 1613</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1684-10">October 1684</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Wittie (1613-84) was baptised at St. Mary's, Beverley, on 14 November 1613, the son of George and Anne Wittie of Beverley. He studied medicine at King's College, Cambridge, and returned to his native Yorkshire to practice medicine, first at Hull, and from 1651 at the latest, at York. He treated Alice Thornton and her family for various ailments. Wittie wrote at least two books; 'The Antimonial Cup', on emetics, and 'Scarborough Spaw', which extolled the healing virtues of spas. He married Mary Hall (d. 1692). In 1675, when his mother died, he was resident in the parish of St. Martin's, Coney street, York. On his retirement from active profession he moved to London and was incorporated at the Royal College of Physicians on 30 September 1680. He died in October 1684.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="aow1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Alice</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Wandesford</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Osborne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Alice Wandesford (1593-1659)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1593">1593</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1659-12-10">10 December 1659</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Alice Wandesford was born in 1593 in Isleham, Cambridgeshire, the daughter of Hewett and Joyce Osborne of Kiveton. She married Christopher Wandesford and they had 7 children, of which 5 survived to adulthood, including Alice Thornton. She joined her husband in Dublin with her young children in 1633. Widowed suddenly in December 1640, she and her children fled back to northern England after the Irish rebellion of 1641, living from 1644 until her death at her jointure property, Hipswell Hall. She died on 10 December 1659, after falling ill on 17 November, and was buried at Catterick Church.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ps1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                  <forename>Peter</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Samways</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Peter Samways (1615-1693)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1615">1615</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1693-04">April 1693</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Peter Samways (1615-93) was born in 1615 in Eltham, Kent. He attended Westminster School and then Trinity College Cambridge, where he gained his MA in 1641. He was ordained Deacon of Rochester in 1643. A loyal monarchist, he was nevertheless presented to the rectory of Wath in the North Riding in 1658 on petition to Cromwell. On the Restoration in 1660 he was created Doctor of Divinity at Cambridge, and was made prebendary of Barneby, York in 1668. A friend of Alice Thornton and correspondent of her son-in-law Thomas Comber, he died on 6 April 1693 at Bedale and was buried in the church there.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jk1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Kearton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Kearton (died 1664)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1664-08-18">buried 18 August 1664</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Kearton (xxxx-1664) received his BA from Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge. He was ordained deacon at York in 1628, and priest in 1629. He became rector of Richmond in 1657. Alice Thornton's mother Alice Wandesford wanted him to preach at her funeral service in 1659, and in April 1660 he baptised, and then shortly afterwards buried, Alice Thornton's sixth child, William, at Easby. He was buried on 18 August 1664 at St. Mary Richmond.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="dcl1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Daphne</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Lightfoot</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Cassell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Daphne Lightfoot </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Daphne Cassell entered the service of Alice Thornton's mother, Alice Wandesford, unmarried but at some point before 1654 married George Lightfoot, her mother's steward. The couple had at least one child, a daughter named Mary. She was with Alice's sister Katherine Danby when she died after childbirth in 1645 and prayed with Alice's mother at her death bed in 1659. She and her husband were witnesses to Alice's mothers will. Daphne was a confidante of Alice's throughout the events Alice discusses in her books. She breastfed Alice's child Elizabeth for three months in 1654 when Alice was unable to produce milk. She also helped Alice with the inventory of her house when her husband died in 1668 and defended her and her family staunchly during the rumours that spread about the Thornton-Comber marriage the same year.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cd2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>8th Lord Darcy de Knayth; 1st Earl Holderness</roleName>
                  <forename>Conyers</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Darcy</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Conyers Darcy (1599-1689)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1599-01-24">24 January 1599</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1689-06-14">14 June 1689</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Conyers Darcy, 1st  Earl  of  Holdernesse, 8th Lord Darcy de Knayth (1599-1689) was born on 24 January 1599 to Sir Conyers and Dorothy Darcy. He was constable of Middleham Castle, Yorkshire, and created Earl of Holdernesse on 6 December 1682. On 14 October 1616 he married Grace,  only  daughter  and  heir  of  Thomas Rokeby,  of  Skyers. They had 6 sons and 5 daughters, only one of the sons, Conyers, surviving childhood. He died on 14 June, 1689 in Hornby, Yorkshire.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ha1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Hanna(h)?</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Ableson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Hanna(h)? Ableson </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Hannah Ableson was a servant in Alice's household.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ra1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir; Lord</roleName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Adair</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Adair (1583-1655)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1583">1583</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1655-03-01">1 March 1655</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir  Robert  Adair,  of  Ballymenna and Kinhilt (1583-1655) was born in 1583 at Ballymena , co. Antrim, to Sir William and Rosina Adair. He was  served heir  to  his  father  and  grandfather  in  the  Scotch  estates on 19 February 1629. He was knighted by Charles I and became a Royalist soldier, before switching to the Scottish parliamentarians and became a major in the Earl of Leven's Horse Regiment. He commanded the cavalry at the 1650 Battle of Dunbar. He married Jane Edmonstone, and they had 2 sons and a daughter. He died on 1  March,  1655,  and was succeeded by his eldest son.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ga1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>George</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Anderson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Anderson </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Anderson, a Scotsman, was a tutor for Alice's brother George in France when he fled there after being sequestered after the battle of Marston Moor in 1644.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cda1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Armitage</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Armitage (1612-1667)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1612-02-27">baptised 27 February 1612</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1667-01-13">buried 13 January 1667</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Armitage (1612-67) was baptised at St. Peter, Leeds on 27 February 1612, the oldest daughter and second child of Thomas and Elizabeth Danby of Farnley. She married Francis Armitage, later 1st Baronet, in 1629. They had at least 11 children, 5 of whom, 3 sons and 2 daughters, can be identified. A widow from 1644, she attended Katherine Danby, her sister-in-law, on her death bed in September 1645. She was buried on 13 January 1667 at All Saints, Wakefield.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wa1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Ayscough</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Ayscough (1648-1676)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1648-03-09">9 March 1648</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1676-11-20">buried 20 November 1676</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Ayscough of Osgoodby (1648-76) was born on 9 March 1648 to Sir William and Judith Ayscough. He (or perhaps his father) was one of the coffin bearers at William Thornton's funeral in September 1668, and he married Alice Thornton's sister-in-law, Anne Thornton, on 27 January 1676. He died within a year of marriage and was buried on 20 November 1676 at Thirkleby.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ja1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Captain</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Ashton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Ashton (1613-1642)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1613-09-19">19 September 1613</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1642-10">October 1642</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Captain John Ashton (1613-42), born on 19 September 1613 at Cuerdale Hall, Preston was the son of Radclyffe and Elizabeth Ashton. He married Anne Shuttleworth and they had one son. He was Captain of the Foot during the first English civil war which broke out in 1642. When Alice Thornton and her family fled Ireland in after the Irish Rebellion broke out in 1641, they were aided by Ashton on their journey through north-west England returning to Yorkshire. He died in October 1642 from wounds sustained at the Battle of Edge Hill.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xa1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                  <surname type="birth">Atie</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Dr Atie </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dr. Atie appears briefly in Alice's account of her mother's death, being sent to her, perhaps as a deputy, by Dr Wittie who could not attend her deathbed.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Bathurst</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Bathurst (1597-1659)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1597-08-21">baptised 21 August 1597</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1659-04-19">19 April 1659</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Bathurst (1597-1659) was baptised at Mayfield, East Sussex on 21 August 1597, the son of John and Dorothy Bathurst. John was a doctor in Goudhurst, Kent. He matriculated from Pembroke College Cambridge in 1614 and became a Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians in 1637. He was incorporated at Oxford in 1643, and acted as physician to Oliver Cromwell. He was MP for Richmond in 1656 and 1658. He married Elizabeth Willance on 27 January 1636, and they had 10 children, 7 sons and 3 daughters. Alice Thornton's mother sent her son Christopher to Dr. Bathurst at York when he suffered a distemper from grief over his father's death in November 1643, and her brother John was likewise sent to him when he dropped out of Cambridge University and moved to London in a state of melancholy. He died on 19 April 1659.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mb2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Martha</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Batte</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Martha Batte (born 1636)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1636-09-29">baptised 29 September 1636</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Martha Batte (1636-xxxx) was the daughter of John and Martha Batte. She was baptised at Birstall, Yorkshire on 29 September 1636. She and her father and brothers emigrated to a plantation in Charles County, Virginia in 1649, where she was still living in 1665, as she and her brothers were granted a land patent for transporting slaves. By 1667 she was back in Yorkshire in the service of the Countess of Sussex at Howley Hall. She was a friend of Alice Thornton's niece-by-marriage, Anne Danby, from their time in Virginia. According to Alice, Anne wanted to prevent the marriage of Thomas Comber and Nally Thornton in order for Thomas to marry Martha.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="hb1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Henry</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Best</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Henry Best (died 1674)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1674-01">January 1674</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Henry Best (xxxx-1674) was the son of George and Grace Best of Middleton Quernhow. He married Katherine Danby, Alice Thornton’s niece, after 1659. He had 2 children by Katherine, a son and a daughter. A barrister at Gray’s Inn, he died there in January 1674.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tb2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Binks</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Binks </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Binks was a poor man who warned Alice Thornton that Jeremy Smithson was plotting to abduct her after Alice refused his hand in marriage.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename>Thomas(?)</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Binlows</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas(?) Binlows </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Binlows was one of the ministers attendant at Alice Thornton's mother's funeral in 1659. He may be Thomas Binlowes, preacher at Scruton, near Northallerton, from 1655.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb5">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Borlase</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Borlase (c.1576-1648)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1576~">c. 1576</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1648-03-15">15 March 1648</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir John Borlase (c. 1576-1648) was born in Cornwall to Edward and Suzannah Borlase. He attended Cambridge University, but did not graduate, and then pursued a military career. He fought extensively in the Low Countries in the early 17th century, becoming master-general of the ordnance of Ireland in 1634, and became Lord Justice of Ireland after the death of Alice Thornton's father Christopher Wandesford in 1640 along with Sir William Parsons. He married Alice (née Edwards), widow of Thomas Ravis, bishop of London, and they had 3 sons. He died at London on 15 March 1648 and was buried at Bartholomew-the-Great.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb4">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Bishop of Derry</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Bramhall</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Bramhall (1594-1663)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1594-11-18">baptised 18 November 1594</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1663-06-25">25 June 1663</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Bramhall (1594-1663) was baptised 18 November 1594, one of six children of Peter Bramhall of Carleton, Pontefract. He graduated with a BA from Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge in 1612, and was ordained in York in 1615. On 24 June 1618, Alice Thornton's father Christopher Wandesford presented him to the rectory of South Kilvington, near Thirsk. On 10 November he married a clergyman's widow, Ellen Collingwood. The couple had 6 children, 3 sons and 3 daughters. Wandesford and Thomas Wentworth helped Bramhall secure the prebend of Huisthwaite, Yorkshire in 1632. He became Bishop of Derry, in Ireland, in May 1634, and was present at Christopher Wandesford's deathbed in December 1640. After Wandesford's death he was exiled and had returned to his native Yorkshire by 1642; and was restored in Ireland by Charles II in 1660. He died on 25 June 1663.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb6">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Colonel</roleName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Brandling</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Brandling (1617-1669)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1617">1617</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1669">1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Brandling (1617-69) was the son of Robert and Mary Brandling of Felling. He was a royalist Colonel of the Horse during the Civil War.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mb1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Mary</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Breakes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mary Breakes </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Breakes was a servant in Alice Thornton's household, who was implicated by Anne Danby and others in spreading rumours about Alice Thornton and Thomas Comber in 1668. She married William Heard some time after she left the Thorntons' service.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wb1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Brereton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Brereton (1604-1661)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1604-09-13">13 September 1604</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1661-04-07">7 April 1661</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir William Brereton, 1st Baronet, (1604–1661) was born on 13 September 1604 to William and Margaret Brereton. A Puritan who owned extensive estates in Cheshire, and Member of Parliament for Cheshire at various times between 1628 and 1653, he was commander of Parliamentarian forces in the North Midlands during the first Civil War (1642-46). He married twice; firstly, Susanna Booth in 1623, by whom he had 4 children, 3 daughters and a son; and after her death Cicely Mytton in 1641, a wealthy Staffordshire widow, by whom he had 2 more daughters.
When Christopher Wandesford's family, including a teenage Alice Thornton, fled Ireland after his death in 1640 and landed in Cheshire, they were held up on their way home to Yorkshire at Chester due to Brereton's Parliamentary forces. When the first Civil War ended in 1646, Brereton gave up his local offices, and although nominated as a judge, refused to attend the trial of Charles I in January 1649. He was elected to the Council of State in 1652 and 1653 but didn't attend frequently, living in semi-retirement in London. He resumed his seat for Cheshire when the Long Parliament was reinstated in 1659, until its dissolution in March 1660, and died on 7 April 1661.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tb1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Brockill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Brockill (c.1617-1669)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1617~">c. 1617</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1669-04-13">buried 13 April 1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Brockill (c. 1617-69), was born at Richmond, the son of John Brockill, a glover. He matriculated St John's, Cambridge in 1635 and obtained his BA in 1639. He was master of Richmond school 1642-5 and vicar of St. Mary, Hornby, from 1650-69. He married Susanna, and they had a son, Thomas, baptised in 1650. He was one of the ministers who conducted Alice Wandesford's funeral service in 1659. He was rector of Tanfield from 1664 until his death and was buried there on 13 April 1669.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>James</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Brodricke</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">James Brodricke </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">James Brodricke was Alice's brother George Wandesford's footman.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="bb1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename>Benjamin</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Browne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Benjamin Browne (1613-1681)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1613-06-28">baptised 28 June 1613</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1681-12-11">buried 11 December 1681</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Benjamin Browne (1613-81), was the son of William Browne of Buckton, baptised at Bempton, East Riding on 28 June 1613. He was educated at St. John's Cambridge (BA 1639) and instituted at Masham the same year, made vicar of Masham in 1645, sequestered in the 1650s, and restored to Masham in 1661. He was ordained priest at York in September 1662. He was buried on 11 December 1681.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb3">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Joseph</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Browning</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Joseph Browning </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Joseph Browning was a coachman who was driving a carriage containing Alice Thornton, her parents and siblings in October 1636. They were heading to Kildare, west of Dublin. The carriage was overturned on a narrow pass by a river but mercifully all passengers survived.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb7">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mrs</roleName>
                  <surname type="birth">Bucke</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mrs Bucke </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mrs Bucke was possibly a servant in Alice Thornton's household or a local woman, who advised Alice on the pearl in her daughter Nally's eye which appeared after she had recovered from small pox in April 1667.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb5">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Bullock</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Cousin Bullock </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">'Cousin Bullock' is listed as a bearer of William Thornton's coffin at his funeral on 18 September 1668. He was probably a descendant of Launcelot Bullock of Holme and Margaret Thornton, the daughter of William Thornton's great-grandmother, making him a cousin-by-marriage to Alice Thornton.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb4">
               <persName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Berridge</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Berridge </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Berridge was one of the accused in the murder of Alice Thornton's nephew Thomas Danby, allegedly over a pawned sword, near Gray's Inn, London in August 1667.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb6">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>1st Earl of Ormond</roleName>
                  <forename>James</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Butler</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">James Butler (1610-1688)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1610-10-19">19 October 1610</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1688-07-21">21 July 1688</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">James Butler (1610-88) was born on 19 October 1610 to Thomas and Elizabeth Butler. He was an Anglo-Irish statesman and first Earl of Ormond. He married Elizabeth Preston at Christmas 1629, by whom he had 10 children; 3 sons and 2 daughters surviving to adulthood. He was brought to Ireland by Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl of Strafford as head of government in Ireland in 1633 and was present at the meal where Christopher Wandesford, Alice Thornton's father became unwell in December 1640, dying soon afterwards. He witnessed Wandesford's will. He commanded the Royalist forces in Ireland during the Civil War of the 1640s and subsequent Cromwellian invasion, and became Lord Lieutenant of Ireland on the Restoration of Charles II in 1660. He died at his estate at Kingston Lacey, Dorset, on 21 July 1688.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wc1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>1st Duke of Newcastle upon Tyne</roleName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Cavendish</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Cavendish (1593-1676)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1593-12-16">baptised 16 December 1593</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1676-12-25">25 December 1676</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Cavendish, 1st Duke of Newcastle upon Tyne (1593-1676) was baptised on 16 December 1593, the son of Charles Cavendish and his second wife Catherine, their second but first surviving son. He married twice, first Elizabeth Howard by whom he had 5 children, 3 sons and 2 daughters, and later Margaret Lucas. A writer, courtier and royalist army officer, he led his battalion, the Whitecoats, under the Royalist forces of Prince Rupert at the battle of Marston Moor in 1644. The Royalist army suffered a huge defeat, and the Whitecoats lost some 4,000 troops. He died at Welbeck Abbey on Christmas Day 1676.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ksc1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lady</roleName>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Cholmondeley</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Stanhope</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Cholmondeley (died 1657)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1657-06-15">15 June 1657</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Cholmondeley (d. 1657) was the daughter of Sir John Stanhope, 1st Lord Harrington and his second wife Margaret. She married Lord Robert Cholmondeley c. 1610. Alice Thornton lists them as friendly and helpful neighbours of the family when they returned to England from Ireland in the early 1640s, staying for some time in Cheshire. She died on 15 June 1657 without issue and was buried in the chancel of Malpas parish church.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rc4">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lord; 1st Earl of Leinster</roleName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Cholmondeley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Cholmondeley (1584-1659)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1584-06-26">26 June 1584</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1659-10-02">2 October 1659</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Cholmondeley (1584-1659), 1st Earl of Leinster, was born on 26 June 1584 in Middlesex to Sir Hugh and Mary Cholmondeley. He inherited the largest landed estate in Cheshire after his father's death in 1601. He was educated at Queen's College Oxford, and married Katherine Stanhope c. 1610. They had no children. He was MP for Cheshire in 1625 and a royalist supporter of Charles I during the Civil War. Alice Thornton lists Lord and Lady Cholmondeley as friendly and helpful neighbours of the family when they returned to England from Ireland in the early 1640s, staying for some time in Cheshire. He was made Earl of Leinster in 1646. He died on 2 October 1659 and was buried next to his wife at Malpas parish church.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="uc1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Ursula</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Cholmondeley</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Ursula Cholmondeley (born 1600)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1600-03-13">baptised 13 March 1600</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ursula Cholmondeley (1600-xxxx), baptised on 13 March 1600 at Stonegrave, was the eldest daughter of Robert Thornton and his first wife, Dorothy. She was William Thornton's older half-sister. She married Marmaduke Cholmondeley of Bransby and they had a son and 2 daughters. William Thornton, on his way home from York to East Newton, stopped at Bransby Hall when he became ill with a palsy in November 1665.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="kc1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Twisleton</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Cholmondeley</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Stapleton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Cholmondeley (c.1607-1672)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1607~">c. 1607</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1672-06-14">14 June 1672</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Stapleton (c. 1607-72) was the daughter of Robert or Henry and Mary Stapleton of Wighill. She married George Twisleton, who died c. 1635, and then married Henry Cholmondeley, MP for New Malton 1641-48. They had 3 children, 2 sons and 1 daughter. Katherine was godmother to Alice Thornton's son, Robert, baptised in September 1662. She was buried on 14 June 1672 at Oswaldkirk.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jc2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Clotworthy</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Clotworthy (died 1665)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1665-09">September 1665</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Clotworthy, 1st Viscount Massereene (xxxx-1665) was an Anglo-Irish politician, son of Sir Hugh and Mary Clotworthy of Antrim. He was knighted in 1626 and married Margaret Jones, daughter of Viscount Ranelagh. They had one daughter. He was a presbyterian and opponent of Thomas Wentworth during his time as Lord Deputy of Ireland. He died in September 1665.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tc1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Comber</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Comber (1645-1699)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1645-03-19">19 March 1645</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1699-11-25">25 November 1699</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Comber (1645-99) was the son of James and Mary Comber of Westerham, Kent, born on 19 March 1645 and baptised on 23 March at the parish church. From a royalist family, he was educated at Westerham school before entering Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge in 1659. He graduated with his BA in 1663 and became curate at Stonegrave at the behest of the absentee Gilbert Bennett. He was ordained priest in September 1664 and in March 1665 he lodged with Alice Thornton and her family at East Newton for a year. After a further year of studies in Cambridge for an MA, he returned north. He married Alice Thornton’s eldest daughter, Alice (Nally), in November 1668 and in 1669 he got the living of Stonegrave; they had 9 children, with 2 sons and 2 daughters surviving him. Comber wrote several treatises and books on religious topics. He became prebendary of York in 1677, precentor at York in 1683, and Dean of Durham in 1691. He was made chaplain-in-ordinary to the joint monarchs William and Mary in 1692. He died of consumption on 25 November 1699 at East Newton and was buried at Stonegrave on 30 November.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mc1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Mary</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Cotes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mary Cotes </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Cotes was probably a servant in Alice Thornton's household who, with Hanna Ableson, cared for Katherine Thornton in September 1666 when she had the small pox.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rc2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Roger</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Covill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Roger Covill (died 1664)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1664-07-12">12 July 1664</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Roger Covill (xxxx-1664) was a solicitor based at Fremington, Swaledale. He was admitted to Inner Temple in 1629 and called to the bar in 1639. He married Anne Norton at Scruton on 17 June 1641. They had 2 daughters. He acted as Alice Thornton's solicitor, settling her estate in 1662. He was buried on 12 July 1664 at Grinton.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jc1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Crathorne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Crathorne (born c.1642)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1642~">c. 1642</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Crathorne (c. 1642-xxxx) was the son of Ralph Crathorne and his second wife, Margaret; William and Alice Thornton's nephew. He was a pall-bearer at William's funeral in 1666 along with his brother Ralph.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mtc1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Margaret</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Crathorne</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Margaret Crathorne (born 1608)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1608-05-09">baptised 9 May 1608</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Margaret Thornton Crathorne (1608-xxxx), baptised 9 May 1608 at Stonegrave, was the daughter of Robert Thornton and his first wife Dorothy. She was William Thornton's half-sister. Around 1632 she became the second wife of Ralph Crathorne of Crathorne, and they had 3 sons.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rc1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Ralph</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Crathorne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Ralph Crathorne (born c.1634)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1634~">c. 1634</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ralph Crathorne (c. 1634-xxxx) was the first son of Ralph Crathorne of Crathorne and his second wife Margaret; William Thornton's half-sister. He married Anne Tunstall, and they had three sons. He was a pall-bearer at his uncle William Thornton's funeral in 1668.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="oc1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Oliver</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Cromwell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Oliver Cromwell (1599-1658)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1599-04-25">25 April 1599</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1658-09-03">3 September 1658</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Oliver Cromwell (1599-1658), born 25 April 1599, was Lord Protector of England, Wales and Ireland during the Interregnum period of 1649 until his death in 1658. The son of Robert and Elizabeth Cromwell he was educated at Sidney Sussex College Cambridge and married Elizabeth Bourchier in 1621. They had 9 children; 5 sons and 4 daughters. He died on 3 September 1658.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rc3">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Richard</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Cromwell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Richard Cromwell (1626-1712)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1626-10-04">4 October 1626</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1712-07-12">12 July 1712</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Richard Cromwell (1626-1712): born 4 October 1626 was the third son, and fourth child, of Oliver and Elizabeth Cromwell. On his father's death in September 1658 he was elected Lord Protector of England, a position he held until 1659, when the Protectorate collapsed. He married Dorothy Maijor on 1 May 1649, and they had nine children, only 4 of whom survived to adulthood. He died on 12 July 1712.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rd2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Daggett</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Daggett (died 1644)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1644-08-19">buried 19 August 1644</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Daggett of Howe studied at Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge, then went to Oxford soon after in 1612. He became Rector of Kirklington in April 1639. Alice and her family stayed with him at Kirklington in 1644, unable to get to York or their home at Hipswell due to the ongoing Civil War. He died shortly after this and was buried at Kirklington on 19 August 1644.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="acd1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mrs</roleName>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Danby</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Culpeper</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Danby (1630-1695)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1630-09-16">16 September 1630</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1695-11-11">11 November 1695</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Danby was born on 16 September 1630 to John and Katherine Culpeper. While in Virginia, c.1652, she married Christopher Danby, son of Katherine and Thomas Danby, making her Alice's niece-in-law. A did not approve of the match. By the time their first son, Abstrupus, was born in 1655, they had moved back to Yorkshire and a daughter, Francelia, followed in 1659. By the late 1660s Anne Danby was living with Alice Thornton and her family at East Newton and, in 1668, was allegedly the source of rumours about Alice and Thomas Comber, resulting in her being evicted from the household by William Thornton. She died on 11 November 1695 and was buried at York.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ad1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Alice</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Alice Danby (born 1641)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1641-05-22">22 May 1641</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Alice Danby (1641-xxxx) was born 22 May 1641 at Greenwich and baptised on 5 June at St. Alfege's. She was the daughter of Thomas Danby and Katherine Wandesford, and was Alice Thornton's niece.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cd1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Francelia (Celia)</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Goodrich</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Parker</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Francelia (Celia) Parker (c.1659-1699?)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1659~">c. 1659</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1699-03?">after March 1699</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Francelia Parker (c. 1659-99) was the daughter of Christopher and Anne Danby; Alice Thornton's great-niece. Although born in Leeds and brought up in Yorkshire, she moved back to colonial Virginia where her parents had met, and married Joseph Goodrich in or around 1685. They had 2 sons before his death in 1694. She married Thomas Parker in 1694. She died shortly after 25 March 1699 in James City County, Virginia, when her will was witnessed.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cd4">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Danby (1632-1689)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1632-07-30">30 July 1632</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1689">1689</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Danby (1632-89) was the second son of Thomas and Katherine Danby, born 30 July 1632 at St-Martin-in-the-Fields, London; Alice Thornton's nephew. After his mother's death in 1645 the family emigrated to Virginia and around 1652 he married Anne Culpeper, perhaps without his father's permission. Christopher and Anne moved back to Yorkshire and had two children, a son and a daughter. On his older brother Thomas's murder at Gray’s Inn in 1667, he became heir to his father's estate, but granted this estate to his son Abstrupus in the same year. He died in 1689.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cd5">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Charles</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Charles Danby (1643-1672)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1643-06-02">2 June 1643</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1672-04">April 1672</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles Danby (1643-72) was the son of Thomas and Katherine (née Wandesford) Danby, born on 2 June 1643 at Snape; Alice Thornton's nephew. He was admitted to Gray's Inn in 1664, and died without issue in April 1672.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fd2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Francis</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Francis Danby (1640-1645)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1640-03-22">22 March 1640</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1645-07-09">9 July 1645</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Francis Danby (1640-45) was the son of Thomas and Katherine Danby, born on 22 March 1640 at Farnley; Alice Thornton's nephew. He died in July 1645 and was buried at  St. Michael the Archangel, Well. Thomas and Katherine's youngest son, Francis, born in August 1645, was named after him.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="med1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Madam</roleName>
                  <forename>Margaret</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Danby</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Eure</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Margaret Danby (c.1640-1688)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1640~">c. 1640</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1688-06-23">23 June 1688</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Margaret Danby (c. 1640-88) was the daughter of William and Margaret Eure of Ingleby. She married Thomas Danby, son and heir of Thomas and Katherine Danby of Thorpe Perrow, in 1659; Alice Thornton's niece-in-law. They had 3 children, a son and 2 daughters. Widowed on the murder of her husband near Gray's Inn in August 1667, she spent much of her widowed life in conflict with other members of the Danby family over her husband's estate. Alice's intervention in Margaret's conflicts with her sister-in-law Anne Danby perhaps led to the slanders against Alice and Nally Thornton by Anne Danby in 1668. She died on 23 June 1688.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="td3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Danby (c.1610-1660)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1610~">c. 1610</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1660-08-05">5 August 1660</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Thomas Danby (c. 1610-60) was the son of Christopher and Frances Danby of Farnley. A ward of Christopher Wandesford after his father's death in 1624 and a protracted legal dispute, he entered St John's College Cambridge in 1627. He married Christopher Wandesford’s daughter, Katherine, in 1630, making him Alice Thornton's brother-in-law. He was knighted in 1633 and became Sheriff of York in 1637, and elected MP for Richmond in 1640. He was banned from sitting in Parliament after 1642 and was fined heavily for his loyalty to Charles I. He and Katherine had 10 children, 7 of whom survived to adulthood. After his wife's death in 1645, he relocated to Virginia where he held lands, moving back to Yorkshire in the 1650s. He died in York on 5 August 1660.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="td4">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Danby (1631-1667)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1631-08-17">17 August 1631</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1667-07-31">31 July 1667</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Danby (1631-67) was born on 17 August 1631 in Westminster, the oldest son and heir of Sir Thomas and Katherine Danby and Alice Thornton's nephew. He married Margaret Eure in 1658, and they had 3 children, a son and 2 daughters. In 1660 he became MP for Malton and in 1661 he became the first Mayor of Leeds. He was killed in a tavern brawl near Gray's Inn, London, on 31 July 1667. William Berridge, Thomas Jenney and John Ogle were tried for his murder. His brother Christopher became heir to the family estate, which was quite quickly passed to Christopher's son Abstrupus.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cd3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>2nd Earl Holdernesse; Baron Conyers</roleName>
                  <forename>Conyers</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Darcy</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Conyers Darcy (1622-1692)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1622-03-03">baptised 3 March 1622</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1692-12-13">13 December 1692</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Conyers Darcy, 2nd Earl Holdernesse (1622-92), baptised 3 March 1622 at St. Michael le Belfrey, York, was the son and heir of Conyers and Grace Darcy. Educated at University College, Oxford (1637), he entered Gray's Inn in 1640. He married 4 times: to Catherine Fane, Frances Howard, Frances Seymour and Elizabeth Frescheville. With Frances Howard he had 6 children, 3 sons and 3 daughters. He was elected MP for Boroughbridge in 1660, and became a peer in 1680, as Baron Conyers. He died at Aston on 13 December 1692.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="dbd1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Dorothy</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Darcy</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Belasyse</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Dorothy Darcy (1572-1653)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1572">1572</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1653-05-11">11 May 1653</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dorothy Belasyse (1572-1653) was the daughter of Henry and Ursula Belasyse. She married Conyers Darcy, 4th Lord Conyers, on 2 May 1594 at Coxwold, with whom she had 12 children, 6 sons and 6 daughters. She died on 11 May 1653 in Hornby.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="hd1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Henry</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Darcy</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Henry Darcy (1610-1662)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1610-10-19">baptised 19 October 1610</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1662-04-28">28 April 1662</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Henry Darcy (1610-62) was the third son of Conyers and Dorothy Darcy, baptised 19 October 1610 at Hornby. He married Mary Scrope in 1628, and they had 10 children. He died on 28 April 1662, and was buried at St. Olave's, York.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>James</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Darcy</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">James Darcy (1617-c.1673)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1617-08">August 1617</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1673~">c. 1673</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">James Darcy (1617-c.  1673) was the sixth son of Conyers and Dorothy Darcy. He married Isabel Wyvill. They had 7 children, 3 sons and 4 daughters. He was elected MP for Richmond in 1660, but was not re-elected in 1661, being then appointed to Master of the Royal Stud. He died after 13 October 1673, when his will is dated.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fd3">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Francis</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Darley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Francis Darley (1605-1679)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1605">1605</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1679-12-31">buried 31 December 1679</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Francis Darley (1605-79) was the son Sir Richard Darley of Buttercrambe, Yorkshire and his second wife, Elizabeth Gates. He was William Thornton's uncle, the younger brother of Elizabeth Gates (née Darley, then Thornton). He was an executor of Alice Wandesford's will in 1659. He was buried at Buttercrambe on 31 December 1679.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rd1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Richard</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Darley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Richard Darley (c.1602-1681)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1602~">c.1602</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1681-02-02">2 February 1681</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Richard Darley (c.1602-81) was the third son of Sir Richard and Elizabeth Darley of Buttercrambe, Yorkshire. He was William Thornton's uncle, a younger brother of Elizabeth (née Darley, then Thornton) Gates. He married Elizabeth Hildyard, the niece of Catherine Hansby, Alice Thornton's great-grandmother, on 20 December 1632 at Bishop-Wilton, York. Elizabeth and Richard had 6 children, 5 sons and a daughter.  He died on 2 February 1681.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ddl1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Don de Lan</forename>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Don de Lan </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Don de Lan was a French page in the service of Robert Meredith, Chancellor of the Irish Exchequer. When dining at Sir Robert's in Dublin in 1637, Dan de Lon swung Alice too hard and she fell on the floor.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="etd1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Denton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth Denton (died 1669)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1669-02-14">14 February 1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth Thornton (xxxx-1669) was the first child of Robert and Elizabeth Thornton; William Thornton's older sister and Alice Thornton's sister-in-law. She married John Denton, minister of Oswaldkirk, on 8 May 1654 at East Newton. They had at least 2 sons. She was buried on 14 February 1669.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Denton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Denton (1626-1709)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1626-02-02">baptised 2 February 1626</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1709-01-14">14 January 1709</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Denton (1626-1709) was baptised on 2 February 1626 at Kildwick-in-Craven, the son of John and Elizabeth Denton of Steeton. He studied at Clare College Cambridge, gaining his MA in 1653. He became minister of Oswaldkirk in 1654. The same year he married Elizabeth Thornton, older sister of William Thornton. He was ejected from Oswaldkirk in 1662 for nonconformity, after which he served as curate at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave, under Alice Thornton's future son-in-law, Thomas Comber.  Elizabeth died in 1669 and Denton remarried. His second wife, also Elizabeth, died in 1715. With Elizabeth Thornton he had 1 or 2 sons, and with his second wife, also Elizabeth, he had 2 sons and 2 daughters. He died on January 14 1709 and was buried on 16 January in the north aisle of Stonegrave.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd3">
               <persName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Denton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Denton (born 1655)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1655-09-05">baptised 5 September 1655</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Denton (1655-xxxx) was the son of John Denton and Elizabeth Thornton, baptised on 5 September 1655 at Oswaldkirk; William Thornton's nephew. He attended Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge, where he received his BA in 1677.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wd1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Denton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Denton </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Denton was probably the son of John Denton and Elizabeth Thornton.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd4">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>James</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Dillon</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">James Dillon (c.1600-1669?)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1600~">c. 1600</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1669?">after 1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir James Dillon (c. 1600-c. 1669) was the youngest son of Theobald and Eleanor Dillon. An army officer, he became Commissioner of Ireland in 1627, and was elected MP for Co. Westmeath in 1634. Commissioned by Charles I in 1640 to recruit regiments from disbanded soldiers in Ireland, he was said to have been involved in the 1641 plot to seize Dublin castle. He married twice, first Elizabeth Plunkett in the 1630s, with whom he had 2 sons. Elizabeth died before 1653. His second marriage, in the early 1660s, was to Mary Ridge, a childless widow. He died after 1669.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd5">
               <persName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Dodsworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Dodsworth (1617-1662)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1617">1617</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1662">1662</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Dodsworth (1617-62) was the son of John and Frances Dodsworth of Thornton Watlass; Alice's Thornton's cousin. Alice's great-great-grandfather George Bowes of Streatlam was John's great-grandfather. He was also related to Alice by marriage; since he married Frances Lowther, aunt of Alice's sister-in-law, Christopher's wife Eleanor. John and Frances had 2 children, John and Helen. He died in 1662.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xe1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <surname type="birth">Edrington</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Edrington </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Edrington who attended Alice Osborne Wandesford's funeral may be the vicar of Langton who graduated from St. John's Cambridge in 1644; or a William Etherington who was instituted at St. Agatha's, Gilling, in 1665.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="kf1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mrs</roleName>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Farrer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Farrer </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Farrer was a friend of Anne Danby whom Anne tried to set up with Thomas Comber to prevent a match with Alice Thornton's daughter Alice (Nally). Anne Danby's letter to Parson Farrer, also mentioned in Alice's books, indicates that Katherine is a relation of his.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gf1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>George</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Farrer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Farrer </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Farrer was probably the minister of Thornton Watlass, made rector of St. Mary the Virgin in 1635. He may have studied at Alban Hall, Oxford in 1625 ,or he may have studied at Cambridge. Jackson suggests he may have been a chaplain at the Malton household of the Eures.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ef1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Edward</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Fleetwood</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Edward Fleetwood (c.1534-1604)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1534~">c. 1534</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1604-10-12">12 October 1604</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edward Fleetwood (c. 1534-1604) was the son of Thomas Fleetwood and his second wife Bridget. He was the brother of Alice Thornton's maternal grandmother, Joyce Osborne. He studied at St. Alban Hall, Oxford (MA 1575), and married Christian Wentworth. The couple had at least 4 children. He was instituted rector of Wigan in 1571; a position he held until his death on 12 October 1604.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mf1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Miles</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Fleetwood</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Miles Fleetwood (1576-1641)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1576-10-01">baptised 1 October 1576</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1641-03-08">8 March 1641</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Miles Fleetwood of Aldwinkle (1576-1641), was baptised on 1 October 1576. He was the nephew of Alice Thornton's maternal grandmother Joyce, by her brother William Fleetwood. He was MP in several constituencies across England in the 1620s and 1630s, and was elected MP for Hindon, Wiltshire, in the Short Parliament of 1640, which he held until his death on 8 March 1641.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jf2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Jane</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Flouer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Jane Flouer </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Jane Flouer was a servant in Alice's household.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jf1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Frescheville</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Frescheville (1606-1682)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1606">1606</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1682-03-31">31 March 1682</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Frescheville, first Baron Frescheville (1606-82), was the son of Sir Peter Frescheville and his first wife, Joyce. He was Alice Thornton's uncle, the younger half-brother of her mother Alice Wandesford. He was educated at Magdalen Hall Oxford and the Middle Temple (1624). He married twice; firstly Bruce Nicholls, who died in 1629 without issue and then Sarah Harington with whom he had 3 daughters. He was elected MP for Derbyshire in 1628, though this ended a year later when Charles I abolished parliament. He was Lieutenant of Derbyshire from 1630-42, and then became a Captain in the Royalist army. He was created Baron in 1665 and died without a male heir to inherit his baronetcy on 31 March 1682.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pf1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Peter</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Frescheville</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Peter Frescheville (1575-1634)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1575-03-14">baptised 14 March 1575</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1634-04-07">7 April 1634</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Peter Frescheville (1575-1634) was baptised 14 March 1575, the eldest son of Peter Frescheville of Staveley and his second wife Margaret. He sat in the House of Commons as MP for Derbyshire in 1601 and in 1621-22, and built Staveley Hall in 1604. He married twice, first Joyce Osborne (nee Fleetwood), widow of Hewett Osborne, with whom he had 3 children, a son and 2 daughters; and secondly Isabel Neville who died without issue. His marriage to Joyce made him Alice Thornton's maternal step-grandfather. He died on 9 April 1634 and was buried at Staveley.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="sg1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Susanna</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Graham</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Washington</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Susanna Graham (1618-1699)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1618-11-15">baptised 15 November 1618</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1699-02-26">26 February 1699</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Susanna Washington Grahame (1618-99) was the daughter of William and Anne Washington, baptised 15 November 1618 at St-Martin-in-the-Fields, London. She married Ranald Graham of Lewisham c. 1640. The couple purchased Nunnington Hall in Ryedale in 1655, and Ranald became Justice of the Peace of the North Riding of Yorkshire in 1662. This brought Susanna into the social circle of Alice Thornton, who counted her as a friend. She was godmother to Alice's youngest daughter and eighth child Joyce, born in 1665. She died on 26 February 1699 and was buried in the parish church at Lewisham.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jh1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Joseph</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Hall</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Joseph Hall (1574-1656)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1574-07-01">1 July 1574</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1656-09-08">8 September 1656</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Joseph Hall (1574-1656) was the son of John and Winifred Hall, born on 1 July 1574 at Bristow Park, Ashby-de-la-Zouch. He was a religious writer, satirist, and became Bishop of Exeter (1627) and Norwich (1647). He married Elizabeth (née Winniff) in 1603 with whom he had 8 children, 6 sons and 2 daughters. He died on 8 September 1656.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xh1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <surname type="birth">Hubert</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Hubert </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Hubert, a man of Skerries, Dublin, sent boats to assist the Wandesford family's ship during a perilous crossing of the Irish Sea back to Dublin in 1639. Hubert had previously been helped by Christopher Wandesford as Justice of the Peace, who had decided a law suit in his favour.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ah1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Hutton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Hutton </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Hutton may be the daughter of Thomas Wentworth's sister Margaret and her husband Richard Hutton. Alice describes her as a 'cousin' – a kinship that could be claimed via great-great-grandfather George Bowes, to whom both the Wandesfords and Huttons were related.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xi1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Captain</roleName>
                  <surname type="birth">Innes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Captain Innes </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Captain Innes was an officer in the Scottish army who was stationed at Alice's mother's property after the battle of Marston Moor in summer 1644. He pursued Alice aggressively for her hand in marriage and even plotted to abduct her with his men at one point. Possibly the same a John Innis who fought at the Battle of Dunbar in 1650.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rj1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Ralph</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Janson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Ralph Janson </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ralph Janson of Thorpe was present at the wedding of Alice and William Thornton in 1651. He and Alice had previously nearly drowned crossing the Swale on a journey to Alice's aunt Anne Norton's house at St Nicholas in 1646.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tj1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Jenney</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Jenney </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Jenney was implicated in the murder of Alice Thornton's nephew Thomas Danby at Gray's Inn in July 1667, but was pardoned and released from jail in October 1667.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jl2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Lambert</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Lambert (1619-1684)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1619-09-07">7 September 1619</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1684-03-01">1 March 1684</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Lambert (1619-84) was born on 7 September 1619 to Josias Lambert and his second or third wife, Anne. He was a Parliamentarian general during the English Civil War. He married Frances Lister on 10 September 1639, and they had 10 children, 3 of whom survived to adulthood. He died on 1 March 1684.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="el1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Ed(ward) (mund)</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Lassells</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Ed(ward) (mund) Lassells </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edward or Edmund Lassells was a coffin-bearer at the funeral of William Thornton in September 1668. Alice Thornton describes him as a cousin: her paternal aunt Eleanor had married George Lassells, and so this Edward/Edmund may have been a descendant of theirs. Perhaps the same Edward Lassells who was buried on 22 August 1675 at St. Michael-le-Belfrey, York.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wl2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Laud</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Laud (1573-1645)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1573-10-07">7 October 1573</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1645-01-10">10 January 1645</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Laud (1573-1645), Archbishop of Canterbury, was born on born on 7th October 1573 in Reading to William and Lucy Laud. He was educated at Reading school and then Oxford University and elected Archbishop of Canterbury in 1633. A royalist, he was executed on 10 January 1645.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rl2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Richard</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Legard</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Richard Legard (1607-c.1680)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1607-03-15">baptised 15 March 1607</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1680-01~">c. January 1680</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Richard Legard (1607-c. 1680) was the second son of John and Elizabeth Legard, baptised at Ganton on 15 March 1607. He was related to Alice Thornton via Alice's great-great-grandfather George Bowes, who married Dorothy Mallory. A barrister at the Middle Temple, he was admitted to Gray's Inn on 14 March 1625. He married Elizabeth, the daughter or widow of John Pierson of Mowthorpe on 14 August 1666, but had no issue. He was a Royalist captain during the Civil War, and was godfather to Alice Thornton's eighth child and youngest daughter, Joyce, born and baptised in September 1665. He died c. 10 January 1680 when his will was witnessed.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xl2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>General; 1st Lord Newark</roleName>
                  <forename>David</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Leslie</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">David Leslie (1601-1682)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1601">1601</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1682-02">February 1682</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">David Leslie, 1st Lord Newark (1601-82), the son of Patrick and Jean Leslie, was an army officer in the employ of Alexander Leslie, 1st Earl Leven. A key figure in the parliamentarian success at the battle of Marston Moor in July 1644, he was stationed in Yorkshire, when Alice Thornton and her mother complained to him about Captain Innes, a soldier who was harassing them due to Alice's refusal to become romantically involved with him. He married Jane Yorke and they had 9 children; 3 sons and 6 daughters. He was elevated to the title of First Lord Newark by Charles II. He died in February 1682.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gl1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>George</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Lightfoot</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Lightfoot </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Lightfoot was a servant in the household of Alice Wandesford, Alice Thornton's mother. He married another of Alice's mother's servants, Daphne Cassell, before 1645, and they had at least one child, a daughter named Mary. A literate man, he and Daphne were witnesses to Alice Thornton's mother's will in 1659.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="al1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Loftus</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Loftus (c.1626-1659)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1626~">c. 1626</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1659-04-04">4 April 1659</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Loftus (c. 1626-59) was the daughter of Robert and Eleanor Loftus, and the granddaughter of Adam Loftus, Lord Chancellor of Ireland (c. 1568-1643). She and her parents lived in the household of Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl Strafford, at Dublin in the late 1630s, when she kept company with a young Alice Thornton and Wentworth's daughters Anne and Arabella. She married Richard Lennard Barrett c. 1653 and had 4 children, 2 sons and 2 daughters. She died on 4 April 1659.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="el2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>2nd Viscount Elye</roleName>
                  <forename>Edward</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Loftus</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Edward Loftus (c.1598-1680)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1598~">c. 1598</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1680-04-11">11 April 1680</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edward Loftus, 2nd Viscount Elye (c. 1598-1680) was the second son of Adam and Sarah Loftus. His father was Lord Chancellor of Ireland. He married Jane Lindley, and through her inherited Middleham Castle, Yorkshire, where Alice Thornton's sister Katherine Danby gave birth to her penultimate child Edward in August 1644. The Loftus, Wentworth and Wandesford families were close associates in Ireland. Edward and Jane had 2 children, a son and a daughter. He died on 11 April 1680.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rl3">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Loftus</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Loftus (1614?-c.1672)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1614?">1614(?)</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1672-08-29~">c. 29 August 1672</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Loftus of Waitwith (1614(?)-1672) was possibly born in 1614 at St. Mary, Richmond to William Loftus. A servant of Alice Thornton's mother Alice Wandesford, he was present at the wedding of Alice and William Thornton in 1651. He had 4 daughters and a son. He may have been an investor in the lead mining and smelting that was taking place in Thorpe Edge in 1656. His will, dated 29 August 1672, shows that he owed money to Christopher Wandesford, Alice Thornton's brother. He was buried at Hudswell.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wl1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Lowcock</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Lowcock (died 1678)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1678-07-31">31 July 1678</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Lowcock (xxxx-1678) was rector of All Saints, Nunnington from 1658 until his death in 1678. He baptised Alice Thornton's son Robert in 1662 at the family home in East Newton.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cm1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>2nd Baron Enniskillen</roleName>
                  <forename>Connor</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Maguire</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Connor Maguire (1616-1645)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1616">1616</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1645-02-20">20 February 1645</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Connor Maguire, 2nd Baron Enniskillen (1616-45) was the eldest son of Brian Roe and Rose Maguire. He attended Oxford University but did not graduate, and on his father's death in 1632 he became 2nd Baron. He married Mary Fleming and they had 1 son. As a member of the House of Lords in Ireland, he was one of the conspirators in the failed plot to seize Dublin Castle during the Irish rebellion of 1641, and was imprisoned in the Tower of London. He escaped for five weeks in 1644 along with his co-conspirator Hugh Óg MacMahon, but was recaptured, stood trial and executed at Tyburn on 20 February 1645.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="hm1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Hugh Óg</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">MacMahon</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Hugh Óg MacMahon (c.1606-1644)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1606/1607">1606/1607</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1644-11-22">22 November 1644</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Hugh Óg MacMahon (1606/07-44) was a younger son of Brian Hugh Óg MacMahon and his wife Mary. He was an Irish conspirator in the failed 1641 plot to seize Dublin Castle during the Irish Rebellion, and it was his drunken confession to his Protestant foster brother Owen Connolly that brought down the plot. He was imprisoned in the Tower of London along with co-conspirator Conor Maguire. They escaped for five months in August 1644 but were captured. He was put on trial on 13 November 1644, and executed at Tyburn on 22 November.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="em1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                  <forename>Edmund</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Mainwaring</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Edmund Mainwaring (1579-c.1643)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1579">1579</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1643~">c. 1643</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edmund Mainwaring (1579-c. 1643) was the second son of Randle and Margaret (née Fitton) Mainwaring of Over Peover, Cheshire. He matriculated Brasenose College, Oxford in 1594 and All Souls in 1600. He married Jane, and they had 3 children, a daughter and 2 sons, who were baptised at York. A civil lawyer, he held various positions before becoming Chancellor of Chester in 1634. He died c. 1643.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xm2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mrs</roleName>
                  <forename>Jane</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Mainwaring</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Jane Mainwaring </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Jane Mainwaring was the wife of Edmund Mainwaring. Her birth name is unknown but she is thought to have come from York. She and Edmund married before 1614 had 3 children, a daughter and 2 sons.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xm3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Captain</roleName>
                  <surname type="birth">Mainwaring</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Captain Mainwaring </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Captain Mainwaring could be William Mainwaring, son of Edmund Mainwaring, killed during the Siege of Chester in 1645; or Philip Mainwaring, son of Randle Mainwaring and Jane (née Smith), who is referred to as a 'captaine of the horse'. Both were involved in the defence of Chester.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rm1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Meredith</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Meredith (c.1597-1668)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1597~">c. 1597</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1668-10-17">17 October 1668</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Meredith (c. 1597-1668) was the son of Richard and Sarah Meredith. His father was Bishop of Leighlin. He married Anne Usher, and they had 3 sons. He served as Chancellor of the Exchequer of Ireland. He and Anne held a Greenhills estate in Kildare. He died on 17 October 1668 and was buried in the family vault at St. Patrick's Cathedral, Dublin.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mm1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Margery</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Millbanke</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Margery Millbanke </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Margery Millbanke was a servant in Alice Thornton's household.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gm1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>General; 1st Duke of Albermarle</roleName>
                  <forename>George</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Monck</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Monck (1608-1670)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1608-12-06">6 December 1608</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1670-01-01">1 January 1670</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Monck (1608-70) born 6 December 1608 at Great Potheridge, Devon, was the fourth son of Sir Thomas Monck, landowner in Devon and his wife Elizabeth. He volunteered in the English expedition against Cadiz in 1625, which was the beginning of a very successful military career. A colonel in the Royalist army, he landed in Dublin in 1642 to quell the Irish uprising. He  married Anne Clarges in 1653, and they had 1 son. He died on 1 January 1670.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pn1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Philip</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Nesbit</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Philip Nesbit (died 1663)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1663-10-15">buried 15 October 1663</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Philip Nesbit (xxxx-1663); son of Philip and Elizabeth Nesbit of York. He received his Cambridge BA and MA from Corpus Christi in 1638 and 1641, and held the rectorship of Kirklington from 1649-62. He married Susan Hemmingway and they had 6 children, 4 sons and 2 daughters, 5 of whom survived childhood. He was removed from the rectorship of Kirklington in 1662 for refusing to subscribe to the Act of Uniformity. He died the next year, according to Alice Thornton by 'vomiting up his very excrements', and was buried at St. Martins, York on 15 October 1663.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rn1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Nettleton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Nettleton </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Nettleton was a creditor of Sir Christopher Wandesford, Alice Thornton's father. William Thornton inherited this debt via his marriage to Alice. Possibly Robert Nettleton of Thornhill Lees who died in 1673.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cn1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Norton (born 1651)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1651">1651</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Norton (c1651-xxxx) was the third son of Maulger and Anne Norton and Anne; Alice Thornton's first cousin. He was still alive in 1685 when he sold the family home of St. Nicholas, Richmond. He had a daughter, Anne.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wn1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Norton (1627-1666)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1627">1627</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1666-12">December 1666</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Norton (1627(?)-66) was the son of Maulger and Anne Norton; Alice Thornton's first cousin. He was admitted to Gray's Inn on 2 September 1649, and was murdered in December 1666 in London.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jo1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Ogle</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Ogle </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Ogle was implicated in the murder of Alice Thornton's nephew Thomas Danby at Gray's Inn in 1667, but was pardoned and released from jail in October 1667.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="awo1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Middleton</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Osborne</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Walmesley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Osborne (died 1666)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1666-08-20">buried 20 August 1666</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Walmesley (xxxx-1666) was the daughter of Thomas Walmesley of Dunkenhalgh and his first wife Eleanor. She married William Middleton and had no issue; on his death she married (before 1630) Edward Osborne, Alice Thornton's maternal uncle, and became his second wife. They had a son, Thomas. She was buried on 20 August 1666 at Harthill.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ho1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Hewett</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Osborne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Hewett Osborne (1567-1599)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1567-03-13">baptised 13 March 1567</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1599-09">September 1599</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Hewett Osborne (1567-1599) was baptised on 13 March 1567, the son of Sir Edward and Anna Osborne; Alice Thornton's maternal grandfather. A landowner and soldier, he married Joyce Fleetwood, and they had a son and a daughter. He owned lands at Kiveton, Yorkshire, but lived in Essex. He died in September 1599, and Joyce remarried Sir Peter Frescheville.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jfo1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lady</roleName>
                  <forename>Joyce</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Osborne</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Frescheville</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Fleetwood</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Joyce Frescheville (1569-1619)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1569">1569</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1619-04-16?">16 April(?) 1619</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Joyce Fleetwood (1569-1619) was the daughter of Sir Thomas Fleetwood of The Vache and his second wife, Bridget; maternal grandmother of Alice Thornton. She married Sir Hewett Osborne of Kiveton on 26 December 1588 and they had 2 children, Edward and Alice. Hewett died in 1599, and on 18 October 1604 she married Sir Peter Frescheville, and they had 3 children. She died on 16 April 1619 and was buried at St. John the Baptist, Staveley, Derbyshire.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cp1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Parkes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Parkes </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Parkes attended St. John's College Cambridge where he graduated with an MA in 1663. He was vicar of Catterick and minister of the chapel at Hipswell, Bolton-super-Swale and Hudswell.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jp1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Payton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Payton (1561-1616)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1561">1561</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1616-12-19">19 December 1616</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir John Payton (1561-1616) was  the son of Robert and Elizabeth Payton. He married Alice Osborne, sister of Hewett Osborne; making him Alice Thornton's maternal great-uncle by marriage. John and Alice had 6 sons and 7 daughters. He was twice elected MP for Cambridgeshire, in 1593 and in 1604, and died on 19 December 1616.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wp1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Parsons</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Parsons (c.1570-c.1650)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1570~">c. 1570</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1650-01/1650-02">January 1650/February 1650</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Parsons (c. 1570-1650) was the son of James and Catherine Parsons. He became one of the Lord Justices of Ireland after the death of Alice Thornton's father Christopher Wandesford in 1640 until 1642. He had previously been Surveyor General of Ireland and an MP for County Wicklow. He married Elizabeth Lany and they had 12 children, 5 sons and 7 daughters. He died in January or February 1650 and is buried at St. Margaret's, Westminster.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jp2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>John</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Plummer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Plummer </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Plummer discovered the body of George Wandesford, Alice Thornton's brother, near Catterick Bridge on the river Swale in 1651.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ftp1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Frances</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Portington</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Frances Portington (died 1705)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1705-03-11">buried 11 March 1705</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Frances Thornton (xxxx-1705) was the daughter of Robert and Elizabeth Thornton, and was the youngest sister of Alice Thornton's husband William. She became the third wife of Timothy Portington of Malton on 27 July 1663, and they had 1 son. She was buried on 11 March 1705.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tp1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Timothy</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Portington</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Timothy Portington (c.1630-1697)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1630~">c. 1630</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1697-06-26">26 June 1697</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Timothy Portington (c. 1630-1697) was the son of Francis and Ellen Portington. An apothecary in New Malton, he was married three times; to Mary Pye (d. 1654), Mary Ruddock (d. 1662) and Frances Thornton; the younger sister of Alice Thornton's husband William. He had a daughter with Mary Ruddock and a son with Frances. He died on 26 June 1697.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xr1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <surname type="birth">Raines</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Raines </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Raines was a man to whom William Thornton was in debt along with his brother-in-law Timothy Portington. He could be John Raynes of Appleton-le-Street, west of Malton, who held the manor of Malton Priory until 1665, or Thomas Raynes, an attorney and Lord Mayor of York in the 1660s.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gr1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>George</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Radcliffe</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Radcliffe (1593-1657)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1593-04-21">baptised 21 April 1593</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1657">1657</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir George Ratcliffe (1593-1657)  was baptised on 21 April 1593, the son of Nicholas and Margaret Ratcliffe. He was educated at University College Oxford and entered the bar at Gray's Inn c. 1618. He was briefly engaged to the only daughter of John Finch but she died age 10 in 1621. He married Anne Trappes at Thornhill, York on 21 February 1622. A cousin-by-marriage through Anne of Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl Strafford, he was part of Strafford's Irish administration 1633-40, and was imprisoned in Dublin Castle after being tried for treason in 1640. George and Anne had a son. After his release in 1642 he spent much of his time in the Netherlands, and died in 1657.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mr2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Martha</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Richison</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Martha Richison </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Martha Richison was a witness at Alice and William Thornton's wedding in 1651.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jr1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Jane</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Rimer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Jane Rimer </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Jane Rimer was a midwife who, in 1654, helped Alice Thornton's young daughter Nally through a fit.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ar1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Robinson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Robinson </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Robinson was a maid in the Thornton household whom Alice saved from choking on a goose bone in 1661.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mr1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Matthew</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Robinson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Matthew Robinson (1628-1694)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1628-12-14">baptised 14 December 1628</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1694-11-27">27 November 1694</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Matthew Robinson (1628-94) was baptised at Rokeby on 14 December 1628, the third son of Thomas and Frances Robinson. He graduated from Cambridge in 1652 and was appointed vicar of St. Lambert, Burneston in 1651, which he held for 40 years. He married Jane Pickering on 12 October 1657. The marriage had no issue. He died at Ripley on 27 November 1694 and was buried at Burneston.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xr2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <surname type="birth">Robinson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Robinson </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr. Robinson was possibly Thomas Robinson of Easby, who held land in the Richmond area.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rr1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Prince and count of the Palatinate, Duke of Cumberland</roleName>
                  <forename>Rupert</forename>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Prince Rupert (1619-1682)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1619-12-18">18 December 1619</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1682-11-29">29 November 1682</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Prince Rupert of the Palatinate, Duke of Cumberland (1619-82) was born on 18 December 1619 to Frederick V of the Palatinate and Countess Louisa Juliana of Nassau. One of the main military commanders in the Wars of the Three Kingdoms, he never married, but had 2 children, a son with Francesca Bard (to whom his marriage is disputed), and a daughter with Margaret Hughes. He died on 29 November 1682.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="aws1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Countess of Sussex</roleName>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Savile</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Overton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wake</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Overton (1647-1679)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1647-01-19">baptised 19 January 1647</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1679">1679</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Overton (1647-79) was baptised 19 January 1647, the daughter of Robert and Mabel Wake. She married James Savile, 2nd Earl of Sussex, and they had a son, James, who did not survive infancy. After his death in 1671 she married Fairfax Overton in April 1674. She died in 1679.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ls1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Laurence</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Sayer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Laurence Sayer (born c.1632)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1632~">c. 1632</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Laurence Sayer (b. c. 1632) was a member of a recusant family in Worsall, Northallerton, whose estates had been forfeited in the 1650s for his father Laurence Sayer's recusancy and delinquency. Laurence Sayer junior borrowed heavily to buy back the estates. He is possibly the same Laurence Sayer who married Catherine Burdon in 1690, who went on to have a son, Robert.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rs1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Richard</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Shuttleworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Richard Shuttleworth (1587-1669)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1587">1587</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1669">1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Richard Shuttleworth (1587-1699) was the son of Thomas and Anne Shuttleworth. In 1607 he inherited Gawthorpe Hall from his uncle Lawrence Shuttleworth. He married Fleetwood Barton with whom he had 12 children, 8 sons and 4 daughters. He may also have married Judith Thorpe. A Parliamentarian, he was MP for Preston from 1640-48 and re-elected in 1654 during the Interregnum. He died in 1669.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <forename>Henock(?)</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Sinkler</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Henock(?) Sinkler </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Possibly Enoch or Henock Sinkler, rector of Slingsby, who was educated at St. John's College Cambridge, graduating in 1633 and made curate of Auburn Chapel, Carnaby, East Riding in 1635, a position he held until at least 1638.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mss1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lady</roleName>
                  <forename>Mary</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Smith</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Smyth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mary Smith </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Smyth was the daughter of Hugh and Elizabeth Smyth of Long Ashton, Somerset. She married Sir Thomas Smith of Hatherton, Cheshire, who was mayor of Chester in 1622, High Sheriff of Cheshire in 1623, alderman of Chester and MP for Chester in the Short and later Long Parliaments, 1640-44. Thomas and Mary had 22 children.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ts1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Smith</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Smith (c.1595-c.1668)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1595~">c. 1595</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1668~">c. 1668</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Thomas Smith (c. 1595-c. 1668) was the son of Thomas and Anne Smith of Hatherton,  Cheshire. Mayor of Chester from 1622 and High Sheriff of Cheshire in 1623, he sat as MP for Chester 1640-44 in the Short and then Long Parliaments before being barred from Parliament for his royalist support. He married Mary Smyth, and they had 22 children. He died c. 1668.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Dr</roleName>
                  <surname type="birth">Smith</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Dr Smith </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dr. Smith was a physician who attended Alice Wandesford, Alice Thornton's mother, on her deathbed.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="hs1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Hugh</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Smithson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Hugh Smithson (c.1598-1670)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1598~">c. 1598</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1670-10-21">21 October 1670</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Hugh Smithson (c. 1598-1670) of Stanwick St. John, North Yorkshire, was the son of Anthony and Eleanor Smithson. He was a London merchant, recusant and royalist made Baronet of Stanwick in 1660 by Charles II for his support. He married Dorothy Rawsthorne, and they had 4 sons and 2 daughters. According to Alice Thornton, his oldest son Jerome plotted to rape her. He died on 21 October 1670.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="js1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir; 2nd Baronet Stanwick</roleName>
                  <forename>Jerome</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Smithson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Jerome Smithson (1632-1684)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1632">1632</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1684">1684</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Jerome Smithson, 2nd Baronet Stanwick (1632-84) was the eldest son and heir of Sir Hugh Smithson, 1st Baronet Stanwick and his wife Dorothy. According to Alice Thornton, Jerome's father and uncle sought her hand in marriage to Jerome, but on refusal he plotted to rape and abduct Alice when she was living at Hipswell, but a man named Tom Binks informed her of the plot so she could escape. He married Mary Wingate, and they had a son and a daughter. He became 2nd Baronet Stanwick on his father's death in 1670, and died in 1684.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Smithson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Uncle Smithson </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Uncle Smithson is one of Sir Jerome's Smithson's paternal uncles, Francis, Richard or John. He helped his brother Hugh Smithson in a bid to marry his nephew Jerome to Alice Thornton in the late 1640s or early 1650s.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cs2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>King</roleName>
                  <forename>Charles</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Stewart</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Charles Stewart (1630-1685)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1630-05-29">29 May 1630</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1685-02-06">6 February 1685</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles Stewart (1630-85), King Charles II of England, Scotland and Ireland was born on 29 May 1630 to King Charles I and Henrietta Maria. He was King of Scotland 1649-51 and King of England, Scotland and Ireland from the Restoration of 1660 until his death in 1685. He married Catherine of Braganza, but had no legitimate issue. He fathered some 9 illegitimate children. He died on 6 February 1689.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <surname type="birth">Thomson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Thomson </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Thomson of Catterick Bridge owned the house where the body of George Wandesford, drowned in the Swale while attempting to cross it on horseback, was laid after its recovery in 1651.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ct1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Thornton (1667-1667)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1667-11-11">11 November 1667</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1667-12-02">2 December 1667</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Thornton (1667) was the 9th child of Alice and William Thornton. He was born at Newton, 11 November 1667 and baptized the next day. He contracted small pox and died on 1 December 1667 and was buried at Stonegrave the following day.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jt1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Joyce</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Joyce Thornton (1665-1666)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1665-09-23">23 September 1665</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1666-01-26">26 January 1666</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Joyce Thornton (1665-6) was the 8th child of Alice and William Thornton, born on 23 September 1665 at Newton and baptized on 28 September.  She fell ill on 20 January 1666 with a cold and red spots and died on 26 January. She was buried the next day at Stonegrave.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rt2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Thornton (1662-1692)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1662-09-19">19 September 1662</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1692-06-04">4 June 1692</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Thornton (1662-92): the seventh child and third son of Alice and William Thornton. He was born on 19 September 1662 at East Newton. He was educated first by John Denton, then by the reverend John Burton at Sutton-on-the-Forest, entered Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge in April 1680, before moving to University College, Oxford in May 1682. In 1687 he became the rector of Oddington but resigned it later that year. He was by now heavily in debt, as was his mother who had been trying to bail him out. In 1691 he was offered a living in Northamptonshire but swapped it for that of Boldon, diocese of Durham, and resided at the Deanery in Durham with his sister Alice and her husband, Thomas Comber. In 1692 Comber helped arrange a marriage for him, to a woman worth £2800, but he fell ill and died on 4 June 1692, aged 29. He is buried in the Chapel of the Nine Altars, Durham Cathedral.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rt3">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Thornton (c.1575-1637)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1575~">c. 1575</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1637-05-27">buried 27 May 1637</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Thornton (c.1575-1637), was the father of William Thornton. He was the son of William and Eleanor Thornton of East Newton. His first marriage was to Dorothy Metham and they had 4 daughters, 1 of whom died in infancy. He then married Elizabeth Darley, with whom he had 7 children, 4 sons and 3 daughters. He was buried at Stonegrave on 27 May 1637.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tt1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Thornton (1626-1685)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1626">1626</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1685">1685</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Thornton (1626-85) was the son of Robert and Elizabeth Thornton, and the younger brother of William Thornton.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wt2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Thornton (1660-1660)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1660-04-17">17 April 1660</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1660-04-28">28 April 1660</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Thornton (1660) was the 6th child and 2nd son of Alice and William Thornton. Born, and baptized at St Nicholas, on 17 April 1660. He died on 28 April 1660 of small pox and was buried the next day at Easby, in the same grave as his unnamed sister.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt5">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <surname type="birth">Tirrill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Tirrill </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Tirrill of Hoddesdon was a chief mourner at the funeral of Alice Thornton's brother John Wandesford in 1664.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="bt1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Barbara</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Todd</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Barbara Todd </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Barbara Todd was a maid of Anne Danby, Alice Thornton's niece-by-marriage. According to Alice, she was one of the perpetrators of the slanders faced by Alice and her daughter Nally around Nally's marriage to Thomas Comber in 1668.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt4">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Mr</roleName>
                  <surname type="birth">Troutbeck</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Troutbeck </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Young Mr Troutbeck was a man who gave Alice Thornton's sick mother advice while Alice herself was in labour with her daughter Elizabeth in February 1654.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="et2">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Queen</roleName>
                  <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Tudor</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth Tudor (1533-1603)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1533-09-07">7 September 1533</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1603-03-24">24 March 1603</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth I (1533-1603) was Queen of England from 1558 until her death in 1603. Born on 7 September 1533, she was the daughter of Henry VIII and his second wife Anne Boleyn. Alice Thornton notes that her mother Alice Wandesford was born during Elizabeth's reign. She died on 24 March 1603.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cw4">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir</roleName>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Wandesford (c.1548-1590)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1548~">c. 1548</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1590-07-11">buried 11 July 1590</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Christopher Wandesford (c. 1548-90) was the son of Francis and Jane Wandesford of Kirklington; Alice Thornton's great-grandfather. He married Elizabeth Bowes c. 1568 and they had 4 children; 3 sons and a daughter. He was the Vice President of the Council of the North, and was responsible for escorting Mary Queen of Scots from Carlisle to Bolton in 1568. He was buried at Kirklington on 11 July 1590.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cw5">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Wandesford (1617-1627)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1617">1617</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1627">1627</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Wandesford (1617-27) was the son of Sir Christopher and Alice Wandesford; Alice Thornton's older brother. He died age 10 in 1627, and his brother born in 1628 was named after him.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ww2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Wandesford </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Wandesford of Pickhill was the son of Richard and Muriel Wandesford; and was a cousin of Alice Thornton's father Christopher Wandesford. He married Elizabeth Askwith on 27 October 1619 and they had 3 sons. He was living in Ireland at the time of Christopher Wandesford's death in December 1640 and was a witness to his will as well as one of the executors of his estate.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="lw1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Luke</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wastell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Luke Wastell </persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Luke Wastell was the third son of Leonard and Anne Wastell of Scorton and Kirkby Knowle. His brother John was a Parliamentarian and MP for Northallerton. He married twice; first Sarah Laton and then Elizabeth Pattison.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rw2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Webster</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Webster (died 1667)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1667-10-27">buried 27 October 1667</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Webster of Nunnington was a witness at Alice and William Thornton's marriage in 1651. He was buried at Nunnington on 27 October 1667.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="erw1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Lady Strafford</roleName>
                  <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Wentworth</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Rodes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth Wentworth (c.1614-1688)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1614~">c. 1614</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1688-04-10">10 April 1688</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth Wentworth (c. 1614-88) was the daughter of Godfrey and Anne Rhodes. She became the third wife of Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl Strafford c. 1632, and they had two children, Thomas and Margaret. She was also step-mother to Wentworth's children with his second wife Arabella Holles. She died on 10 April 1688.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ww3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>2nd Lord Raby, 2nd Earl Strafford</roleName>
                  <forename>William</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wentworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Wentworth (1626-1695)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1626-06-08">8 June 1626</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1695-10-16">16 October 1695</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Wentworth 2nd Lord Raby 2nd Earl Strafford (1626-1695) was born on 8 June 1626 to Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl Strafford and his second wife Arabella, their first child and only son. He married twice; first Henrietta Maria Stanley; and second Henrietta de la Rochfoucauld. He died without issue on 16 October 1695, when the title Earl Strafford became extinct.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pcw1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Philadelphia</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Wharton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Carey</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Philadelphia Wharton (died 1654)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1654">1654</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Philadelphia Wharton (xxxx-1654), was the daughter of Robert and Elizabeth Carey. She was a lady-in-waiting to Princess Elizabeth, Queen of Bohemia and married Sir Thomas Wharton of Aske Hall in on 11 April 1611. They had 2 sons. She died at Easby in 1654.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rw3">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Ralph</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Widdrington</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Ralph Widdrington (c.1614-1688)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1614/1615">c. 1614/1615</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1688-06-10">10 June 1688</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ralph Widdrington (1614/15-88) was the son of Lewis and Anne Widdrington of Cheesburn Grange, Northumberland. He attended Morpeth School and was then admitted to Christ's College Cambridge in 1632. He was admitted to Gray's Inn in 1641, before being ordained and tutoring at Christ's, where he taught Alice Thornton's younger brother John Wandesford. He became Regius Professor of Greek in 1654. He died at Christ's on 10 June 1688.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cw3">
               <persName>
                  <roleName>Sir, 3rd Baronet of Constable Burton</roleName>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wyvill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Wyvill (1614-1681)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1614-12-06">baptised 6 December 1614</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1681-02-08">buried 8 February 1681</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Christopher Wyvill, 3rd Baronet of Constable Burton (1614-81), was baptised on 6 December 1614, the eldest son and heir of Marmaduke and Isabel Wyvill. He married Ursula Darcy on 12 December 1636, and the couple had 12 children, 6 of whom died before them and 6 survived them. He wrote an elegy for Alice Thornton's brother George Wandesford, who drowned in the Swale in 1651. He was elected MP for Richmond in 1659 and returned to the Long Parliament in 1660. He was buried with his wife, who died in 1680, at Masham on 8 February 1681.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
         </listPerson>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
