<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader><!--
        **DO NOT MANUALLY EDIT THIS FILE**  
        its generated automatically with XSLT
        -->
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>ATB People (14 November 2024)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>blah blah</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>
              sources: 
              <list>
                  <item>Teams spreadsheet: Ographies/atb_people_masterlist_****.xlsx</item>
                  <item>Teams biographies docs</item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p>
            NOTES: 
          </p>
         <p>
            bios are still work in progress. 
          </p>
         <p>
            ID construction is based on name initials:
            uses full initials where known
            for married women include maiden surname initial if known
            if firstname [or surname for that matter] unavailable use x
            then add number to ensure uniqueness
          </p>
         <p>
            TODO:
            roleName, forename, need finessing. esp @type=...
            title?
            listRelation - also once name tagging and biographies are complete
            wikidata etc linkage to do once name tagging and internal linkage is completed
            
            bio sources *may* get reformatted into a separate listBibl at a later stage
          </p>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date when="2024-11-14"/>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <listChange>
            <change>
               <date>2023-11-29</date>
               <desc>updated bios.</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
               <date>2023-03-13</date>
               <desc>updated to include new bios for books 2 and 3. added sources.</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
               <date>2022-10-20</date>
               <desc>slight revision to schema (persName label); revised format of label names. added EDTF date formatting for births and deaths.</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
               <date>2022-06-27</date>
               <desc>updated to use KDL schema</desc>
            </change>
         </listChange>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <listPerson>
            <person xml:id="awt1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Thornton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Alice Thornton (1626-1707)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1626-02-13">13 February 1626</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1707-02-01">buried 1 February 1707</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Alice Thornton, daughter of Christopher and Alice Wandesford, was born in Kirklington (North Yorks.) on 13 February 1626 and baptised at St Michael’s on 19 February. She was their fifth child of seven and the youngest daughter. She married William Thornton on 15 December 1651. They had nine children, three of whom survived to adulthood. A widow from the age of 42, she died at East Newton and was buried at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave on 1 February 1707.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cw1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Wandesford (1592-1640)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1592-09-24">24 September 1592</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1640-12-03">3 December 1640</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Wandesford, eldest son and heir of Sir George and Catherine Wandesford, was born at Bishop Burton, East Riding on 24 September 1592. He attended Clare College, Cambridge but returned home on his father's death to provide for his siblings. He married Alice Osborne in 1614 and they had seven children, five of whom survived childhood. He was an MP in Yorkshire in the 1620s. In 1633 he relocated the family to Dublin, Ireland, to serve as Master of Rolls and became MP for County Kildare. In 1640 he was briefly Lord Deputy of Ireland before he died on 3 December 1640. He was buried at Christ Church, Dublin, on 10 December 1640.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rl1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Lascelles</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Roger Lascelles (c.1557-1630)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1557~">c.1557</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1630-07-21">21 July 1630</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Roger Lascelles, born c.1557, was rector of St Michael’s, Kirklington from May 1590 until his death in July 1630. He was Thornton’s godfather. He died on 21 July 1630.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="awn1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Norton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Norton (c.1593-1683)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1593~">c.1593</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1683-12-23">buried 23 December 1683</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Norton, daughter of Sir George Wandesford and his wife, Catherine, was born c.1593; she was Thornton’s aunt. She married Maulger Norton on 4 March 1622. They had six children (four sons and two daughters). She was buried on 23 December 1683 at St Mary’s, Richmond.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Best</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Mallory</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Olive Best (1594-1654)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1594-12-05">baptised 5 December 1594</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1654-06-16">buried 16 June 1654</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is likely Olive Best, daughter of John and Anne Mallory, born in late 1594. She became the second wife of Thomas Best on 17 January 1619. She died in 1654 and was buried at St Mary’s, Wath on 16 June.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="st1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Tomlinson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Sarah Tomlinson (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sarah Tomlinson was a servant in the Wandesford household. She was a nursemaid at Kirklington in the late 1620s and moved with the family to London in the early 1630s. We have not been able to trace her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cw2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">1st Baronet of Kirklington</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Wandesford (1628-1687)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1628-02-02">2 February 1628</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1687-02-23">23 February 1687</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Christopher Wandesford was born on 2 February 1628, the son of Christopher and Alice Wandesford; he was Thornton's younger brother. He was baptised at St Michael the Archangel’s, Kirklington on 14 February 1628. He became heir on his brother George’s death in March 1651 and married Eleanor Lowther, who had been intended for his brother, on 30 September 1651. He was made 1st Baronet of Kirklington in 1660 and was elected MP for Ripon in 1679 and again in 1680. He had 12 children. He died in London on 23 February 1687 and was buried on 12 March at St Michael the Archangel’s, Kirklington.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Baxter</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Baxter (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Baxter was a man acquainted with the Wandesford family who lived in Kent in the 1630s. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xl1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Leveson</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Dudley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Leveson (1598-1674)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1598">1598</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1674-02">February 1674</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is likely Lady Katherine Leveson, the daughter of the illegitimate son of the Elizabethan courtier Robert Dudley  also called Robert – and his first wife, Alice. She was born in 1598, and married Sir Richard Leveson in 1609. She died in February 1674 at Trentham, Kent, without issue, and in her will she endowed alms-houses and an education fund which survives to this day at Temple Balsall.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tw1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wentworth</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">1st Baron Raby</roleName>
                  <roleName type="peerage">1st Earl of Strafford</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Wentworth (1593-1641)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1593-04-13">13 April 1593</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1641-05-12">12 May 1641</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Wentworth, 1st Baron Raby, 1st Earl Strafford, was born on 13 April 1593 to William Wentworth, a Yorkshire landowner, and his wife Anne; he was their second son and eldest surviving. He was a childhood friend of Christopher Wandesford, both being educated by the Dean of Ripon. His first marriage to Margaret Clifford took place in 1611 and she died childless in August 1622. He married Arabella Holles in February 1625 and they had three children (one son and two daughters). After her death on 6 October 1631, he married Elizabeth Rhodes in 1632 and had another son and daughter. In 1633 he was made Lord Deputy of Ireland and relocated to Dublin. He was made Lord Lieutenant in 1640, and on 12 January that year 1st Baron Raby, and 1st Earl Strafford. He was recalled to England in 1639, was impeached and executed on 12 May 1641.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="aw1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Watson</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wentworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Watson (1627-1696)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1627-10-08">8 October 1627</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1696-01-02">2 January 1696</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Lady Anne Watson was born on 8 October 1627 in Finningley, Nottinghamshire, the eldest daughter of Thomas Wentworth and his second wife, Arabella. She was a childhood friend of Thornton's in Dublin. She married Edward Watson, 2nd Baron Rockingham, on 24 November 1654, and they had eight children (four sons and four daughters). She died on 2 January 1696 and was buried at St Leonard’s, Rockingham six days later, where a monument to commemorate her was erected by her son, George.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="aw2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">McCarthy</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wentworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Arabella McCarthy (1630-1697?)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1630-10">October 1630</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1697-04-14?">after 14 April 1697</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Lady Arabella McCarthy was born in October 1630 in London, the daughter of Thomas Wentworth and his second wife, Arabella. She was a childhood friend of Thornton's in Dublin. She married Justin MacCarthy, 1st Viscount Mountcashel, about 13 years her junior. She was still alive (but ill) on 14 April 1697, when mentioned in a letter by Thornton to Abstrupus Danby, and died without issue.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jw1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Wandesford (c.1634-1664)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1634~">c.1634</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1664-12-02">2 December 1664</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Wandesford was the fourth son of Christopher and Alice Wandesford. He was born in London c.1634, after which the family moved to Ireland to join their father, Christopher Wandedsford, who was Master of the Rolls. After returning to Yorkshire in the mid-1640s, he was educated at schools in Bedale, Chester and Richmond, before entering Christ's College, Cambridge (1649–51). He was elected MP for Richmond in 1661 and died in his lodgings at London on 2 December 1664. He was buried at St Augustine’s, Broxbourne, Hertfordshire.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fk1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Kelly</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Frank Kelly (c.1634-1643)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1634~">c.1634</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1643">1643</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Frank Kelly was an orphan taken into the Wandesford household in Dublin. He moved with the family to Chester in 1641. He was about nine when he died of smallpox in 1643.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="td1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Danby (died 1644)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1644-07-02">2 July 1644</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Danby was the son of Richard and Alice Danby of South Cave. He was Thornton’s relation by marriage: a cousin of her brother-in-law, Thomas Danby. He married (wife’s name unknown) and had a son, Francis, who was fined in 1646 for taking arms against parliament. He died at the battle of Marston Moor on 2 July 1644, fighting for the royalist side.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xm1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Richard</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Mahum</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Dr Richard Mahum (died 1659)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1659">1659</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dr Mahum, described by Thornton as her 'old doctor', may be the same Richard Mahum who witnessed her mother's will in 1659. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="kwd1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Danby</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Danby (1615-1645)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1615-10-20">baptised 20 October 1615</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1645-09-10">10 September 1645</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Danby was the eldest child of Christopher and Alice Wandesford. She was baptised on 20 October 1615 at St Michael’s, Kirklington. She married Thomas Danby in July 1630, aged 14. She was pregnant 16 times but suffered six stillbirths. Of the couple's 10 baptised children, eight were boys and two were girls; seven of her 10 children survived infancy. She died on 10 September 1645, aged 29, at Thorpe Perrow of postpartum complications. She was buried at St Mary’s, Masham.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fd1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Francis Danby (1645-1672?)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1645-08-27">27 August 1645</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1672?">after 1672</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Francis Danby was the youngest son of Thomas and Katherine Danby, born at Thorpe Perrow on 27 August 1645. He was Thornton's nephew, named after his brother who had died the month before. He and his brother John were involved in a protracted legal suit with Margaret Danby, widow of their eldest brother, Thomas, throughout the 1670s. He was still alive in November 1680 when the case was ongoing.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="en1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Edmund Norton (1622-1648)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1622">1622</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1648-11-29">buried 29 November 1648</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edmund Norton, second son of Maulger and Anne Norton, was born in 1622. He attended the University of Cambridge and was admitted to Gray's Inn to study law in February 1646. He served as a colonel of the regiment of dragoons under John Mallory in the Skipton garrison in the 1640s. He married Jane Dudley of Chopwell on 10 February 1647. He died in 1648 and was buried at St-Michael-le-Belfrey’s, York on 29 November.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="td2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Dudley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Toby Dudley (c.1597-1661)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1597~">c.1597</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1661">1661</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Toby Dudley, born c.1597, was the oldest son and heir of Ambrose Dudley of Chopwell, Northumberland. He married Jane Blackiston and they had one child, also named Jane. He was buried at Holy Cross, Ryton in 1661.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jdn1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Norton</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Clavering</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Dudley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Jane Clavering (died 1690)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1690">1690</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Jane Clavering, birth date unknown, was the daughter and sole heir of Toby and Jane Dudley of Chopwell. She married Edmund Norton on 10 February 1647 but he died in 1648. She then married Robert Clavering at St Ebba’s, Ebchester on 15 July 1651. They had four children (two sons and two daughters). She died in 1690.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cs1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Stuart</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">King Charles I</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Charles Stuart (1600-1649)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1600-11-19">19 November 1600</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1649-01-30">30 January 1649</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles I of England, born 19 November 1600 to James I and VI and Anne of Denmark, was king of England, Scotland and Ireland from 1625 and the reigning monarch for the first 23 years of Thornton's life. He married Henrietta Maria and had nine children (four sons and five daughters). He was executed on 30 January 1649.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jn1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Julian Norton (1633-1649)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1633-01-06">6 January 1633</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1649-04-09">9 April 1649</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Julian Norton, daughter of Maulger and Anne Norton, was born 6 January 1633. She died aged 17 on 9 April 1649 at her father's house in Richmond, Yorkshire and was buried the next day at St Mary's, Richmond.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jn2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Norton (c.1637-1646)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1637~">c.1637</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1646">1646</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Norton, fourth son of Maulger and Anne Norton, was born c.1637. He died at the family home in Richmond of a consumption in 1646, aged nine.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="eo1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Osborne</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">1st Baronet Kiveton</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Edward Osborne (1596-1647)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1596-12-12">baptised 12 December 1596</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1647-09-09">9 September 1647</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Edward Osborne, 1st Baronet Kiveton, son of Sir Hewett and Joyce Osborne, was baptised on 12 December 1596. He was the maternal uncle of Thornton. Educated at Trinity College, Cambridge, he was admitted to the Inner Temple to study law in 1620. He was knighted and created Baronet by James I that same year and was vice president of the Council of the North. He married twice: on 13 October 1618 to Margaret Belasyse, with whom he had a son; after her death in 1624, to Anne Walmesley, widow of William Middleton, with whom he had another son. He died on 9 September 1647 at his family home of Kiveton Hall, South Yorkshire.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gw1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Wandesford (1623-1651)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1623-09-14">14 September 1623</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1651-03-31">31 March 1651</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Wandesford, born 14 September 1623, was Christopher and Alice Wandesford's eldest son; his godfather was Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl of Strafford. He attended Trinity College, Dublin from 1636, when the family were living in Ireland. Accused of taking part in the battle of Marston Moor in July 1644, his estates were sequestered and he moved to Hipswell Hall, his mother's property, before fleeing to France for the remainder of the fighting in England. He drowned in the River Swale, through which he was riding on horseback, on 31 March 1651, and was buried at St Michael the Archangel’s, Kirklington.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ww1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Wandesford (1605-1690)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1605-08-26">baptised 26 August 1605</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1690">1690</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Wandesford was the youngest son of Sir George Wandesford by his second wife, Mary; he was Thornton's uncle. He was baptised on 26 August 1605 at St Michael the Archangel’s, Kirklington. His brother, Christopher Wandesford, sent him to be an apprentice to a London merchant. He married Rebecca Reade and they had a daughter, Catherine. He was granted an annuity of £20 for life on 30 June 1637 out of Wandesford property at Castlecomer, Ireland, paid yearly at Christ's Church, Dublin. He suffered severe losses during the Wars of the Three Kingdoms due to his loyalty to the royalist cause. According to Thornton, a committee who advised Charles I during his trial met in his London home. He was made a gentleman-pensioner by Charles II after the Restoration in 1660 and died in 1690.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mny1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Yorke</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mary Yorke (1635-1675?)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1635-07-12">baptised 12 July 1635</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1675?">after 1675</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Yorke, fourth child of Maulger and Anne Norton, was baptised at St Mary’s, Richmond on 12 July 1635; she was Thornton's cousin. On 20 August 1651 she married John Yorke of Gouthwaite, who was knighted in 1660.  They had four children (three sons and a daughter). She became a widow in 1663 and purchased the manor of Bewerley in 1675. She died in 1694.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jy1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Yorke</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Yorke (c.1634-1663)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1634~">c.1634</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1663-04-01">1 April 1663</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir John Yorke, son of John Yorke of Gouthwaite and his second wife, Catherine, was born c.1634. He was educated at Queen's College, Oxford, matriculating in 1650. On 20 August 1651 he married Mary Norton and they had four children (three sons and a daughter). He was knighted by Charles II on his restoration in 1660. He was elected MP for Richmond the following year, a position he held until his death on 1 April 1663. He was buried at St Chad’s, Middlesmoor.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jl1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Lowther</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">1st Baronet Lowther</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Lowther (1606-1675)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1606-02-20">20 February 1606</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1675-11-30">30 November 1675</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir John Lowther, 1st Baronet Lowther and Sheriff of Cumberland, was born on 20 February 1606 to Sir John and Eleanor Lowther. He graduated from the Inner Temple in 1621 and was called to the bar in 1630. He married Mary, daughter of Richard Fletcher, before 1628, and they had 11 children (five sons and six daughters). His second wife was Elizabeth Hare, by whom he had four children (three sons and a daughter). His eldest daughter with Mary, Eleanor, originally intended to marry Thornton’s eldest brother George who died in 1651, married his younger brother Sir Christopher Wandesford, and Lowther agreed to £1,500 towards the debts of Wandesford’s late father. He was twice elected MP for Westmorland, in 1628–29 (with his father) and again in 1660. He fought for the royalists during the Wars of the Three Kingdoms. He died on 30 November 1675 and is buried at St Michael’s, Lowther, alongside his father.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="elw1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Wandesford</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Lowther</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Eleanor Wandesford (1633-1714)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1633-03-25">baptised 25 March 1633</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1714-12-20">buried 20 December 1714</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Eleanor Lowther, the daughter of Sir John Lowther and his first wife Mary, was baptised on 23 March 1633 at St Michael’s, Lowther. She was betrothed to George Wandesford but after his drowning married his younger brother, Sir Christopher Wandesford, on 30 September 1651 at Lowther. Her marriage portion from her father amounted to £2,000. They had nine children (three sons and six daughters). She was buried on 20 December 1714 at St Michael the Archangel’s, Kirklington.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wt1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Thornton (1624-1668)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1624-06-02">2 June 1624</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1668-09-17">17 September 1668</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Thornton, the son of Robert Thornton of East Newton and his second wife, Elizabeth, was born (along with his twin brother, Richard) on 2 June 1624 and baptized at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave on 9 June. He married Alice Wandesford on 15 December 1651 at Hipswell Hall. They had nine children, of whom three outlived him. He performed the role of Justice of the Peace sometime around the early 1660s. He died at Malton on 17 September 1668 and was buried at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave the next day. His wife commissioned a memorial, which is still there today.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ms1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Syddall</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Michael Syddall (1614-1659)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1614-09-30">baptised 30 September 1614</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1659-01-08">buried 8 January 1659</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Michael Syddall was baptised on 30 September 1614 at SS Martin and Gregory’s, York, the son of William Syddall, a baker, and his wife, Margaret. He was admitted to Christ's College, Cambridge in 1631 at the age of 16, graduating with his B.A. in 1635 and M.A. in 1638. He married Ellen Hunton, widow of the steward of the late Christopher Wandesford. He was minister at St Michael the Archangel’s, Kirklington, 1644–49 and vicar of St Anne’s, Catterick, from 1645–58. He was buried on 8 January 1658 in the chancel at St Anne’s. In his will, dated 3 January 1658, he left money to build a school and he made William Thornton one of four trustees.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Unnamed Thornton (1652-1652)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1652-08-27">27 August 1652</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1652-08-27">27 August 1652</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thornton's first child, an unnamed daughter, was born on 27 August 1652 but lived for less than an hour and so was not baptised. She was buried at St Agatha’s, Easby the next day.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="atc1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Alice</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Comber</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
                  <addName type="nickname">Nally</addName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Alice Comber (1654-1721)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1654-01-03">3 January 1654</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1721-01-20">20 January 1721</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Alice Comber, nicknamed Nally, was born on 3 January 1654 at Hipswell Hall to Alice and William Thornton and was baptised two days later. She was their second child and one of three Thornton children to survive to adulthood. She married Thomas Comber on 17 November 1668, by whom she had nine children (five sons and four daughters), with two sons and two daughters surviving childhood. She was Thornton’s main heir in 1707 and inherited her ‘books of my life’. She died on 20 January 1721 and was buried at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave two days later, where there is a memorial plaque.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mn1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Maulger Norton (1594-1673)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1594-03-25">baptised 25 March 1594</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1673-12-12">buried 12 December 1673</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Maulger Norton, first son of Robert and Catherine Norton of St Nicholas, Richmond, was baptised on 25 March 1593 at All Saints’, Wath. He was elected MP for Richmond in the Short Parliament of 1640. He married Thornton's paternal aunt, Anne Wandesford, on 4 March 1622, by whom he had six children (four sons and two daughters). He was receiver for crown venues for Northumberland, Durham and Richmond in the 1660s but by 1667 was in financial trouble and was briefly imprisoned and later suspended from receiving rents in those regions. He was buried at St Mary’s, Richmond on 12 December 1673.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="et1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
                  <addName type="nickname">Betty</addName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth Thornton (1655-1656)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1655-02-14">14 February 1655</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1656-09-03">3 September 1656</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth (Betty) Thornton was born on 14 February 1655 to Alice and William Thornton and baptised on 16 February, probably in the private chapel at Hipswell. She was their third child. She died on 3 September 1656, aged 18 months, and was buried at St Anne’s, Catterick.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ca1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Anthony</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Charles Anthony (1600-1685)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1600-11-06">6 November 1600</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1685-06-25">25 June 1685</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles Anthony was born on 6 November 1600 and was educated at Jesus College, Cambridge (BA 1624, MA 1627). He was ordained in 1636 and became vicar of St Anne’s, Catterick in 1660. He baptised Thornton's daughter, Elizabeth, in 1654, probably at the private chapel at Hipswell Hall. He died on 25 June 1685 and was buried at St Anne’s, Catterick.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="kb1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Blackburne</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Covill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Blackburne (1645-1696?)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1645-01-26">baptised 26 January 1645</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1696?">after 1696</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Blackburne, baptised 26 January 1645 at St Andrew, Grinton was the daughter of Roger and Anne Covill of Fremington, Yorks. She married Timothy Blackburne. She stood in for Thornton’s mother, who was unwell, at the baptism of Thornton's daughter, Elizabeth, in 1654. A widow from 1694, she was still alive in 1696 when she was named executrix in her mother's will.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="edg1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Thornton</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Gates</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Darley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth Gates (1597-1655)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1597-10-03">3 October 1597</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1655-05-10">10 May 1655</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth Gates, born 3 October 1597 at Buttercrambe, was the eldest daughter of Sir Richard Darley of Buttercrambe and his second wife, Elizabeth (née Gates). She became the second wife of Robert Thornton after his wife Dorothy’s death in July 1619 and they had seven children (four sons and three daughters). After his death in 1637, she married Geoffrey Gates on 26 June 1638 at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave. Her joint-eldest son, William, married Thornton in 1651. She died on 10 May 1655 at Oswaldkirk and was buried the next day at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gg1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Gates</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Geoffrey Gates (died 1655)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1655-05-18">18 May 1655</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Geoffrey Gates was the second husband of Elizabeth Gates, whom he married on 26 June 1638 at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave, becoming the stepfather of William Thornton. He was resident at Burn Park, Cottingham, in the East Riding. In 1642–43 and 1644–45 he was appointed Parliamentary Commissioner to collect monies from royalists in the North Riding of Yorkshire and in 1645 he performed the same duty in the East Riding, taking over from his father-in-law, Sir Richard Darley.  In 1651 he refused to sign documents allowing his wife to dispose of her landed property, which meant William Thornton’s part of the marriage settlement with the Wandesfords was not legally binding. Gates died eight days after his wife, on 18 May 1655, and was buried at St Mary Lowgate, Hull on the 20th. On his death he was described as a colonel.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rt1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Richard Thornton (1624-1656)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1624-06-02">2 June 1624</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1656-07-03">3 July 1656</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Richard Thornton, born on 2 June 1624 and baptised on 9 June, was the son of Robert Thornton and his second wife, Elizabeth, and the twin brother of William Thornton; Thornton’s brother-in-law. He died unmarried in Dublin on 3 July 1656 and was buried at St Patrick's Cathedral the next day.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ktp1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Katherine</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Purchas</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Danby</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
                  <addName type="nickname">Katy</addName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Danby (1656-1726)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1656-06-12">12 June 1656</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1726-12-17">17 December 1726</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Danby was the fourth child of Alice and William Thornton and the second of the three that survived to adulthood. She was born on 12 June 1656 at Hipswell Hall and baptised the next day by Michael Syddall, probably at Hipswell chapel. In the later 1660s she was sent with her sister Nally to study at York. She married Thomas Purchas, rector, by arrangement of her brother-in-law, Thomas Comber, on 27 December 1682. She had five children by Purchas (three sons and two daughters), although is possible they also had a further son and a daughter who died as children before 1697. After Purchas's death in April 1697, she married Robert Danby of Northallerton in 1698, without her mother’s approval. She died on 17 December 1726 and was buried at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="kdb1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Best</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Best (1637-1688)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1637-05-25">25 May 1637</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1688">1688</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Best was the daughter of Thomas and Katherine Danby; she was Thornton's niece. She was born on 25 May 1637 at Richmond. She married Henry Best of Middleton Quernhow sometime after 1659 and they had two children (a son and a daughter). She was widowed in 1674 and died in 1688.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Unnamed Thornton (1657-1657)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1657-12-10">10 December 1657</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1657-12-10">10 December 1657</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">An unnamed Thornton son born on 10 December 1657; the fifth child of Alice and William Thornton. He lived only half an hour after a difficult birth. He was buried at St Anne’s, Catterick the same day by Michael Syddall.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rw1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wittie</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Wittie (1613-1684)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1613-11-14">baptised 14 November 1613</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1684-10">October 1684</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Wittie, the son of George and Anne Wittie of Beverley, was baptised at St Mary's, Beverley, on 14 November 1613. He studied medicine at King's College, Cambridge and returned to Yorkshire to practice medicine, first at Hull and then, from 1651 at the latest, at York. He treated Thornton and her family for various ailments. Wittie wrote at least two books; 'The Antimonial Cup' (1640), on emetics, and 'Scarborough Spaw' (1660), which extolled the healing virtues of spas. He married Mary Hall, who outlived him. In 1675, when his mother died, he was resident in the parish of St Martin's, Coney Street, York. On his retirement from active profession, he moved to London and was incorporated at the Royal College of Physicians on 30 September 1680. He died in October 1684.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="aow1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Wandesford</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Osborne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Alice Wandesford (1593-1659)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1593-01-16">baptised 16 January 1593</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1659-12-10">10 December 1659</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Alice Wandesford, the daughter of Hewett and Joyce Osborne of Kiveton, was born in Isleham, Cambs. and baptised on 16 January 1593. She married Christopher Wandesford in 1614 and they had seven children (four sons and three daughters), with five surviving past childhood, including Thornton. She and her children joined her husband in Dublin c.1634 but she was widowed suddenly in December 1640. She and her children fled back to northern England after the Irish rebellion of 1641, living from 1644 at her jointure property, Hipswell Hall. She died on 10 December 1659 and was buried at St Anne’s, Catterick.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ps1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Samways</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Peter Samways (1615-1693)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1615">1615</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1693-04">April 1693</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Peter Samways was born in 1615 in Eltham, Kent. He attended Westminster School and then Trinity College, Cambridge, where he gained his MA in 1641. He was ordained Deacon of Rochester in 1643. A loyal monarchist, he was nevertheless presented to the rectory of Wath-by-Ripon, Yorks in 1658 on petition to Cromwell. With the Restoration in 1660, he was created Doctor of Divinity at Cambridge and then was made prebendary of Barneby, York in 1668. He administered the sacrament to Alice Wandesford on her death bed and was a correspondent with Thomas Comber. He died on 6 April 1693 and was buried at St Gregory’s, Bedale.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jk1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Kearton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Kearton (died 1664)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1664-08-18">buried 18 August 1664</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Kearton received his BA from Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge. He was ordained deacon at York in 1628 and priest in 1629. He became rector of St Mary’s, Richmond in 1657. Alice Wandesford wanted him to preach at her funeral service in 1659. In April 1660 he baptised, and then shortly afterwards buried, Thornton's sixth child, William, at St Agatha’s, Easby. Kearton was buried on 18 August 1664 at St Mary’s, Richmond.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="dcl1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Lightfoot</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Cassell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Daphne Lightfoot (died 1689)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1689-09-20">buried 20 September 1689</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Daphne Lightfoot entered the service of the Wandesford family as an unmarried woman with the family name Cassell; the earliest reference is to her moving to Hipswell with the family in 1644. She was with Katherine Danby, Thornton's sister, when she died after childbirth in 1645. She was present at Thornton’s marriage in 1651. She married another of the household servants, George Lightfoot, before 1654, and they had at least two children. By 1655, when Daphne wet-nurses Thornton’s daughter, Elizabeth, they lived away from Hipswell Hall. They were witnesses to Alice Wandesford's will in 1658, in which they were left 20 shillings each, and Daphne prayed with Alice Wandesford at her bedside in 1659. She provided a great deal of support to Thornton in the wake of her husband's death in September 1668 and was present with her daughter, Mary, at the private wedding of Thomas and Alice Comber in November 1668. Thornton rewarded her for her loyalty in 1669. She was buried on 20 September 1689 at St Agatha’s, Gilling West.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cd2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Darcy</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">8th Lord Darcy de Knayth</roleName>
                  <roleName type="peerage">1st Earl Holderness</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Conyers Darcy (1599-1689)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1599-01-24">24 January 1599</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1689-06-14">14 June 1689</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Conyers Darcy, 8th Lord Darcy de Knayth, was born on 24 January 1599 to Sir Conyers and Dorothy Darcy. He was constable of Middleham Castle, Yorkshire, and was made 1st Earl of Holderness on 6 December 1682. On 14 October 1616 he married Grace Rokeby, the only daughter and heir of Thomas Rokeby of Skyers. They had six sons and five daughters, with only one of the sons, Conyers, surviving childhood. He died on 14 June 1689 in Hornby, Yorks.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ha1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Ableson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Hannah Ableson (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Hannah Ableson was a servant in the Thornton household from at least 1666. In 1667 she accompanied Nally and Katherine Thornton to York, where they were at school. She witnessed the wedding of Nally and Thomas Comber in November 1668. We have not been able to trace her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ra1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Adair</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Adair (1583-1655)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1583">1583</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1655-03-01">1 March 1655</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Robert Adair of Ballymenna and Kinhilt was born in 1583 at Ballymena, co. Antrim, to Sir William and Rosina Adair. He became heir to his family’s Scottish estates on 19 February 1629. He fled to Scotland in 1638 to avoid swearing the Black Oath under Wentworth, after which he was declared a traitor by Charles I. He became major in the Earl of Leven's Horse Regiment c.1643 and commanded a regiment at the battle of Marston Moor in July 1644. He also led the cavalry at the 1650 Battle of Dunbar. He married Jane Edmonstone and they had two sons and a daughter. He died on 1 March 1655.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ga1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Anderson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Anderson (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Anderson, a Scotsman, was a tutor to George Wandesford, in France. It is not known exactly when, but it was 'during the heat of the war' so c.1642; Wandesford had returned to Yorkshire by July 1644. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cda1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Armitage</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Armitage (1612-1667)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1612-02-27">baptised 27 February 1612</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1667-01-13">buried 13 January 1667</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Armitage, the second child of Thomas and Elizabeth Danby of Farnley, was baptised at St Peter's, Warmfield on 27 February 1612. She married Francis Armitage, later 1st Baronet, in 1629. They had at least 11 children before he died in 1644. A letter dated 6 July 1634, from her to her sister-in-law, Katherine Danby (Thornton’s sister), survives. She also attended Katherine Danby on her death bed in September 1645. She was buried on 13 January 1667 at All Saints’, Wakefield.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wa1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Ayscough</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Ayscough (1648-1676)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1648-03-09">9 March 1648</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1676-11-20">buried 20 November 1676</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Ayscough, son of Sir William and Judith Ayscough, was born on 9 March 1648. He was one of the coffin bearers at William Thornton's funeral in September 1668. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ja1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Ashton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Ashton (1622-1697)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1622-02-03">baptised 3 February 1622</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1697-06-09">9 June 1697</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Ashton, son of Sir Ralph and Eleanor Ashton (née Shuttleworth) of Whalley Abbey, was baptised at St Mary and All Saints’, Whalley on 3 February 1622. He was the nephew of Richard Shuttleworth of Gawthorpe Hall. He married Catherine Fletcher, who predeceased him in 1676. He fought for the parliamentarians. He became Baronet on the death of his elder brother in 1695 and died on 9 June 1697. He was buried at St Mary the Virgin’s, Gisburn.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xa1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Atie</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Dr Atie (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dr Atie was a physician active in the Hambleton area in the late 1650s, perhaps an associate of Robert Wittie. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Bathurst</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Bathurst (1597-1659)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1597-08-21">baptised 21 August 1597</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1659-04-19">19 April 1659</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Bathurst, the son of John and Dorothy Bathurst, was baptised at St Dunstan’s, Mayfield, East Sussex on 21 August 1597. He matriculated Pembroke College, Cambridge in 1614 and became a Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians in 1637. He was incorporated MA at Oxford in 1643 (i.e. awarded an honorary degree) and acted as physician to Oliver Cromwell. He was elected MP for Richmond in 1656 and 1658. He married Elizabeth Willance on 27 January 1636, and they had 10 children (seven sons and three daughters). Alice Wandesford sent her sons to him for treatment in 1643 and 1655. He died on 19 April 1659.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mb2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Martha</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Batt</surname>
                  <addName type="nickname">Mattie</addName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Martha Batt (1636-1671?)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1636-09-29">baptised 29 September 1636</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1671?">after 1671</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Martha Batt, daughter of John and Martha Batt, was baptised at St Peter’s, Birstall on 29 September 1636. She lived at Oakwell Hall, Batley until c.1649 when the family moved to Charles County, Virginia; her father was part of a business venture with Thomas Danby (d.1660) to transport settlers to the area. It was in Virginia that she became friends with Anne Danby. In 1665 she is named in a patent giving her brothers, Thomas and Henry, permission to transport her and 117 others into Charles City County, Virginia. By 1667 she was back in Yorkshire in the service of Anne Savile, Countess of Sussex, at Howley Hall. We do not know when she died but a transfer of property rights in Buckroe, Virginia from herself and her brother, William, suggests she was still alive and unmarried in 1671.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="hb1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Best</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Henry Best (died 1674)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1674-01">January 1674</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Henry Best was the son of George and Grace Best of Middleton Quernhow. He married Katherine Danby, Thornton’s niece, after 1659. He had two children by Katherine (a son and a daughter). He was a barrister at Gray’s Inn, London. In 1665 he tricked Thornton into allowing him to undo the settlement for her daughters, from which act he ended up benefitting. He died at Gray’s Inn in January 1674.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tb2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Binks</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Binks (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Binks lived in Richmondshire, Yorks in the late 1640s or 1650s. He warned young Thornton of Jerome Smithson's plan to abduct her. He was possibly a relation of the Smithson family; Jane Smithson, Jerome's first cousin, married one Mr Binks and a cousin Francis Binks is mentioned in the 1672 will of Jerome's brother, Hugh. We do not know when he died.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Binlowes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Binlowes (born c.1631)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1631~">c.1631</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Binlowes was born in Kirklington c.1631, possibly the son of Thomas Binlowes, yeoman. He attended Ripon, Coxwold and Bedale schools and matriculated at Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge in May 1647, aged 16, gaining his BA in 1650 and MA in 1654. He was appointed rector at St Radegund’s, Scruton in October 1655 on the resignation of the incumbent and was still in office in 1662. We do not know when he died, but he might be the Thomas Binlowes buried at St Gregory’s, Bedale on 27 April 1705.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb5">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Borlase</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Borlase (c.1576-1648)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1576~">c.1576</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1648-03-15">15 March 1648</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir John Borlase, son of Edward and Suzannah Borlase, was born c.1576 in Cornwall. He attended Cambridge University but did not graduate. He then pursued a military career and fought extensively in the Low Countries in the early seventeenth century. He became master-general of the ordnance of Ireland in 1634 and Lord Justice of Ireland in 1640, along with Sir William Parsons. He married Alice (née Edwards), widow of Thomas Ravis, bishop of London, and they had three sons. He died in London on 15 March 1648 and was buried at St Bartholomew-the-Great’s, Smithfield.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Bramhall</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Bramhall (1594-1663)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1594-11-18">baptised 18 November 1594</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1663-06-25">25 June 1663</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Bramhall was baptised at St Giles’, Pontefract on 18 November 1594, one of six children of Peter Bramhall of Carleton. He graduated with a BA from Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge in 1612. He was ordained in York in 1615. On 24 June 1618, Christopher Wandesford presented him to the rectory of St Wilfrid’s, South Kilvington. On 10 November 1618, he married a clergyman's widow, Ellen Collingwood. The couple had six children (three sons and three daughters). Wandesford and Thomas Wentworth helped Bramhall secure the prebend of Husthwaite in 1633. He became Bishop of Derry, in Ireland, in May 1634, and was present at Wandesford's deathbed in December 1640 and was named as one of the executors of his will. After the Irish rebellion of 1641 he was exiled and had returned to his native Yorkshire by 1642. He was restored to Ireland by Charles II in 1660. He died on 25 June 1663.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb6">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Brandling</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Brandling (c.1620-1669?)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1620~">c.1620</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1669-08-01?">After 1 August 1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Brandling of Leathley, born c.1620, was the son of Robert and Mary Brandling of Felling. He was captain of a troop of Dragoons under Edward Grey and then the colonel of a regiment under the Marquess of Newcastle. He married Helen Hopton (née Lindley) after 1643, widow of Sir Ingram Hopton. Helen was the coheiress of Arthur Lindley of Middleham. Robert and Helen had five daughters. His will is dated 1 August 1669.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mb1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Heard</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Breakes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mary Breakes (died 1691?)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1691-12-03?">buried 3 December 1691?</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Heard, then Breakes, was a servant (‘house maid’) in the Thornton household in the late 1660s. She left Thornton’s service on May Day 1668, initially for Richmond, and was implicated in spreading rumours about Thornton and Thomas Comber. She was in London in May 1669, perhaps already married to William Heard. She could be the Mary Heard of Barlby, buried at St Mary the Virgin’s, Hemingbrough on 3 December 1691.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wb1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Brereton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Brereton (1604-1661)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1604-09-13">13 September 1604</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1661-04-07">7 April 1661</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir William Brereton, 1st Baronet, was born on 13 September 1604 to William and Margaret Brereton. A puritan who owned extensive estates in Cheshire, and Member of Parliament for Cheshire at various times between 1628 and 1653, he was commander of parliamentarian forces throughout the North Midlands during the First Civil War of 1642–47. He married twice: first, Susanna Booth in 1623, by whom he had four children (three daughters and a son); then, Cicely Mytton in 1641, a wealthy Staffordshire widow, by whom he had two more daughters. When the First Civil War ended, Brereton gave up his local offices and, although nominated as a judge, refused to attend the trial of Charles I in January 1649. He was elected to the Council of State in 1652 and 1653 but did not attend frequently, living in semi-retirement in London. He resumed his seat for Cheshire when the Long Parliament was reinstated in 1659, until its dissolution in March 1660, and died on 7 April 1661.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tb1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Brockhall</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Brockhall (c.1617-1669)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1617~">c.1617</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1669-04-13">buried 13 April 1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Brockhall, son of John Brockhall, a glover, was born c.1617 in Richmond, Yorks. He matriculated at St John's, Cambridge in 1635 and obtained his BA in 1639. He was master of Richmond School 1642–45 and vicar of St Mary’s, Hornby, from 1650–69. He married Susanna (surname unknown) and they had a son. He was rector of St Margaret’s, Tanfield from 1664 until his death and was buried there on 13 April 1669.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Brodricke</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">James Brodricke (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">James Brodricke was a footman for Thornton's brother, George Wandesford, in the early 1650s. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="bb1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Browne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Benjamin Browne (1613-1681)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1613-06-28">baptised 28 June 1613</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1681-12-11">buried 11 December 1681</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Benjamin Browne, son of William Browne of Buckton, was baptised at St Michael’s, Bempton on 28 June 1613. Thornton describes him as her 'cousin Browne' in one account. He was educated at St John's, Cambridge, where he received his BA in 1639. He was instituted at St Mary's, Masham the same year, becoming vicar in 1645. He lost the living in the 1650s but regained it in 1661. He was perhaps married since he and a Mrs Browne both attended Thornton in August 1662 at East Newton. He was ordained priest at York in September 1662. He was buried on 11 December 1681.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Browning</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Joseph Browning (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Joseph Browning was a coachman in Dublin in the mid-1630s, possibly an employee of the Wandesford family. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb7">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Bucke</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mrs Bucke (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mrs Bucke was possibly a servant in Thornton's household; she was local to the Ryedale area in the mid-1660s. We have not been able to trace her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb5">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Bullock</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Cousin Bullock (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Cousin Bullock was probably a descendant of Launcelot Bullock of Holme who had married Margaret Thornton, the daughter of William Thornton's great-grandmother, making him a cousin-by-marriage to Thornton. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Berridge</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Berridge (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Berridge was convicted of the murder of Thomas Danby, Thornton's nephew, in a London tavern brawl in August 1667.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb6">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Butler</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">1st Earl of Ormond</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">James Butler (1610-1688)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1610-10-19">19 October 1610</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1688-07-21">21 July 1688</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">James Butler was born on 19 October 1610 to Thomas and Elizabeth Butler. He was an Anglo-Irish statesman and first Earl of Ormond. He married Elizabeth Preston at Christmas 1629, by whom he had 10 children, with three sons and two daughters surviving to adulthood. He was brought to Ireland by Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl of Strafford, as head of government in 1633. He commanded the royalist forces there from 1641 and became Lord Lieutenant of Ireland on the Restoration of Charles II in 1660. He died at his estate of Kingston Lacey, Dorset, on 21 July 1688.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wc1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Cavendish</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">1st Duke of Newcastle upon Tyne</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Cavendish (1593-1676)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1593-12-16">baptised 16 December 1593</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1676-12-25">25 December 1676</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Cavendish, 1st Duke of Newcastle upon Tyne, the (second but first surviving) son of Charles Cavendish and his second wife, Catherine, was baptised on 16 December 1593. He married twice: Elizabeth Howard by whom he had five children (three sons and two daughters); then, Margaret Lucas. A writer, courtier and royalist army officer, he led his battalion, the Whitecoats, under the forces of Prince Rupert at the battle of Marston Moor in 1644. He died at Welbeck Abbey on Christmas Day 1676.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ksc1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Cholmondeley</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Stanhope</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Cholmondeley (died 1657)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1657-06-15">15 June 1657</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Lady Katherine Cholmondeley was the daughter of Sir John Stanhope, 1st Lord Harrington, and his second wife, Margaret. She married Robert Cholmondeley, 1st Earl of Leinster, c.1610. She died on 15 June 1657 without issue and was buried in the chancel of St Oswald’s, Malpas.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rc4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Cholmondeley</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">1st Earl of Leinster</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Cholmondeley (1584-1659)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1584-06-26">26 June 1584</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1659-10-02">2 October 1659</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Cholmondeley, son of Sir Hugh and Mary Cholmondeley, was born on 26 June 1584 in Middlesex. He inherited the largest landed estate in Cheshire after his father's death in 1601. He was educated at Queen's College Oxford. He married Katherine Stanhope c.1610 and they had no children. He was MP for Cheshire in 1625 and a supporter of Charles I during the Civil War. He was made Earl of Leinster in 1646. He died on 2 October 1659 and was buried next to his late wife in the chancel of St Oswald’s, Malpas.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="uc1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Cholmeley</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Ursula Cholmeley (1600-1665?)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1600-03-13">baptised 13 March 1600</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1665?">after 1665</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ursula Cholmeley, eldest daughter of Robert Thornton and his first wife, Dorothy, was baptised on 13 March 1600 at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave; she was William Thornton's half-sister. She married Marmaduke Cholmeley of Brandsby and they had six children (two sons and four daughters). She was still alive in November 1665 when William Thornton visited Brandsby Hall.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="kc1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Twisleton</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Cholmley</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Stapleton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Cholmley (c.1607-1672)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1607~">c.1607</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1672-06-14">14 June 1672</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Cholmley, daughter of the Henry and Mary Stapleton of Wighill, was born c.1607. She married George Twisleton (died c.1635) and then Henry Cholmley, c.1638. The couple resided at West Newton Grange, Oswaldkirk. With her second husband, she had three children (two sons and a daughter). Thomas Comber was one of the witnesses to her will, made in March 1672. She was buried on 14 June 1672 at St Oswald’s, Oswaldkirk.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jc2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Clotworthy</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Clotworthy (died 1665)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1665-09">September 1665</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Clotworthy, 1st Viscount Massereene, was son of Sir Hugh and Mary Clotworthy of Antrim. He was knighted in 1626 and married Margaret Jones, daughter of Viscount Ranelagh, with whom he had one daughter. He was an Anglo-Irish politician, a presbyterian and an opponent of Thomas Wentworth during his time as Lord Deputy of Ireland. He died in September 1665.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tc1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Comber</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Comber (1645-1699)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1645-03-19">19 March 1645</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1699-11-25">25 November 1699</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Comber was the son of James and Mary Comber of Westerham, Kent, born on 19 March 1645 and baptised on 23 March at St Mary’s, Westerham. From a royalist family, he was educated at Westerham School before entering Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge in 1659. He graduated with his BA in 1663 and became curate at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave at the behest of the absentee incumbent, Gilbert Bennett. He was ordained priest in September 1664 and in March 1665 he lodged with the Thorntons at East Newton for a year. After a further year of studies in Cambridge for an MA, he spent some time in London before he could take up the rectorship of Stonegrave. He married Thornton’s eldest daughter, Alice, in November 1668 and in 1669 he was made rector of Holy Trinity, Stonegrave. They had nine children, with two sons and two daughters surviving him. Comber wrote several treatises and books on religious topics. He became prebendary of York in 1677, precentor at York in 1683, and Dean of Durham in 1692. He was made chaplain-in-ordinary to the joint monarchs William and Mary in 1692. He died of consumption on 25 November 1699 at East Newton and was buried at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave on 30 November.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mc1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Cotes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mary Cotes (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Cotes was probably a servant in Thornton's household; she looked after Thornton’s daughter, Katherine, when she had smallpox in 1666. We have not been able to trace her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rc2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Covill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Roger Covill (died 1664)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1664-07-12">buried 12 July 1664</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Roger Covill was the son and heir of John Covill, a gentleman of Lockthwaite, Westmoreland. He was admitted to the Inner Temple in September 1630, called to the bar in May 1639, and was then based at Fremington, Swaledale. He married Anne Norton, a relation of Thornton’s, at Scruton on 17 June 1641. The couple had two daughters. He drafted a deed at Thornton’s request in 1662. He was buried on 12 July 1664 at St Andrew’s, Grinton; his will was proved in 1665.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jc1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Crathorne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Crathorne (born c.1642)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1642~">c.1642</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Crathorne, son of Ralph Crathorne and his second wife, Margaret, was born c.1642 in Crathorne, North Yorks. He was William Thornton's nephew.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mtc1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Crathorne</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Margaret Crathorne (born 1608)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1608-05-09">baptised 9 May 1608</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Margaret Crathorne, the daughter of Robert Thornton and his first wife, Dorothy, was baptised 9 May 1608 at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave. She was William Thornton's half-sister. Around 1632 she became the second wife of Ralph Crathorne of Crathorne (North Yorks.), and they had a daughter and three sons. We do not know when she died.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rc1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Crathorne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Ralph Crathorne (born c.1634)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1634~">c.1634</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ralph Crathorne, the first son of Ralph Crathorne of Crathorne (North Yorks.) and his second wife, Margaret, was born c.1634. He was William Thornton's nephew. He married Anne Tunstall, and they had three sons. We do not know when he died.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="oc1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Cromwell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Oliver Cromwell (1599-1658)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1599-04-25">25 April 1599</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1658-09-03">3 September 1658</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Oliver Cromwell was born 25 April 1599, the son of Robert and Elizabeth Cromwell. He was educated at Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge. He married Elizabeth Bourchier in 1621 and they had nine children (five sons and four daughters). He was Lord Protector of England, Wales and Ireland during the Interregnum period of 1649 until his death in 1658. He died on 3 September 1658.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rc3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Cromwell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Richard Cromwell (1626-1712)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1626-10-04">4 October 1626</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1712-07-12">12 July 1712</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Richard Cromwell, born 4 October 1626, was the fourth child and third son of Oliver and Elizabeth Cromwell. On his father's death in September 1658, he was elected Lord Protector of England, a position he held until May 1659, when the Protectorate collapsed. He married Dorothy Maijor on 1 May 1649, and they had nine children, only four of whom survived to adulthood. He died on 12 July 1712.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rd2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Daggett</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Daggett (c.1587-1644)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1587~">c.1587</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1644-08-19">19 August 1644</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Daggett of Howe was born c.1587. He studied at Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge, matriculated 1605, MA 1612. He was ordained priest in 1613 and incorporated at Oxford in 1614. He was awarded his Bachelor of Divinity in 1619. He became Rector of St Michael the Archangel’s, Kirklington in April 1639. The Wandesfords stayed with him in Kirklington in 1643–44 while waiting for Hipswell Hall to be ready for habitation. He died on 19 August 1644 and was buried at St Michael the Archangel’s, Kirklington.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="acd1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Danby</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Culpeper</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Danby (died 1695)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1695-11-11">11 November 1695</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Danby was born in England, the daughter of Mr John Culpeper; according to her son, Abstrupus, he was the younger brother of Sir John Culpeper, 1st Baron Culpeper. She moved to Virginia, citing her father’s support for the king. She refers to Lady Berkeley (Frances Culpeper Berkeley), wife to three colonial governors of Virginia, as a ‘cousin’. While in Virginia c.1652 she married Christopher Danby, Thornton's nephew, against the wishes of his father, Thomas Danby. Her first child, born in Virginia in 1653, died straight after the birth. The couple relocated to Yorkshire and lived with Christopher's older brother, Thomas, at Farnley Hall and had five more children (three sons and two daughters). Anne and her family lived with the Thorntons at East Newton at least twice in the 1660s: firstly c.1661 for three months and then, after the death of her husband’s brother, in 1667, when she was cast out by his widow, Margaret Danby. In 1668, she was evicted by William Thornton for spreading rumours. She died on 11 November 1695 and was buried at Holy Trinity, Micklegate, York.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ad1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Alice Danby (born 1641)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1641-05-22">22 May 1641</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Alice Danby, daughter of Thomas and Katherine Danby, was born in London on 22 May 1641 and baptised on 5 June at St Alfege’s, Greenwich; she was Thornton's niece. She was still alive – and unmarried – in 1675, when she was involved in a lawsuit with some of her siblings against her elder brother's widow, Margaret Danby.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cd1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Francelia</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Goodrich</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Parker</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
                  <addName type="nickname">Celia</addName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Francelia Parker (c.1659-c.1699)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1659~">c. 1659</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1699~">c. 1699</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Francelia Parker, daughter of Christopher and Anne Danby, was born in Leeds c.1659; she was Thornton's great-niece. Shhe was brought up in Yorkshire but moved to Virginia, where her parents had met, and married Joseph Goodrich in or around 1685. They had two sons before his death in 1694. She married Thomas Parker later that year. Her will was witnessed on 25 March 1699 in James City County, Virginia.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cd4">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
                  <addName type="nickname">Kitt</addName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Danby (1632-1689)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1632-07-30">30 July 1632</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1689-11-25">buried 25 November 1689</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Danby, second son of Thomas and Katherine Danby, was born 30 July 1632 at St-Martin-in-the-Fields’, London; he was Thornton's nephew. His mother died in 1645 and his father took the family to Virginia in 1650. Around 1652 he married Anne Culpeper, against his father's wishes. Their first child, born in Virginia, died straight after birth. They moved back to Yorkshire and had five children (three sons and two daughters). On his older brother’s death in 1667, he became heir to his father's estate but granted it to his son, Abstrupus, in the same year, as he was thought incapable of running it. He was sent to the Channel Islands as a soldier sometime in the late 1660s or early 1670s. He was in London for some time in the early 1670s. In 1683 he was involved in legal action with his sister-in-law, Margaret Danby and, in the 1680s, he was in close contact with Thornton. He was buried on 25 November 1689 at St Mary’s, Masham.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cd5">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Charles Danby (1643-1672)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1643-06-02">2 June 1643</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1672-04">April 1672</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles Danby, the son of Thomas and Katherine Danby, was born on 2 June 1643 at Snape; he was Thornton's nephew. He matriculated Gonville and Caius College, Cambridge, in 1661 and was admitted to Gray’s Inn in January 1664. He died without issue in April 1672.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fd2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Francis Danby (1640-1645)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1640-03-22">22 March 1640</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1645-07-09">9 July 1645</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Francis Danby, son of Thomas and Katherine Danby, was born on 22 March 1640 at Farnley; he was Thornton's nephew. He died in July 1645 and was buried at St Michael’s, Well.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="med1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Danby</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Eure</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Margaret Danby (c.1640-1688)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1640~">c.1640</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1688-06-23">23 June 1688</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Margaret Danby, daughter of William Eure, sixth Baron Eure of Malton, and his wife, Margaret, was born c.1640. She married Thomas Danby, son and heir of Thomas and Katherine Danby of Thorpe Perrow, in 1659; she was Thornton's niece by marriage. They had three children (a son and two daughters). According to Anne Danby, Margaret fell out with her husband and moved to Malton c.1665. Her husband was murdered in August 1667, later rumoured to be at her instigation. She spent much of her widowhood in conflict with other members of the Danby family over her late husband's estate. She died on 23 June 1688.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="td3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Danby (1610-1660)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1610-08-08">baptised 8 August 1610</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1660-08-05">5 August 1660</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Thomas Danby, the son of Christopher and Frances Danby of Farnley, was baptised 8 August 1610 at St Mary’s, Masham. A ward of Christopher Wandesford after his father's death in 1624 and a protracted legal dispute, he entered St John's College, Cambridge in 1627. He married Wandesford’s daughter, Katherine, in 1630, making him Thornton's brother-in-law. He was knighted in 1633, became Sheriff of York in 1637 and was elected MP for Richmond in 1640. He was banned from sitting in Parliament after 1642 and was fined heavily for his loyalty to Charles I. He and his wife had 10 live-born children, seven of whom survived to adulthood. After his wife's death in 1645, he relocated to Virginia where he held lands, moving back to Yorkshire in the 1650s. He died in London on 5 August 1660 and was buried in the north aisle of the choir at York Minster.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="td4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Danby (1631-1667)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1631-08-17">17 August 1631</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1667-07-31">31 July 1667</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Danby, the oldest son and heir of Sir Thomas and Katherine Danby, was born on 17 August 1631 in Westminster; he was Thornton's nephew. He married Margaret Eure in 1658 and they had three children (a son and two daughters). In 1661 he became the first Mayor of Leeds. He was also briefly MP for Malton in 1661. He was killed in a tavern brawl near Gray's Inn, London, on 31 July 1667. Three men were accused (and one convicted) of his murder but there were later rumours that his wife was involved in his death.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wa2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Ayscough</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Sir William Ayscough (1614-1695)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1614-07-31">31 July 1614</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1695-10-12">buried 12 October 1695</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir William Ayscough of Osgoodby Grange, son and heir of William and Anne Ayscough, was born on 31 July 1614. He married Judith Burgoyne on 4 March 1641 and they had four children (two daughters and two sons). He was JP for the North Riding in 1645–49 and 1653–60 and for the East Riding in 1653–60. He was MP for Thirsk in 1645 and again in 1681. He was buried at All Saints’, Thirkleby on 12 October 1695.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cd3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Darcy</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">2nd Earl Holderness</roleName>
                  <roleName type="peerage">Baron</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Conyers Darcy (1622-1692)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1622-03-03">baptised 3 March 1622</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1692-12-13">13 December 1692</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Conyers Darcy, 2nd Earl Holderness, was the son and heir of Conyers and Grace Darcy. He was baptised on 3 March 1622 at St Michael le Belfrey’s, York. Educated at University College, Oxford (1637), he entered Gray's Inn in 1640. He married four times: to Catherine Fane, Frances Howard, Frances Seymour and Elizabeth Frescheville. With Frances Howard he had six children (three sons and three daughters). He was colonel of militia for the North Riding by 1661, and was elected MP for Boroughbridge in 1660. He became a peer in 1680, as Baron Conyers. He died at Aston, West Yorkshire on 13 December 1692.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="dbd1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Darcy</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Belasyse</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Dorothy Darcy (1572-1653)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1572">1572</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1653-05-11">11 May 1653</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dorothy Darcy, the daughter of Henry and Ursula Belasyse, was born in 1572. She married Conyers Darcy, 4th Lord Conyers, on 2 May 1594 at St Michael’s, Coxwold. They had 12 children (six sons and six daughters). She was buried on 11 May 1653 at St Mary’s, Hornby.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="hd1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Darcy</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Henry Darcy (1610-1662)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1610-10-19">baptised 19 October 1610</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1662-04-28">28 April 1662</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Henry Darcy, the third son of Conyers and Dorothy Darcy, was baptised on 19 October 1610 at St Mary’s, Hornby. He married Mary Scrope in 1628 and they had 10 children. He died on 28 April 1662 and was buried at St Olave’s, York.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Darcy</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">James Darcy (1617-c.1673)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1617-08">August 1617</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1673~">c.1673–74</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">James Darcy, the sixth son of Conyers and Dorothy Darcy, was born in August 1617. He married Isabel Wyvill and they had seven children (three sons and four daughters). He was elected MP for Richmond in 1660 but was not re-elected in 1661, being then appointed Master of the Royal Stud. He likely died in late 1673, after making his will.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fd3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Darley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Francis Darley (1605-1679)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1605">1605</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1679-12-31">buried 31 December 1679</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Francis Darley of Aldby Park, son of Sir Richard Darley of Buttercrambe, Yorks and his second wife, Elizabeth, was born in 1605; he was William Thornton's maternal uncle. He was one of the executors of Alice Wandesford’s will in 1659. In 1665 he was given land by William Thornton which was intended for Thornton’s daughters.  He was buried at St John the Evangelist’s, Buttercrambe on 31 December 1679.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rd1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Darley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Richard Darley (c.1602-1681)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1602~">c.1602</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1681-02-02">2 February 1681</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Richard Darley, third son of Sir Richard Darley of Buttercrambe, Yorks and his second wife, Elizabeth, was born c.1602; he was William Thornton's maternal uncle. He married Elizabeth Hildyard, the niece of Catherine Hansby, on 20 December 1632 at St Edith’s, Bishop Wilton, making him also a cousin-by-marriage of Alice Thornton. They had six children (five sons and a daughter). A parliamentarian, he sat on the compounding committee for Yorkshire from at least 1645 and helped the Wandesford family regain their estate at Kirklington in 1651. In 1654 he was one of the commissioners for the East Riding under the ‘Ordinance for Ejecting Scandalous, Ignorant and Insufficient Ministers and Schoolmasters’. He died on 2 February 1681 and was buried at St Edith’s, Bishop Wilton.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ddl1">
               <persName/>
               <persName type="label">Don de Lan (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Don de Lan was a French page in the service of Robert Meredith, Chancellor of the Irish Exchequer, in the 1630s. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="etd1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Denton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth Denton (1622-1669)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1622-09-24">baptised 24 September 1622</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1669-02-14">14 February 1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth Denton, first child of Robert Thornton and his second wife, Elizabeth, was baptised 24 September 1622 at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave; she was Thornton's sister-in-law. She married John Denton on 8 May 1654 at East Newton. They had at least two sons (John and William) by September 1662. She was buried on 14 February 1669.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Denton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Denton (1625-1709)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1625-02-02">baptised 2 February 1625</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1709-01-14">14 January 1709</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Denton, son of John and Elizabeth Denton of Steeton, was baptised on 2 February 1625 at St Andrew’s, Kildwick-in-Craven. He studied at Clare College, Cambridge, gaining his MA in 1653. He became minister of St Oswald’s, Oswaldkirk in 1654. In the same year, he married Elizabeth Thornton, older sister of William Thornton, with whom he had two sons. He was ejected from the living of Oswaldkirk in 1662 for nonconformity, after which he served as curate at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave under Thomas Comber. His first wife died in 1669 and he remarried. With his second wife, also named Elizabeth, he had two sons and two daughters. He died on 14 January 1709 and was buried on 16 January in the north aisle of Holy Trinity, Stonegrave.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Denton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Denton (born 1655)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1655-09-05">baptised 5 September 1655</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Denton, son of John and Elizabeth Denton, was baptised on 5 September 1655 at St Oswald’s, Oswaldkirk; he was Thornton's nephew. He attended Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge, where he received his BA in 1677. We do not know when he died.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wd1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Denton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Denton (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Denton was the son of John and Elizabeth Denton; Thornton's nephew. Thornton described him as ‘crabbed’ in 1662 and needing his mother’s attention. We have not been able to trace him outside of Thornton’s Books.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Dillon</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">James Dillon (c.1600-1669?)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1600~">c. 1600</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1669?">after 1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir James Dillon, the youngest son of Theobald and Eleanor Dillon, was born c.1600. An army officer, he became Commissioner of Ireland in 1627. He was elected MP for Co. Westmeath in 1634. Commissioned by Charles I in 1640 to recruit regiments from disbanded soldiers in Ireland, he was said to have been involved in the 1641 plot to seize Dublin castle. He married Elizabeth Plunkett in the 1630s, with whom he had two sons. She died before 1653 and he remarried in the early 1660s one Mary Ridge, a widow. He was still alive in 1669.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd5">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Dodsworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Dodsworth (1597-1670)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1597-09-21">baptised 21 September 1597</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1670-06-20">buried 20 June 1670</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Dodsworth of Thornton Watlass, the son of John and Winifred Dodsworth, was baptised on 21 September 1597 at St Gregory’s, Bedale. He matriculated at Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge on 23 January 1613 and was admitted to Gray’s Inn on 24 March 1624. He married Frances Hutton and they had five children (three sons and two daughters). He was related to Thornton via marriage – she and his wife Frances shared a common ancestor in Thornton’s great-great-grandfather George Bowes. Dodsworth witnessed Alice and William Thornton’s marriage in December 1651, and was buried at St Mary’s, Thornton Watlass on 20 June 1670.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xe1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Etherington</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Edrington (died 1681)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1681-07-20">20 July 1681</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is possibly William Etherington, a cleric at St Agatha’s, Gilling West between 1659–81. He took part in Alice Wandesford’s funeral in Catterick in December 1659. He was ordained deacon in 1663, priest in 1665. He was instituted to the living of Gilling West by Lord Wharton in 1665 and remained there until his death. He died on 20 July 1681.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="kf1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Farrer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Katherine Farrer (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Katherine Farrer was a friend of Anne Danby, whom Anne tried to set up with Thomas Comber c. 1667–68. She was perhaps a relation of parson George Farrer. We have not been able to identify her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gf1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Farrer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Farrer (born 1610?)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1610-10-28?">baptised 28 October 1610(?)</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Farrer was perhaps the son of Nathaniel Farrer of Closehouse, baptised on 28 October 1610 at Coxwold. He was probably the minister of St Mary the Virgin’s, Thornton Watlass, instituted in 1635 by Thomas Danby (d.1660). Katherine Danby asked for him on her deathbed in 1645 and he took part in Alice Wandesford’s funeral in 1659. In 1668 he was in Malton. Anne Danby wrote to him in late 1668 or 1669; he seemed to have been acting as a mediator between her and her sister-in-law, Margaret Danby. We do not know when he died.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ef1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Fleetwood</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Edward Fleetwood (c.1534-1604)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1534~">c.1534</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1604-10-12">12 October 1604</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edward Fleetwood, son of Thomas Fleetwood and his second wife Bridget, was born c.1534; he was the brother of Thornton's maternal grandmother, Joyce Osborne. He studied at St Alban Hall, Oxford (MA 1575), and married Christian Wentworth. The couple had at least four children. He was instituted rector of All Saints’, Wigan in 1571, a position he held until his death on 12 October 1604.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mf1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Fleetwood</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Miles Fleetwood (1576-1641)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1576-10-01">baptised 1 October 1576</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1641-03-08">8 March 1641</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Miles Fleetwood of Aldwinkle was baptised on 1 October 1576. Thornton confuses him with her maternal great-grandfather, Thomas Fleetwood; he was related to Thornton via her maternal grandmother, Joyce, whose brother, William Fleetwood, was Miles’s father. He married Anne Luke and they had eight children (four sons and four daughters). He was MP for several constituencies across England in the 1620s and 1630s. He was elected MP for Hindon, Wiltshire, in the Short Parliament of 1640, which role he held until his death on 8 March 1641.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jf2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Flower</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Jane Flower (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Jane Flower, whose parents lived in Northallerton, was one of Thornton’s servants. She was nursemaid to Thornton’s second child, Nally, in 1654 and she moved with the family from Hipswell to Richmond in 1660, where she was still looking after Nally. She then moved to Oswaldkirk with the family in 1661, now described as Thornton’s servant, and then to East Newton in 1662. She may be the Jane Flower at whose Northallerton house depositions were taken on 14 July 1676 in the Chancery case of James Danby versus Charles Laton. We do not know when she died.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jf1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Frescheville</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">1st Baron Frescheville</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Frescheville (1606-1682)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1606">1606</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1682-03-31">31 March 1682</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Frescheville was born in 1606, the son of Sir Peter Frescheville and his first wife, Joyce. He was Thornton's uncle, the younger half-brother of her mother. He was educated at Magdalen Hall (now Hertford College), Oxford and the Middle Temple (1624). He married twice: Bruce Nicholls, who died in 1629 without issue, and then Sarah Harington, with whom he had three daughters. He was elected MP for Derbyshire in 1628, the year before the abolition of Parliament by Charles I. He was Lieutenant of Derbyshire from 1630–42 and then became a Captain in the royalist army. He was executor of Alice Wandesford’s will in 1659 and named trustee for Alice and William Thornton's daughters in the settlement of 1667. Thornton references several letters between herself and Frescheville in the mid and late 1660s, as she asked for his help in getting the living of Stonegrave for Thomas Comber. He was made 1st Baron Frescheville in 1665 and died without a male heir to inherit this baronetcy on 31 March 1682.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pf1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Frescheville</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Peter Frescheville (1575-1634)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1575-03-14">baptised 14 March 1575</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1634-04-07">7 April 1634</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Peter Frescheville, eldest son of Peter Frescheville of Staveley, Derbyshire and his second wife, Margaret, was baptised 14 March 1575. He sat in the House of Commons as MP for Derbyshire in 1601 and in 1621–22. He built Staveley Hall in 1604. He married twice, first Joyce Osborne (née Fleetwood), widow of Hewett Osborne, with whom he had three children (a son and two daughters) and second Isabel Neville who died without issue. His marriage to Joyce made him Thornton's maternal step-grandfather. He died on 9 April 1634 and was buried at St John the Baptist’s, Staveley.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="sg1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Graham</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Washington</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Susanna Graham (1618-1699)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1618-11-15">baptised 15 November 1618</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1699-02-26">26 February 1699</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Susanna Graham, daughter of William and Anne Washington, was baptised 15 November 1618 at St-Martin-in-the-Fields’, London. She married Ranald Graham of Lewisham c.1640. The couple purchased Nunnington Hall in Ryedale in 1655 and Ranald became a Justice of the Peace in the North Riding of Yorkshire in 1662. Thornton counted her as a friend and she was godmother to Thornton's daughter, Joyce, in 1665. She died on 26 February 1699 and was buried at St Mary the Virgin’s, Lewisham.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jh1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Hall</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Joseph Hall (1574-1656)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1574-07-01">1 July 1574</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1656-09-08">8 September 1656</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Joseph Hall, son of John and Winifred Hall, was born on 1 July 1574 at Bristow Park, Ashby-de-la-Zouch. He wrote the influential Art of Divine Meditation (1606) and put this theory into practice in several publications, including Meditations and Vowes, Divine and Morall (1605) and Occasional Meditations (1630). He was actively involved in the debates over church governance in the 1630s and 1640s and details his experiences in two autobiographies (first published in 1647): Observations of some Specialities of Divine Providence in the Life of Jos. Hall, Bishop of Norwich and Hard Measure. He became Bishop of Exeter in 1627 and Bishop of Norwich in 1647. He married Elizabeth Winniff in 1603 with whom he had eight children (six sons and two daughters). He died on 8 September 1656.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xh1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Hubert</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Hubert (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Hubert lived in the Dublin area in the 1620s and 1630s. He was not a very powerful man, perhaps a fisherman. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ah1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Hutton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Hutton (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Hutton may be the daughter of Thomas Wentworth's sister, Margaret, and her husband, Richard Hutton. Thornton describes her as a 'cousin', a kinship that could be claimed via great-great-grandfather George Bowes, to whom both the Wandesfords and Huttons were related. We have not been able to trace her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xi1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Innes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Innes (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Captain Robert Innes, a Scot, served as quartermaster in the Earl of Leven’s Horse Regiment in 1644. He fought at the battle of Marston Moor in July 1644, after which his regiment was stationed in Catterick and his soldiers were quartered at Alice Wandesford’s property, Hipswell Hall. Innes was still serving under Leven in 1646. We do not know when he died.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rj1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Janson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Ralph Janson (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ralph Janson was likely a servant in Alice Wandesford's household at Hipswell c.1646–51. He accompanied a young Thornton to Richmond in 1646. He was also present at her marriage in 1651. We have not been able to trace him further, although a Ralph Janson of Newton-le-Willows (North Yorks.), petitioned for a soldier's pension in 1670, so he may have fought in the civil wars.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tj1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Jenney</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Jenney (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Jenney was implicated in the murder of Thornton's nephew, Thomas Danby, in a tavern brawl in London in July 1667. While one William Berridge was convicted, Jenney and John Ogle were convicted of the lesser crime of manslaughter, respited from the usual punishment of being branded and pardoned that October. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jl2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Lambert</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Lambert (1619-1684)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1619-09-07">7 September 1619</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1684-03-01">1 March 1684</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Lambert, son of Josias Lambert and his second or third wife, Anne, was born on 7 September 1619. He was a parliamentarian general during the English Civil Wars. He married Frances Lister on 10 September 1639 and they had 10 children, three of whom survived to adulthood. He died on 1 March 1684.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="el1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Lascelles</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Edward Lascelles (died 1675?)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1675-08-22?">buried 22 August 1675?</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edward Lascelles was a coffin-bearer at the funeral of William Thornton in September 1668. He was probably a descendant of George Lascelles of Sturton and Gateford, Nottinghamshire, who married Eleanor Wandesford, a distant cousin of Thornton’s father. Perhaps the Edward Lascelles buried on 22 August 1675 at St Michael-le-Belfrey’s, York.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wl2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Laud</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Laud (1573-1645)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1573-10-07">7 October 1573</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1645-01-10">10 January 1645</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Laud, son of William and Lucy Laud, was born on 7 October 1573 in Reading. He was educated at Reading school and then the University of Oxford. He was elected Archbishop of Canterbury in 1633. A royalist, he was executed on 10 January 1645.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rl2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Legard</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Richard Legard (1607-c.1680)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1607-03-15">baptised 15 March 1607</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1680~">c.1680</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Richard Legard, second son of John and Elizabeth Legard, was baptised at St Nicholas’s, Ganton (North Riding) on 15 March 1607. He was related to Thornton via her great-great-grandfather, George Bowes, who married Dorothy Mallory, aunt of Legard's father. A barrister at the Middle Temple, he was admitted to Gray's Inn on 14 March 1625. He was a royalist captain during the Wars of the Three Kingdoms and was godfather to Thornton's eighth child, Joyce, in September 1665. He married Elizabeth, the widow (or, less likely, the daughter) of John Pierson of Mowthorpe, on 14 August 1666 at Nunburnholme (East Riding). They had no children. He died around 1680, when his will was witnessed.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xl2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Leslie</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">1st Lord Newark</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">David Leslie (1601-1682)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1601">1601</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1682-02">February 1682</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">David Leslie, son of Patrick and Jean Leslie, was born in 1601. He was an army officer in the employ of Alexander Leslie, 1st Earl Leven. A key figure in the parliamentarian success at the battle of Marston Moor in July 1644 as Major-General of the Horse for his regiment, he was stationed in Yorkshire. He married Jane Yorke and they had nine children (three sons and six daughters). He was elevated to the title of 1st Lord Newark by Charles II. He died in February 1682.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gl1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Lightfoot</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Lightfoot (died 1700)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1700-05-30">buried 30 May 1700</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Lightfoot was a servant in the household of Alice Wandesford; the first reference is to him moving to Hipswell with the family in 1644. He was present at Thornton’s marriage in 1651. He married another of the household servants, Daphne Cassell, before 1654, and they had at least two children (one a daughter). By 1656 they lived away from Hipswell Hall but they were witnesses to Alice Wandesford's will in 1658, in which they were left 20 shillings each. Thornton also rewarded them for their loyalty in 1669. He might be the George referenced in a letter from Thomas Comber to Thornton in 1682. He was widowed in 1689 and was buried at St Agatha’s, Gilling West, on 30 May 1700.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="al1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Barrett</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Loftus</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Barrett (c.1626-1659)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1626~">c.1626</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1659-04-04">4 April 1659</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Barrett, daughter of Robert and Eleanor Loftus, was born c.1626. She and her parents lived in the household of Thomas Wentworth in Dublin in the late 1630s, where she kept company with a young Thornton and Wentworth's daughters, Anne and Arabella. She married Richard Lennard Barrett c.1653 and had four children (two sons and two daughters). She died on 4 April 1659.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="el2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Loftus</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">2nd Viscount Elye</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Edward Loftus (c.1598-1680)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1598~">c.1598</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1680-04-11">11 April 1680</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edward Loftus, 2nd Viscount Elye, second son of Adam and Sarah Loftus, was born c.1598; his father was Lord Chancellor of Ireland between 1619–39. He married Jane Lindley and through her inherited Middleham Castle, Yorkshire, where Thornton's sister, Katherine Danby, gave birth to her penultimate child in August 1644. Edward had two children (a son and a daughter). He died on 11 April 1680.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rl3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Loftus</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Loftus (1614?-1672)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1614?">1614(?)</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1672-09-10">buried 10 September 1672</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Loftus was possibly born in 1614 to William Loftus and baptised at St Mary’s, Richmond. He was a servant in Alice Wandesford’s household, witnessing her will in 1658 in which she left him 20 shillings. The earliest reference we have to him at Hipswell Hall is as a witness to the Thorntons’ marriage in 1651, described as ‘of Waithwith’. In 1659 he is referred to as Christopher Wandesford’s steward at Hipswell. He married a woman called Elizabeth and had five children: four daughters and a son, also called Robert. In his will, dated 29 August 1672, he is described as a ‘yeoman’ and he left three farms, two in Hipswell. He was buried at St Michael and All Angels’, Hudswell on 10 September 1672.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wl1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Lowcock</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Lowcock (died 1678)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1678-07-31">31 July 1678</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Lowcock was rector of All Saints’, Nunnington from 1658 until his death in 1678. He married Helen Bentley of Pannal on 10 October 1661 at All Saints’, Nunnington and they had two daughters and two sons. He baptised Thornton's son, Robert, in 1662 at the family home, East Newton Hall. He died on 31 July 1678.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cm1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Maguire</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">2nd Baron Enniskillen</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Connor Maguire (1616-1645)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1616">1616</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1645-02-20">20 February 1645</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Connor Maguire, eldest son of Brian Roe and Rose Maguire, was born in 1616. He attended the University of Oxford but did not graduate. On his father's death in 1632, he became 2nd Baron Enniskillen. He married Mary Fleming and they had one son. As a member of the House of Lords in Ireland, he was one of the conspirators in the failed plot to seize Dublin Castle during the Irish rebellion of 1641 and was imprisoned in the Tower of London. He escaped for five weeks in 1644, but was recaptured, stood trial and executed at Tyburn on 20 February 1645.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="hm1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">MacMahon</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Hugh Óg MacMahon (c.1606-1644)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1606~">1606/1607</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1644-11-22">22 November 1644</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Hugh Óg MacMahon, son of Brian Hugh Óg MacMahon and his wife Mary, was born in 1606 or 1607. He was a conspirator in the failed 1641 plot to seize Dublin Castle during the Irish Rebellion and it was his drunken confession to his Protestant foster brother, Owen Connolly, which brought down the plot. He was imprisoned in the Tower of London but escaped for five weeks in August 1644, before being recaptured. He was put on trial on 13 November 1644 and executed at Tyburn on 22 November.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="em1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Mainwaring</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Edmund Mainwaring (1579-c.1643)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1579">1579</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1643~">c.1643</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edmund Mainwaring, second son of Randle and Margaret Mainwaring of Over Peover, Cheshire, was born in 1579. He matriculated at Brasenose College, Oxford in 1594 and All Souls in 1600. His doctorate in civil law was conferred in 1629. He married a woman called Jane and they had three children (one daughter and two sons), who were baptised in York. A civil lawyer, he held various positions before becoming Chancellor of Chester in 1634. In 1642 he and his wife helped Alice Wandesford and family on their arrival in the city. He died c.1643.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xm2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Mainwaring</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Jane Mainwaring (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Jane Mainwaring was the wife of Edmund Mainwaring. Her birth name is unknown, but she is thought to have come from York. She and Edmund married before 1614 and had three children (one daughter and two sons). They were living in Chester in 1642 and helped Alice Wandesford and family on their arrival there.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xm3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Mainwaring</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Captain Mainwaring (c.1616-c.1645)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1616~">c.1616</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1645-10-09~">c. 9 October 1645</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Mainwaring was the eldest son of Edmund and Jane Mainwaring, born c.1616. He matriculated King’s College, Cambridge in 1629, graduating with his MA in 1632. He then studied at Gray’s Inn. On 24 September 1639 he married Hester Wase at St Mary’s, Islington. Between 1640–45 they had six children (four sons and two daughters), although all four of their sons died in infancy. The couple moved to Chester in the early 1640s and, when the first English Civil War broke out in 1642, Mainwaring enrolled as a Sergeant-Major. He was knighted at Oxford on 9 January 1643, having fought for the king at Edge Hill in October 1642. When William Brereton’s parliamentary forces attacked Chester in 1643, leading to a siege, he commanded men in the defence of the city, acting as a member of the council approving the dispatch of troops, and then as a senior commissioner in 1644. Mainwaring was shot and killed, around 9 October 1645, trying to defend the city during a successful attack by Brereton’s forces. His memorial in Chester Cathedral, erected in 1671, erroneously gives his year of death as 1644.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rm1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Meredith</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Meredith (c.1597-1668)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1597~">c.1597</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1668-10-17">17 October 1668</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Meredith of Greenhills, co. Kildare, son of Richard and Sarah Meredith, was born c.1597; his father was Bishop of Leighlin. He was admitted to Lincoln’s Inn in 1611. He married Anne Usher, a cousin of Sir Adam Loftus (who became Lord Chancellor in 1619) in 1618 and they had three sons. He became Loftus’s secretary in 1625 and served as Chancellor of the Exchequer of Ireland from 1634 until his death, working closely with the Lord Deputy, Thomas Wentworth. A puritan, he plotted against Wentworth, survived his fall in 1640, and was arrested in 1643 for supporting the English parliament. He became Keeper of the Great Seal of Ireland in 1648 and served as a commissioner during the Interregnum. He was reappointed as Chancellor with the Restoration in 1660. He died on 17 October 1668 and was buried in the family vault at St Patrick's Cathedral, Dublin.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mm1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Margery</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Milbank</surname>
                  <addName type="nickname">Nan</addName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Margery Milbank (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Margery (alias Nan) Milbank, daughter of Lancelot Milbank, was baptised on 24 February 1635 at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave. She was in service with the Thorntons at East Newton Hall c.1667–68. She was implicated in the spreading of rumours about Thornton and Thomas Comber in 1668 but repented, according to Thornton. We have not been able to trace her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gm1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Monck</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">1st Duke of Albermarle</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Monck (1608-1670)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1608-12-06">6 December 1608</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1670-01-01">1 January 1670</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Monck, the fourth son of Sir Thomas Monck and his wife, Elizabeth, was born on 6 December 1608 at Great Potheridge, Devon. He volunteered in the English expedition against Cadiz in 1625, which was the beginning of a very successful military career. A colonel in the royalist army, he landed in Dublin in 1642 to help quell the Irish uprising. He married Anne Clarges in 1653 and they had one son. Becoming Cromwell’s commander-in-chief in Scotland, he was a key player in the Restoration of 1660, by negotiating with the exiled king, dissolving the Rump Parliament in favour of the Convention Parliament, and marching to London with his army to arrange for Charles II’s return from the continent. He died on 1 January 1670.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pn1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Nesbit</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Philip Nesbit (c.1616-1663)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1616~">c.1616</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1663-10-15">buried 15 October 1663</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Philip Nesbit was the son of Philip and Elizabeth Nesbit of St Martin’s Micklegate, York. He received his BA and MA from Corpus Christi, Cambridge in 1638 and 1641 respectively. He married Susan Hemmingway and they had six children (four sons and two daughters), five of whom survived childhood. He was minister of Hutton Buscel, Yorkshire until 1647, and then held the rectorship of St Michael the Archangel’s, Kirklington from 1649–62, when he was removed for refusing to subscribe to the Act of Uniformity. He died the next year and was buried at St Martin’s Micklegate, York on 15 October 1663.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rn1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Nettleton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Nettleton (1601-1673)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1601">1601</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1673-07-03">buried 3 July 1673</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Nettleton, the eldest son of Thomas and Mary Nettleton of Thornhill, Yorks., was born in 1601. He was educated at Gray’s Inn (1619) and gained his Oxford BA in 1621 and MA in 1623. He married Frances Rawlinson and they had nine children (six daughters and three sons). He arrived in Ireland with his younger brother, George, c.1633 and was elected MP for Lifford in 1639, returning to Yorkshire in the early 1640s. In 1652 he inherited a debt from his sister whose late husband had lent Christopher Wandesford £500 pre-1640. William Thornton became a target when he took over the role of administering Wandesford's will c.1661. Nettleton died in 1673 after falling from a horse and was buried on 3 July at St Michael and All Angels’, Thornhill.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cn1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Norton (c.1631-1685?)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1631~">c.1631</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1685?">after 1685</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Norton, third son of Maulger and Anne Norton, was born c.1631; he was Thornton's first cousin. He was still alive in 1685 when he sold the family home of St Nicholas, Richmond. He had a daughter, Anne.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wn1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Norton (1625-1666)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1625-07-02">baptised 2 July 1625</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1666-12">December 1666</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Norton, son of Maulger and Anne Norton, was baptised on 2 July 1625 at All Saints’, Manfield (North Yorks.); he was Thornton's cousin. He was admitted to Gray's Inn on 2 September 1649 and was murdered in a tavern brawl in London in December 1666.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jo1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Ogle</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Ogle (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Ogle was implicated in the murder of Thornton's nephew, Thomas Danby, in a tavern brawl in London in July 1667. While one William Berridge was convicted, Ogle and Thomas Jenney were convicted of the lesser crime of manslaughter, respited from the usual punishment of being branded and pardoned that October. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="awo1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Middleton</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Osborne</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Walmesley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Osborne (died 1666)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1666-08-20">buried 20 August 1666</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Osborne was the daughter of Thomas Walmesley of Dunkenhalgh and his first wife, Eleanor. She married William Middleton and they had no children. On his death, she married (before 1630) Edward Osborne, Thornton's maternal uncle, and became his second wife. They had a child, Thomas, who became the first Duke of Leeds. She was buried on 20 August 1666 at All Hallows’, Harthill.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ho1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Osborne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Hewett Osborne (1567-1599)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1567-03-13">baptised 13 March 1567</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1599-09">September 1599</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Hewett Osborne, son of Sir Edward and Anna Osborne, was baptised on 13 March 1567; he was Thornton's maternal grandfather. He was admitted to the Inner Temple in 1585. He married Joyce Fleetwood on 26 December 1588 in a double marriage with her sister, Bridget, and William Smith. They had three children: two sons and a daughter (Thornton’s mother, Alice). A soldier, Osborne served under Lord Willoughby in France in 1590, the Earl of Essex in Cadiz in 1597 and then in Ireland in 1599. He owned lands at Kiveton, Yorkshire, but lived in Essex. He died in September 1599 during a skirmish with Irish rebels.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jfo1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Osborne</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Frescheville</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Fleetwood</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Joyce Frescheville (1569-1619)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1569">1569</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1619-04-16?">16 April(?) 1619</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Joyce Frescheville, daughter of Sir Thomas Fleetwood of the Vache and his second wife, Bridget, was born in 1569; she was Thornton’s maternal grandmother. She married Sir Hewett Osborne of Kiveton on 26 December 1588 and they had two children (a son and a daughter). Widowed in 1599, she married Sir Peter Frescheville on 18 October 1604 and they had three children. She died on 16 April 1619 and was buried at St John the Baptist’s, Staveley, Derbyshire.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cp1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Parkes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Parkes (born c.1642)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1642~">c. 1642</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Parkes, born c. 1642, attended St John's College, Cambridge where he graduated with an MA in 1663. He was vicar of St Anne’s, Catterick from 1660 and minister of the chapel at Hipswell, Bolton-super-Swale and Hudswell. We do not know when he died.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jp1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Payton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Payton (1561-1616)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1561">1561</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1616-12-19">19 December 1616</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir John Payton, son of Robert and Elizabeth Payton, was born in 1561. He married Alice Osborne, sister of Hewett Osborne, on 29 June 1580, making him Thornton's maternal great-uncle by marriage. They had thirteen children (six sons and seven daughters). He was twice elected MP for Cambridgeshire, in 1593 and in 1604. He died on 19 December 1616.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wp1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Parsons</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Parsons (c.1570-1650)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1570~">c.1570</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1650">1650</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Parsons, son of James and Catherine Parsons, was born c.1570. He was Surveyor General of Ireland (1602–11), MP for Newcastle Borough, County Dublin, 1613–15, MP for County Wicklow (1640–43), and he served as one of two Lord Justices of Ireland after the death of Christopher Wandesford. He married Elizabeth Lany c.1615 and they had twelve children (five sons and seven daughters). He died in January or February 1650 and was buried at St Margaret’s, Westminster.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jp2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Plummer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Plummer (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Plummer was a trooper serving under Thornton’s cousin, Edmund Norton. He gave evidence that George Wandesford was near Marston Moor on the day of the battle (2 July 1644). In March 1651 he discovered George Wandesford’s body near Catterick Bridge. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ftp1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Portington</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Frances Portington (died 1705)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1705-03-11">buried 11 March 1705</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Frances Portington was the daughter of Robert and Elizabeth Thornton; she was the youngest sister of William Thornton. In 1662 she was at East Newton to attend the birth of Thornton’s seventh child. She became the third wife of Timothy Portington of Malton on 27 July 1663 and they had one son. She was buried at St Michael’s, New Malton on 11 March 1705.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tp1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Portington</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Timothy Portington (c.1630-1697)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1630~">c.1630</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1697-06-26">26 June 1697</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Timothy Portington, son of Francis and Ellen Portington, was born c.1630. An apothecary in New Malton, he was married three times: to Mary Pye (d.1654), Mary Ruddock (d.1662), and Frances Thornton, the younger sister of William Thornton. He had a daughter with Mary Ruddock and a son with Frances. He died on 26 June 1697.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xr1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Raines</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Raines (c.1640-1713)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1640~">c.1640</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1713-03-08">8 March 1713</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is possibly Thomas Raines, born c.1640 to James and Sarah Raines of Appleton-le-Street, Ryedale. He was Attorney of the Court of Common Pleas of Westminster, displaced by Charles II in 1688, after which he retired to Easingwold. He was Lord Mayor of York in 1660. He married Mary Conyers in 1668. He died on 8 March 1713 and was buried at St John and All Saints’, Easingwold.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gr1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Radcliffe</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Radcliffe (1593-1657)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1593-04-21">baptised 21 April 1593</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1657">1657</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir George Radcliffe, the son of Nicholas and Margaret Radcliffe, was baptised on 21 April 1593. He was educated at University College, Oxford where he graduated in May 1612, having entered Gray's Inn in February 1612. He was called to the bar in 1618. He was briefly engaged to the only daughter of John Finch, but she died aged 10 in 1621. He married Anne Trappes at St Michael and All Angels’, Thornhill on 21 February 1622 and they had one child (a son). He was a cousin-by-marriage of Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl Strafford, and he became part of Wentworth's Irish administration 1633–40. He was imprisoned in Dublin Castle after being tried for treason in 1640. After his release in 1642 he spent much of his time in the Netherlands and died in 1657.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mr2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Richardson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Martha Richardson (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Martha Richardson was a witness to Alice and William Thornton's marriage at Hipswell Hall in 1651. She was perhaps a servant. We have not been able to trace her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jr1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Rimer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Jane Rimer (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Jane Rimer was a midwife who helped Thornton deliver her third child at Hipswell in 1655. We have not been able to trace her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ar1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Anne</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Robinson</surname>
                  <addName type="nickname">Nan</addName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Robinson (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Robinson was a servant in the Thornton household, first in Richmond in 1660 and then in Oswaldkirk in 1661, where she is referred to as daughter Katherine’s maid. She married one of William Thornton’s servants, unnamed, and they rented a place to live on the Thornton’s estate of East Newton. She is possibly the Anne Robinson who married John Conyers at St Radegund’s, Scruton on 4 April 1662.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mr1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Robinson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Matthew Robinson (1628-1694)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1628-12-14">baptised 14 December 1628</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1694-11-27">27 November 1694</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Matthew Robinson, third son of Thomas and Frances Robinson, was baptised at St Mary the Virgin’s, Rokeby (North Yorks.) on 14 December 1628. He graduated from Cambridge in 1652 and was appointed vicar of St Lambert’s, Burneston in 1651, a position he held for 40 years. He married Jane Pickering on 12 October 1657 and they had no children. He died at Ripley on 27 November 1694 and was buried at St Lambert’s, Burneston.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xr2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Robinson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Leonard Robinson (c.1618-1673)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1618~">c.1618</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1673-03-23">buried 23 March 1673</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Leonard Robinson, son of Thomas and Sythe Robinson of Applegarth, was born c.1618. He entered Gray’s Inn on 4 May 1639. He married Lucy Phillips and they had six children (a son and five daughters). A gentleman, he was accused in 1662 of pretending to be the lord of the manor of Ravensworth so he could lay claim to lead and coal mines on Hudswell Moor that Sir Christopher Wandesford claimed as part of his lands. He was buried on 23 March 1674 at St Peter and St Felix, Kirkby Ravensworth.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rr1">
               <persName>
                  <roleName type="peerage">Prince and count of the Palatinate</roleName>
                  <roleName type="peerage">Duke of Cumberland</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Prince Rupert (1619-1682)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1619-12-18">18 December 1619</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1682-11-29">29 November 1682</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Prince Rupert of the Palatinate, Duke of Cumberland, was born on 18 December 1619 to Frederick V of the Palatinate and Countess Louisa Juliana of Nassau. He was one of the main military commanders in the Wars of the Three Kingdoms. He had two children, a son with Francesca Bard, to whom his marriage has never been acknowledged (although a purported marriage certificate dated 1664 has been found), and a daughter with Margaret Hughes. He died on 29 November 1682.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="aws1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Savile</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Overton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wake</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">Countess of Sussex</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Overton (1647-1679)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1647-01-19">baptised 19 January 1647</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1679">1679</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Overton, daughter of Robert and Mabel Wake, was baptised on 19 January 1647. She married James Savile, 2nd Earl of Sussex, before 1661 and they lived at Howley Hall, Morley from 1661. They had one son, who died as an infant in July 1671. After her husband’s death, later in 1671, she married Fairfax Overton in April 1674. She died in 1679.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ls1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Sayer</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Laurence Sayer (born c.1632)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1632~">c.1632</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Laurence Sayer, son of Laurence and Elizabeth Sayer, was born c.1632. The Sayers were a royalist, Catholic family in Worsall (North Yorks.), whose estate (Yarm, Preston, Egglecliffe, Worsall) was forfeited in the 1650s when it was owned by Laurence Sayer senior. With the Restoration, Sayer junior leased it back from the new owner, Gilbert Crouch, but agreed to its selling 1670–73, leaving only a small parcel of land in Aislaby. By 1684 he was living in Ireland.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rs1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Shuttleworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Richard Shuttleworth (c.1587-1669)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1587~">c.1587</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1669-06-29">buried 29 June 1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Richard Shuttleworth, son of Thomas and Anne Shuttleworth, was born c.1587. In 1608 he inherited the newly-built Gawthorpe Hall from his uncle, Richard Shuttleworth. He studied at Brasenose College, Oxford and Gray’s Inn. He married Fleetwood Barton on 24 April 1612 at St Anne’s, Woodplumpton, with whom he had 12 children (eight sons and four daughters). He was a Justice of the Peace in Lancashire by 1616 and probably served twice as High Sheriff of Lancashire, in 1620 and 1636–37. He was made a colonel of the parliamentary army in 1642, defending northeast Lancashire, and won a significant victory at Read Bridge. He was MP for Preston from 1640 until 1648 and was re-elected in 1654 during the Interregnum, when he also leading magistrate for the Blackburn hundred. He was buried on 29 June 1669 at St Leonard’s, Padiham.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Sinclair</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Enoch(?) Sinclair (born c.1608)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1608~">c.1608</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is possibly Enoch Sinclair who was born c.1608. He was educated at St John's College, Cambridge, graduating in 1633. He was made curate of Auburn Chapel, Carnaby (East Riding) in 1635, a position he held until at least 1638, and was perhaps rector of All Saints’, Slingsby c.1650. William Thornton sent for Sinclair from Malton when he was sick in 1668. We do not know when he died.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mss1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Smith</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Smyth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mary Smith (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Smith was the daughter of Hugh and Elizabeth Smyth of Long Ashton, Somerset. She married Sir Thomas Smith of Hatherton, Cheshire on 20 December 1616 at All Saints’, Long Ashton. They had 22 children. We do not know when she died.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ts1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Smith</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Smith (c.1595-c.1668)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1595~">c.1595</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1668~">c.1668</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Thomas Smith, son of Thomas and Anne Smith of Hatherton, Cheshire, was born c.1595. He married Mary Smyth on 20 December 1616 at All Saints’, Long Ashton, and they had 22 children.  He was Mayor of Chester from 1622 and High Sheriff of Cheshire in 1623. He sat as MP for Chester 1640–44 in the Short and then Long Parliaments, before being barred from Parliament for his royalist support. He died c.1668.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Smith</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Dr Smith (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dr Smith was a physician active in the Richmondshire area of North Yorkshire in the late 1650s. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs12">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Smith</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Henry Smith (c.1560-1591)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1560~">c.1560</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1591-07-04">4 July 1591</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Henry Smith was born c.1560 in Withcote, Leicestershire, to Erasmus and Anne Smith. He was admitted to Queen’s College, Cambridge in 1573, leaving soon afterwards to attend Lincoln College, Oxford, graduating with his BA in 1579. He became a lecturer at St Clement Danes without Temple Bar in 1587. Suffering with poor health, he died on 4 July 1591 and was buried at Husbands Bosworth. While he has been described as the most popular Puritan preacher of the Elizabethan era, Smith had little time for separatist ideas and his avoidance of controversial theological issues made his sermons very popular. Over twenty editions of his collected sermons were published between 1592 and 1675.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="hs1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Smithson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Hugh Smithson (c.1598-1670)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1598~">c.1598</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1670-10-21">21 October 1670</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Hugh Smithson of Stanwick St John (North Yorks.), son of Anthony and Eleanor Smithson, was born c.1598. He was a London merchant, recusant and royalist, made Baronet of Stanwick in 1660 by Charles II for his support. He married Dorothy Rawsthorne and they had six children (four sons and two daughters). He died on 21 October 1670.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="js1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Jerome</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Smithson</surname>
                  <addName type="alias">Jeremy </addName>
                  <roleName type="peerage">2nd Baronet Stanwick</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Sir Jerome Smithson (1632-1684)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1632">1632</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1684">1684</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Jerome Smithson, eldest son and heir of Sir Hugh Smithson, 1st Baronet Stanwick, and his wife, Dorothy, was born in 1632 (named Jeremy). In the late 1640s or very early 1650s, he unsuccessfully plotted to abduct Thornton from her mother’s property at Hipswell Hall. He married Mary Wingate and they had a son and a daughter. He changed his name from Jeremy to Jerome, possibly when he was knighted in 1670 on his father’s death, when he also became 2nd Baronet. He died in 1684.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Smithson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Uncle Smithson (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Uncle Smithson was one of Sir Jerome's Smithson's paternal uncles: Francis, Richard or John. We have not been able to identify him any more precisely.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cs2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Stuart</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">King Charles II</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Charles Stuart (1630-1685)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1630-05-29">29 May 1630</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1685-02-06">6 February 1685</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles Stuart, King Charles II of England, Scotland and Ireland, was born on 29 May 1630 to King Charles I and Henrietta Maria. He was King of Scotland 1649–51 and King of England, Scotland and Ireland from the Restoration of 1660 until his death in 1685. He married Catherine of Braganza but had no legitimate issue. He fathered at least twelve children out of wedlock by various mistresses. He died on 6 February 1685.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Thomson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Thomson (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Thomson perhaps owned the coaching inn at the south end of Catterick Bridge in 1651. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ct1">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Christopher</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
                  <addName type="nickname">Kitt</addName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Thornton (1667-1667)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1667-11-11">11 November 1667</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1667-12-02">2 December 1667</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Thornton, the 9th child of Alice and William Thornton, was born at East Newton on 11 November 1667 and baptized the next day at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave. He contracted smallpox and died on 1 December 1667. He was buried at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave the following day.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jt1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Joyce Thornton (1665-1666)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1665-09-23">23 September 1665</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1666-01-26">26 January 1666</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Joyce Thornton, the eighth child of Alice and William Thornton, was born on 23 September 1665 at East Newton and baptized on the 28th at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave.  She fell ill on 20 January 1666 and died on the 26th. She was buried the next day at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rt2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Robert</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
                  <addName type="nickname">Robin</addName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Thornton (1662-1692)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1662-09-19">19 September 1662</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1692-06-04">4 June 1692</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Thornton was the seventh child and third son of Alice and William Thornton. He was born on 19 September 1662 at East Newton and baptised the next day at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave. He was educated first by his uncle, John Denton, then by the reverend John Burton at Sutton-on-the-Forest. He entered Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge in April 1680, before moving to University College, Oxford in May 1682. In 1687 he became the rector of Oddington, Gloucestershire but resigned later that year. By 1688 he was in considerable debt and in 1689 he was working as a chaplain on a naval ship. In 1691 he was offered a living in Northamptonshire but swapped it for that of Boldon in the diocese of Durham and resided at the Deanery in Durham with his sister, Alice, and her husband, Thomas Comber. In 1692 Comber helped arrange a marriage for him, to a woman worth £2800, but he fell ill and died on 4 June 1692, aged 29. He is buried in the Chapel of the Nine Altars, Durham Cathedral.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rt3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Thornton (c.1575-1637)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1575~">c.1575</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1637-05-27">buried 27 May 1637</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Thornton, the son of William and Eleanor Thornton of East Newton, was born c.1575; he was William Thornton’s father. His first marriage was to Dorothy Metham and they had four daughters, one of whom died in infancy. Dorothy was buried in July 1619, after which he married Elizabeth Darley, with whom he had seven children (four sons and three daughters). He was buried at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave on 27 May 1637.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tt1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Thornton (1626-1685)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1626-08-29">baptised 29 August 1626</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1685-08-17">buried 17 August 1685</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Thornton, son of Robert and Elizabeth Thornton, was baptised 29 August 1626 at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave; he was the younger brother of William Thornton and was involved in his funeral procession. He was buried on 17 August 1685 at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wt2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Thornton (1660-1660)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1660-04-17">17 April 1660</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1660-04-28">28 April 1660</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Thornton, the sixth child of Alice and William Thornton, was born and baptized at St Nicholas, Richmond, on 17 April 1660. He died on 28 April 1660 of smallpox and was buried the next day at St Agatha’s, Easby.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt5">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Tirrill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Tirrill (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Tirrill of Hoddesdon was a chief mourner at the funeral of Thornton's brother, John Wandesford, at St Augustine’s, Broxbourne, Herts in 1664. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="bt1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Pape</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Todd</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Barbara Todd (died 1675)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1675-09-09">buried 9 September 1675</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Barbara Pape, then Todd, worked as a maid for Anne Danby and lived at East Newton Hall in the late 1660s. She left in 1668, after being implicated in spreading rumours about Thornton. She married John Pape on 29 May 1670 at Nunnington. They had at least one child and seem to have moved to New Malton, where she was treated by Thornton’s brother-in-law, Timothy Portington. She was buried on 9 September 1675 at St Leonard's, New Malton.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Troutbeck</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Troutbeck (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Troutbeck is described by Thornton as being ‘young’ in 1655 when he visited her sick mother at Hipswell Hall, near Catterick, and gave medical advice. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="et2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Tudor</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth Tudor (1533-1603)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1533-09-07">7 September 1533</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1603-03-24">24 March 1603</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth I was Queen of England from 1558 until her death in 1603. Born on 7 September 1533, she was the daughter of Henry VIII and his second wife, Anne Boleyn. She died on 24 March 1603.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cw4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Wandesford (c.1548-1590)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1548~">c.1548</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1590-07-11">buried 11 July 1590</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Christopher Wandesford, son of Francis and Jane Wandesford of Kirklington, was born c.1548; he was Thornton's great-grandfather. He married Elizabeth Bowes c.1568 and they had four children (three sons and a daughter). He was the Vice President of the Council of the North and was responsible for escorting Mary Queen of Scots from Carlisle to Bolton in 1568. He was buried at St Michael the Archangel’s, Kirklington on 11 July 1590.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cw5">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Wandesford (1617-c.1623)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1617-03-20">20 March 1617</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1623~">c.1623</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Wandesford, second child of Christopher and Alice Wandesford, was born on 20 March 1617; he was Thornton's brother. He died aged six, c.1623, according to Thornton. His date of death has been given as 1627 elsewhere which seems to be based on a misreading of the baptism date of his younger brother, Christopher, in the Kirklington parish registers.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ww2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Wandesford (born 1595)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1595?">after 1595</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Wandesford, born after 1595, was the son of Richard and Muriel Wandesford of Pickhill; he was a distant cousin of Thornton's father. He married Elizabeth Ayscough of Osgoodby on 27 October 1619 and by 1624 they had three sons. He was in Dublin in 1640 and was an executor of Christopher Wandesford's will.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="lw1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wastell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Luke Wastell (died 1697)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1697-02-16">buried 16 February 1697</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Luke Wastell was the third son of Leonard and Anne Wastell of Scorton, North Yorks. Wastell was executor of his father’s will in 1630, in which he was left all of his father’s lands in Brompton and Northallerton. He married twice: Dorothy Laton and then Elizabeth Alleson (née Patison). He was a parliamentarian during the 1640s. He was buried at St Mary’s, Kirkby Fleetham on 16 February 1697.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rw2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Webster</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Webster (died 1667)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1667-10-27">buried 27 October 1667</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Webster was a servant, perhaps initially for Alice Wandesford, as he was present at the Thornton’s wedding at Hipswell in 1651. He is described as being ‘from Nunnington’ in the parish register entry for the wedding. By 1661 he was described as William Thornton’s ‘man’; at this date, Thornton and her servant, Jane Flower, tried to persuade another servant, Anne Robinson, to marry him, although this was not realised. He was buried at All Saints and St James’, Nunnington on 27 October 1667.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="erw1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Wentworth</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Rhodes</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">Lady Strafford</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth Wentworth (c.1614-1688)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1614~">c.1614</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1688-04-10">10 April 1688</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth Wentworth, daughter of Godfrey and Anne Rhodes, was born c.1614. She became the third wife of Thomas Wentworth c.1632 and they had two children (a son and a daughter). She was also stepmother to Wentworth's children from his second wife, Arabella Holles. She died on 10 April 1688.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ww3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wentworth</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">2nd Lord Raby</roleName>
                  <roleName type="peerage">2nd Earl Strafford</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Wentworth (1626-1695)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1626-06-08">8 June 1626</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1695-10-16">16 October 1695</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Wentworth, 2nd Lord Raby, 2nd Earl Strafford, son of Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl Strafford and his second wife, Arabella, was born on 8 June 1626 at the family home of Wentworth Woodhouse. By 1635, he was knighted in Dublin. He matriculated Trinity College, Dublin on 12 January 1638 and Christ Church, Oxford on 21 March 1642, after which he left England for nine years in the wake of his father’s execution, returning around 1651. His estates were sequestered in 1652 but he regained his family title in 1662. He was elected to the Royal Society in 1668 but ejected in 1685 for non-payment of arrears. He was made privy councillor in 1672 and privy councillor of Ireland in 1677. He married twice: first, Henrietta Maria Stanley in 1654; second, Henrietta de la Rochfoucauld. He died without issue on 16 October 1695 and was buried in York Minster.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="pcw1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Wharton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Carey</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Philadelphia Wharton (died 1654)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1654">1654</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is probably Philadelphia Wharton, daughter of Robert and Elizabeth Carey. She was a lady-in-waiting to Princess Elizabeth, Queen of Bohemia and married Sir Thomas Wharton of Aske Hall on 11 April 1611. They had two sons. She died in 1654 or 1655 and was buried at St Agatha’s, Easby.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rw3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Widdrington</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Ralph Widdrington (c.1615-1688)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1615~">c.1615</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1688-06-10">10 June 1688</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ralph Widdrington, son of Lewis and Catherine Widdrington of Cheeseburn Grange, Northumberland, was born c.1615. He attended Morpeth School and matriculated Christ's College, Cambridge in 1632. He was admitted to Gray's Inn in 1641, before being ordained and tutoring at Christ's College, where he taught Thornton's younger brother, John Wandesford, in the late 1640s. He became Regius Professor of Greek in 1654 and was awarded a doctorate of Divinity in 1661. He died in Cambridge on 10 June 1688.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cw3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wyvill</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">3rd Baronet of Constable Burton</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Wyvill (1614-1681)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1614-12-06">baptised 6 December 1614</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1681-02-08">buried 8 February 1681</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Christopher Wyvill, 3rd Baronet of Constable Burton, eldest son of Marmaduke and Isabel Wyvill, was baptised on 6 December 1614. He married Ursula Darcy on 12 December 1636 and the couple had 12 children, six of whom predeceased them. He wrote an elegy for Thornton's brother, George Wandesford, on his death in 1651 and took part in Alice Wandesford’s funeral in 1659. He was elected MP for Richmond in 1659 and returned to the Long Parliament in 1660. He was buried with his wife, who died in 1680, at St Mary’s, Masham on 8 February 1681.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ch1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Hunton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Hunton (died 1644?)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1644?">before 1644</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Christopher Hunton was Christopher Wandesford’s steward at Kirklington from at least 1623 until at least 1636. He was named in deeds with Wandesford as early as 1618. Described as a yeoman, he was married to a woman named Ellen. He had left Wandesford’s service by 1640 when he was described as a ‘late servant’ in his will. He died by 1644, around which time Ellen married again.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xe3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Edrington</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Edrington (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Edrington was a friend or acquaintance of Thornton in the late 1660s who heard (and seemingly believed) the slanders spread about Thornton by Anne Danby. Thornton was able to convince him of her innocence, with Daphne Lightfoot’s help, and he wrote her a letter in 1669 to comfort her about the rumours that had been spread.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gw2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Wandesford (1572-1612)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1572-05-20">20 May 1572</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1612-09-11">11 September 1612</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir George Wandesford, son of Sir Christopher and Elizabeth Wandesford, was born 20 May 1572; he was Thornton’s paternal grandfather. He married twice: first, Catherine Hansby on 10 August 1591, with whom he had four children (three sons and a daughter); second, Mary Pamplyn, with whom he had two children (a son and a daughter). He had alterations made to the fifteenth-century manor house, Hipswell Hall, in 1596. He was knighted at Whitehall in 1607. He seems to have been financially imprudent as much of his inheritance was lost or sold during his lifetime. He died on a trip to London on 11 September 1612 and was buried at St Andrew’s, Holborn.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xa2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Ande</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Ande (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Ande lived in the Ripon area in the late 1660s. He was married to Jane Wandesford, Thornton’s cousin. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xa3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Anstruther</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Philip Anstruther (c.1630-1702)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1630~">c. 1630</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1702">1702</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is probably Sir Philip Anstruther, the son of Sir Robert and Mary Anstruther born c.1632. He inherited the Anstruther estate from his childless uncle, John Anstruther, in 1649. He was a royalist colonel during the Wars of the Three Kingdoms and was captured at the final royalist defeat at Worcester in 1651 and had his property sequestered by Cromwell. He was reinstated under Charles II. He married Christian Lumsden and they had 10 children (seven sons and three daughters). He died in 1702.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="aa1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Ayscough</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Alan Ayscough (c.1588-1672?)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1588~">c. 1588</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1672?">1672(?)</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is perhaps Alan Ayscough, son of Christopher Ayscough, baptised on 29 April 1587 at St Mary’s, Richmond. He entered Queen’s College, Oxford in 1605 aged 17 and entered Gray’s Inn in May 1606.  He married Anne Braithwaite, with whom he had five sons. His will was proved at York in January 1673, suggesting he died the previous year; he was buried at St Peter’s, Dalby-cum-Skewsby. Thornton describes him as ‘cousin’ when he wrote to her on her husband’s death in September 1668.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rb1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Barwick</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Barwick (1587-1660)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1587-12-02">2 December 1587</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1660-04-25">25 April 1660</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Robert Barwick, son of Robert Barwick, was baptised on 2 December 1587 at Doncaster. He was admitted to Gray’s Inn on 29 October 1611. He married twice: first, Mary Ellis at St Martin’s, Coney Street, York, on 3 January 1618; and, second, Ursula Strickland, on 26 October 1630 at St Andrew’s, Boynton. They had three children (a son and two daughters). A barrister and master in chancery, his seat was at Toulston Hall, Newton Kyme. He was elected deputy recorder of York on 17 April 1637, knighted by Charles I at York on 21 November 1641, and elected recorder of York in 1658. He died on 25 April 1660 and was buried at St Andrew’s, Newton Kyme.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb13">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Beal</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Cozen Beal (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Cousin Beal helped purchase a bed in London for Alice and William Thornton, perhaps after their move to East Newton in 1662. We have not been able to identify her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb10">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Bennett</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Gilbert Bennett (c.1599-1669)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1599~">c.1599</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1669-12-10">buried 10 December 1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Gilbert Bennett was born c.1599. He matriculated at Christ's College, Cambridge in July 1617 and graduated with his MA in 1624. He was ordained priest at Peterborough in 1625 and was rector of Bilsthorpe, Notts. 1625–34. He is possibly the Gilbert Bennett who married Theodosia Goodricke at St Michael’s, Linby, Notts. on 8 October 1633. Bennett held the prebendary of Southwell Minster, Notts. from 1660. He was vicar of St John the Baptist’s, Carnaby from 1662–64, rector of Holy Trinity, Stonegrave 1663–36 (which living he then leased to the Thorntons), and prebend of York 1667–69. Bennett had at least two daughters. He was buried at Southwell Minster on 10 December 1669.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb11">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Bradley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Bradley (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Bradley was a married acquaintance of William Thornton’s, who advised on a route from East Newton to Osgoodby, Thirsk in 1652. We have been unable to identify him more precisely.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb12">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Browne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mrs Browne (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mrs Browne was possibly the wife or female relation of Benjamin Browne as they were present together at East Newton Hall in August 1662. We have not been able to identify her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jb7">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Burniston</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Burniston (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Burniston was a witness to Christopher Wandesford's will in 1640. He also confirmed the veracity of the will when it was rediscovered c.1647 in Dublin, writing to William Wandesford to let him know the will had been located. He is possibly the same John Burniston who was sword-bearer of Ireland under the Commonwealth in the 1650s.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb9">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Burton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Dr Burton (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dr Burton was made a trustee of a deed of gift for Thornton’s children c.1668/9. No further identification made.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb8">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Butterfield</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">? Butterfield (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Butterfield was a tenant on Alice Wandesford’s land, whom Thornton allowed to stay until the end of the lease c.1666.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="hc1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Cholmley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Henry Cholmley (1609-1666)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1609-02-02">baptised 2 February 1609</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1666-06-30">buried 30 June 1666</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Henry Cholmley, second surviving son of Sir Richard Cholmley and his wife, Susanna, was baptised 2 February 1609. He was originally intended for the legal profession but was expelled from the Temple after 1634 and married Katherine, the wealthy widow of George Twiselton, in the late 1630s. The couple lived at West Newton Grange, Oswaldkirk and had one daughter. He was knighted on 27 December 1641 and sat as MP for New Malton 1641–18. He was a colonel in the parliamentarian army 1642–44 and directed the siege of Pontefract in 1648. Cholmley became an active royalist in 1659 and assisted in Booth’s rising of that year. He was once again a colonel of an infantry regiment June to October 1660. He was sent to Tangier in spring 1666 to oversee the harbour development but died there not long afterwards. His body was brought home and he was buried at West Newton Grange on 30 June 1666.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xc1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Clarkson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Clarkson (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Clarkson was ordained minister of St Michael the Archangel’s, Kirklington in October 1644. According to Thornton, he was very unpopular with parishioners as he preached against the Lord's prayer. He was replaced by Michael Syddall in 1646. He was also chaplain to Lord Ferdinando Fairfax pre-1648.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xc4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Hamden</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Comber</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Burton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mary Comber (1617-1672)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1617-09-14">baptised 14 September 1617</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1672-05-13">13 May 1672</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Comber, daughter of Brian and Alice Burton, was baptised 14 September 1617 at St Mary the Virgin’s, Westerham, Kent. On 30 April 1638 she married Edward Hamden, a mercer, but he died less than a year later. They had one daughter. She then married James Comber of Allington in 1639. They had five children, two of whom survived to adulthood, James and Thomas. Thornton and Mary Comber corresponded by letter after the marriage of their children, Nally and Thomas. She died on 13 May 1672 and was buried two days later at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave, where there is a plaque.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rc5">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Crathorne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Ralph Crathorne (1604-1665?)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1604">1604</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1665?">after 1665</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ralph Crathorne, son and heir of Thomas and Catherine Crathorne, was born in 1604. He married twice: first, Mary Wright, by whom he had two children (a son and a daughter), and second, Margaret Thornton, sister of William Thornton. Thornton writes that he was worth £800 per annum when he remarried. With Margaret he had four children (three sons and a daughter). He was still alive in 1665, as recorded in Dugdale’s visitation of that year.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xc3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Culliss</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Culliss (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Culliss was a presumably a cleric; in the 1660s, Gilbert Bennett, rector of Holy Trinity, Stonegrave, wished to marry one of his daughters to him and her portion was the living of Stonegrave. We have not been able to identify him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xd7">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Dalton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wyvill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth Dalton (1613-1711)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1613-10-10">baptised 10 October 1613</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1711-04-22">buried 22 April 1711</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is probably Elizabeth Dalton, daughter of Marmaduke Wyvill, 2nd Baronet of Constable Burton, and his wife, Isabel, baptised 10 October 1613 at St Mary the Virgin’s, Richmond. She married Sir William Dalton of Hauxwell Hall. They had 10 children (six sons and four daughters). She was buried at St Oswald’s, Hauxwell on 22 April 1711.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ed1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Edward Danby (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Edward Danby, the ninth child of Sir Thomas Danby and his wife Katherine, was born on 26 August 1644 at Middleham Castle, Yorkshire. Thornton was his aunt and godmother. He died on 6 July 1647 and was buried at St Peter’s, Leeds, the next day.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ad2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Abstrupus Danby (1655-1727)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1655-12-27">27 December 1655</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1727-12-27">27 December 1727</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Abstrupus Danby, the oldest surviving child of Christopher and Anne Danby, was born 27 December 1655; he was Thornton's great-nephew. Before 1679 he married Judith Moone and they had a son. He gained the Danby estate around 1683, from his father, the second son of Thomas Danby, who had inherited it on his elder brother’s murder in 1667. The estate was in debt and so he sold off much of the family's property (at Scruton, Thorpe Perrow, Driffield and Thornton Watlass) but came to be known as the 'Restorer' of his family. He corresponded with Thornton during the 1680s and 1690s, largely over money she felt owed. He was knighted in 1691 and was MP for Aldborough 1698–1700. Defeated in 1701, he retained an active interest in Yorkshire politics until his death on 27 December 1727.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xd1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Danby</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Danby (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Danby bought a rent charge, worth £80 per annum, which had been William Thornton’s. It has not been possible to identify him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xd6">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Darcy</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wyvill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Isabel Darcy (died 1660)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1660">1660</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Isabel Darcy was the daughter of Marmaduke Wyvill, second baronet of Burton Constable, and his wife, Isabel. Before 1650 she married James Darcy of Sedbury Park, near Richmond, and they had seven children (three sons and four daughters). She died in 1660.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fd4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Darcy</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Howard</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Frances Darcy (1623-1670)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1623-10-19">baptised 19 October 1623</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1670-04-10">buried 10 April 1670</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Lady Frances Darcy, daughter of Thomas Howard, 1st Earl of Berkshire and his wife Elizabeth, was baptised on 19 October 1623 at St Martin-in-the-Fields, London. On 6 February 1650 she became the second wife of Lord Conyers Darcy, 2nd Earl Holdernesse. They had six children (three sons and three daughters). She visited Thornton in Richmond in 1660. She was buried at St Margaret’s, Hornby on 10 April 1670.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jd6">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Darley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Darley (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Darley held a bond with William Thornton for £1000, dated 7 August 1662. We have not been able to identify him with any certainty but he is possibly John Darley, son of Richard Darley (and William Thornton’s first cousin), baptised on 16 January 1637 at St John the Evangelist’s, Buttercrambe.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xd3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Denton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Denton (c.1615-1668?)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1615~">c.1615</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1668?">after 1668</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Denton, son of Thomas and Barbara Denton, was born c.1615. He married Anne Maw in 1640 at St Gregory’s, Kirkdale and they had four children (two sons and two daughters). He was named as an appraiser of the late William Thornton’s goods in 1668.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="td5">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Dodsworth</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Timothy Dodsworth (1622-1673?)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1622-01-01">baptised 1 January 1622</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1673?">before 1673</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Timothy Dodsworth, son of John and Frances Dodsworth, was baptised on 1 January 1622 at St Mary the Virgin’s, Thornton Watlass. He was a household servant for Christopher Wandesford in Ireland in the 1630s and then entered Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge in 1637. He was admitted to Gray's Inn in January 1640. He married Dorothy Stringer on 14 April 1646 at St Bartholomew’s the Less, London, when he was in the service of the Earl of Holland at Kensington. They had two children (a son and a daughter). He died before 1673.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xd4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Driffield</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher(?) Driffield (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is probably Christopher Driffield, son of William and Ursula Driffield of Easingwold, baptised on 11 December 1627 at St John and All Saints’, Easingwold. He was admitted to Gray's Inn December 1650 and made Recorder of Ripon in 1673. He married Bridget West and they had at least one son, Christopher. He gave Thornton legal advice on a couple of occasions. He was buried on 7 March 1684 at St Peter and St Wilfrid’s, Ripon.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xe2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Edmunds</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas(?) Edmunds (c.1595-1663)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1595~">c.1595</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1663-01-09">9 January 1663</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is possibly Thomas Edmunds, son of John Edmunds of Dalton, born c.1595 and settled at Worsborough, Yorkshire. He was secretary to Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl Strafford. In the 1640s he lent Thornton’s cousin, William Wandesford, £200, with Alice Wandesford acting as a surety. Edmunds sued her many years later for the amount, interest and damages. Thornton refers to him negatively as ‘that Jew’. If the same man, he was involved in drawing up the articles of surrender for the city of York in summer 1644. He became a considerable landowner at Worsborough but, as a royalist, was sequestered, buying back his lands for £350.  He had at least one son. His will was dated 7 October 1662 and he died on 9 January 1663. He was buried at St Mary’s, Worsborough.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xf4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Fairfax</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">de Vere</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Fairfax (c.1617-1665)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1617~">1617/18</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1665-10-16">16 October 1665</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Fairfax, daughter of Horace Vere, Lord Tilbury and his wife, Mary, was born c. 1617/18 in the Netherlands, where she spent her early life. She married Thomas Fairfax, 3rd Lord of Cameron on 20 June 1637 and they had two daughters. She followed her husband, a parliamentarian commander, as he fought during the 1640s and was briefly taken prisoner by the Earl of Newcastle in 1643.  She and her husband retired to their estate at Nun Appleton, Yorks during the Interregnum. She died on 16 October 1665.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xf2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Fairfax</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Cholmeley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mary Fairfax (born 1624)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1624-11-04">baptised 4 November 1624</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Fairfax, daughter of Marmaduke and Ursula Cholmeley, was baptised 4 November 1624 at All Saints’, Brandsby; she was Thornton’s niece-by-marriage. She became the second wife of William Fairfax of Lythe and they had two sons. We do not know when she died.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tf1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Fairfax</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">3rd Lord of Cameron</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Fairfax (1612-1671)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1612-01-17">17 January 1612</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1671-11-12">12 November 1671</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Fairfax, son of Ferdinando Fairfax, 2nd Lord Cameron of Denton, Yorks and his first wife, Mary, was born 17 January 1612. He was educated at St John's College, Cambridge, matriculating in 1626, and entered Gray's Inn in 1628. He married Anne Vere in 1637 and they had two daughters. He was commander-in-chief of the parliamentarian forces during the First English Civil War, including leading the successful campaign at Marston Moor in July 1644. He was leader of the New Model Army from 1645 but refused to participate in the trial and execution of Charles I. Inheriting the title of 3rd Lord Cameron on his father’s death in 1648, he retired to Nun Appleton, Yorks, after the king's execution, and was instrumental in the restoration of Charles II. He died on 12 November 1671.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xf6">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Belasyse</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">1st Earl Falconbridge</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Belasyse (1627-1700)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1627">1627</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1700-12-31">31 December 1700</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Belasyse, son of Henry and Grace Belasyse, was born at Newburgh Priory, Coxwold (North Yorks) in 1627. He married twice: first, Mildred Saunderson in 1651; second, Mary, daughter of Lord Protector Oliver Cromwell, on 18 November 1657. He had no children. He inherited the title Viscount Falconbridge in 1653 and he took his seat as Lord Falconbridge in 1658. He became Lord Lieutenant of the North Riding and Durham in 1660. He became 1st Earl Fauconberg on 9 April 1689. He died in Chiswick on 31 December 1700 and was buried at St Michael’s, Coxwold on 31 January 1701.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cf1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Field</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Charles Field (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles Field seems to have been a servant in the Thornton household in the late 1660s. He was implicated in the spreading of rumours. We have not been able to identify him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="nf1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Fisher</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Normavill Fisher (born c.1642)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1642~">c.1642</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Normavill Fisher, born c.1642, was in the service of Anne Norton, Thornton's aunt, at St Nicholas, Richmond in 1660, aged 18. He was said to be born out of wedlock and to have fathered a child before marriage. He got married c.1661. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xf1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Flathers</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Flathers (c.1616-1686)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1616~">c. 1616</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1686">1686</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Flathers, son of Marmaduke Flathers of Weston was born c.1616. He was educated at Wakefield and Coxwold schools, and then Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge, graduating with a BA in 1635/6. He married Frances Shutte at Escrick on 15 November 1634. He was ordained deacon in 1638 and priest in 1639. He was vicar of St Nicholas’, North Grimston 1640–62, and vicar of St Mary’s, Lastingham and Rural Dean of Ryedale from September 1662. He died in 1686.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rf1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Fleetwood</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">Lord Fleetwood</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Charles Fleetwood (c.1618-1692)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1618~">c. 1618</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1692-10-04">4 October 1692</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles Fleetwood, third son of Sir Miles and Anne Fleetwood of Aldwincle, Northants, was born c.1618. Educated at Emmanuel College, Cambridge, he entered Gray's Inn on 30 November 1638. A parliamentarian soldier during the 1640s, leading troops at the Battle of Naseby in 1645, he rose to prominence during the Interregnum and became Commander in Chief of the parliamentary forces in Ireland in 1652 and Lord Deputy in 1654. He married three times; first, to Frances Smith and they had two children (a son and a daughter). He then married Bridget, daughter of Oliver Cromwell and widow of Henry Ireton, previous Commander of Ireland. They had three children, two of whom survived to adulthood. Bridget died in 1662 and in 1664 he married Mary, daughter of Sir John Coke. He died on 4 October 1692 and was buried at Bunhill Fields, London.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jf3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Foxcraft</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">James Foxcraft (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">James Foxcraft witnessed the will of Christopher Wandesford in Dublin in 1640. He may have come to Ireland with or around the same time as Wandesford, in which case he was perhaps the James Foxcraft, son of Isaac, of Bargrange, baptised on 27 October 1594 at St Peter’s, Leeds. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cf2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Foxley</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Foxley (c.1609-1680)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1609~">c.1609</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1680-09-24">24 September 1680</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Foxley, born c.1609, was an alderman in Hull and mayor of the city in 1657–58 and 1676–77. Described as a ‘gentleman’ in a settlement of May 1635, in 1647–48 he was auditor of the Hull Wool House accounts. William Thornton owed him money in the late 1650s. During his second term as mayor, Foxley was the recipient of several letters from the MP for Hull, Andrew Marvell. Foxley had an eight-hearth house built, probably in the 1660s, and was still living there in 1673; it is now the Old White Hart, Silver Street. He died aged 71 on 24 September 1680, predeceased by his wife, Mary, and was buried at Holy Trinity, Hull.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xf5">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Frankland</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Belasyse</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Arabella Frankland (c.1638-1687)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1638~">c.1638</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1687-02-26">26 February 1687</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Arabella Frankland, daughter of Henry and Grace Belasyse, was born c.1638. She was the younger sister of Thomas Belasyse, 1st Earl Falconbridge. In 1662 she married Sir William Frankland of Thirkleby and they had nine children, with four sons and a daughter surviving childhood. In 1668 she was involved in spreading rumours about Thornton. She died on 26 February 1687 and was buried at All Saints’, Great Thirkleby.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rg2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Garbutt</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Robert Garbutt (c.1617-1668?)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1617~">c.1617–19?</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1668?">after 1668</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Robert Garbutt was named as an appraiser of the late William Thornton’s goods in 1668. This might be the Robert Garbutt baptised at St John’s, Bilsdale Kirkham in 1617, or the one baptised at St Michael’s, Coxwold in 1619. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xg1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Gibson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Gibson (1630-1711)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1630-08-04">4 August 1630</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1711-11-20">20 November 1711</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is probably John Gibson of Welburn, Yorks, son of Sir John and Penelope Gibson, born 4 August 1630. He married Joan Pennyman on 30 September 1650 and they had 10 children (six sons and four daughters). He died on 20 November 1711.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jg1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Gibson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Gibson (1606-1665)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1606-01-20">20 January 1606</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1665-06-13">13 June 1665</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir John Gibson of Welburn, Yorks, son of Sir John and Anne Gibson, was born 20 January 1606. He married Penelope Woodall on 18 June 1629 and they had four sons. He died on 13 June 1665.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tg1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Gill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Gill (born c.1632)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1632~">c.1632</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Gill, second son of Thomas and Elizabeth (née Wandesford) Gill, was born c.1632; he was a distant relation of Thornton’s by marriage. An attorney, he married Elizabeth Smithson, and they had 10 children (five sons and five daughters).</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="sg2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Gosling</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Susan Gosling (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Susan Gosling was a maid who accompanied Thornton on a trip to meet her husband’s family in 1652. We have not been able to trace her any further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fg1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Graham</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Francis Graham (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Francis Graham was involved in delivering a letter from Peter Samways to Alice Thornton in 1668. He was possibly the Francis born c.1614, brother of Ranald Graham of Nunnington.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rg1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Graham</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Ranald Graham (c.1605-1685)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1605~">c.1605</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1685">1685</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ranald Graham, third son of Fergus and Sibill Graham of Plomp, was born c.1605. Apprenticed to a London merchant in 1622, he became a draper in Watling Street. By 1640 he was very wealthy and around this time he married Susannah Washington. He acquired Nunnington Hall in 1655 and Ranald and his wife moved from London. He became MP for Leominster in 1661 and Justice of the Peace for the North Riding of Yorkshire in 1662. Thornton called him ‘a good friend’ and he was made a trustee of a deed of gift for her children c.1668/9. He died without issue and his will was proved on 2 December 1685.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jh3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Hall</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Hall (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Hall was involved in a legal settlement between William Thornton and Christopher Wandesford in 1664. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xh4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Hassell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Hassell (c.1627-1694)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1627~">c. 1627</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1694-10-27">buried 27 October 1694</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Hassell, oldest son of Samuel and Mary Hassell of Hutton-on-Derwent, was born c.1627. He married Elizabeth Wood on 11 November 1647. He entered Gray's Inn in February 1648, becoming an utter barrister. He had seven children (three sons and four daughters). Thornton employed him to draw up a deed of gift after her husband’s death in 1668. He was buried at St Michael's, Malton on 27 October 1694.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jh2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Heald</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Jane Heald (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Jane Heald was likely employed in Thornton’s household in East Newton in 1662 as she was sent to Oswaldkirk to get help when Thornton was in labour. We have not been able to trace her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wh2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Heard</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Heard (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Heard married Mary Breakes, a former servant of Thornton’s. He was a joiner and Thornton had paid towards his apprenticeship. The couple were in London by May 1669.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jh4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Hicke</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Hicke (died 1677?)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1677-04-16?">buried 16 April 1677?</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Hicke was an old friend of William Thornton's who lent Alice Thornton £150 after William's death. The Hicke family had close connections with East Newton, with William Thornton’s great-grandfather (Robert) and grandfather (William) mentioning servants with the surname ‘Hicke’ in their wills made in 1572 and 1615 respectively. He is possibly the John Hicke ‘of Stonegrave’ buried at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave on 16 April 1677.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xh7">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Hickeringill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mrs Hickeringgill (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mrs Hickeringill was present when Alice Thornton was in labour at St Nicholas, Richmond in 1660. She was a perhaps a midwife. We have not been able to trace her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="eh1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Hicke</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth Hicke (born 1636?)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1636-03-13?">13 March 1636?</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth Hicke was a tenant of the Thorntons at East Newton in the 1660s; in 1668 she was paying £28 per annum for the land. The Hicke family had close connections with East Newton, with William Thornton’s great-grandfather (Robert) and grandfather (William) mentioning servants with the surname ‘Hicke’ in their wills made in 1572 and 1615 respectively. She was possibly Ralph Hicke’s daughter who was baptised on 13 March 1636 at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xh2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Darley</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Hildyard</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth Darley (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth Darley was the daughter of Sir William and Isabel Hildyard of Bishop Wilton, East Riding. She married Richard Darley, William Thornton’s maternal uncle, on 20 December 1632 at St Edith’s, Bishop Wilton. She was also the niece of Catherine Hansby, Alice Thornton's great-grandmother, via her mother Isabel. Elizabeth and Richard had five children (four sons and a daughter). Her date of death is unknown but she was buried at St Edith’s, Bishop Wilton.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wh1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Hildyard</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Hildyard (1577-1632)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1577-07-11">baptised 11 July 1577</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1632-10-06">6 October 1632</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir William Hildyard of Bishop Wilton, eldest son of William and Anne Hildyard, was baptised on 11 July 1577. He married Isabel Hansby, Thornton’s great aunt, and they had six children, of which three daughters survived to adulthood. He died on 6 October 1632.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xh5">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Holland</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Holland (c.1620-1677)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1620~">c.1620</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1677-10">October 1677</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Holland, son of George Holland, a Doncaster merchant, was born c.1620. He was educated at Sheffield Grammar School and St John’s, Cambridge, gaining his BA in 1642. He was ordained deacon and then priest in 1646. He became vicar of St Mary the Virgin’s, Westerham, Kent in 1657. During his time as vicar there, he taught a young Thomas Comber. He was then vicar of both St Nicholas’s, Great Wakering, Essex and All Hallows’, Staining, London between 1663 and 1677. In 1666 he tried to persuade Comber to marry his daughter. He died in October 1677.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xh6">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Holland</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">[unknown] Holland (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">An unknown daughter of William Holland who was vicar of both St Nicholas’s, Great Wakering, Essex and All Hallows’, Staining, London between 1663 and 1677. In 1666 her father suggested that Thomas Comber might marry her and take up a living in the south. We have not been able to identify her more precisely.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xh3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Hoyle</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Hoyle (1587-1650)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1587-01-29">baptised 29 January 1587</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1650-01-30">30 January 1650</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Hoyle, son of Thomas Hoyle of Slaithwaite and his wife Elizabeth, was baptised 29 January 1587. He was apprenticed to a merchant in Micklegate, York. He married Elizabeth Maskewe in 1611 and they went on to have 13 children, although only one survived childhood. He married his second wife, Susanna, c.1641 and they had two sons with one surviving to adulthood. Hoyle took up the Freedom of the city of York in 1612 and was warden of St Martin's, Micklegate in 1613. Rising up the civic ranks over the next 20 years, he became an alderman in 1626 and Mayor of York in 1632. A devout presbyterian, he called for Charles I to be brought to justice but took no part in the king's trial. He hanged himself on 30 January 1650, exactly a year after the regicide, in his lodgings at Broad Sanctuary, Westminster.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="eh2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Hunton</surname>
                  <surname type="married">Syddall</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Ellen Syddall (died 1661?)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1661-05-02?">buried 2 May 1661(?)</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ellen Syddall was the wife of Michael Syddall, minister of St Michael the Archangel’s, Kirklington. Her first husband was Christopher Hunton, steward to Thornton's father, Christopher Wandesford, at Kirklington. After his death, c.1644, she married Syddall. She was named co-executor of his will in 1658. She is perhaps the Ellen Syddall buried at All Saints’, Pickhill, on 2 May 1661.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xj2">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Thomas</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Jackson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Jackson (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is possibly Thomas Jackson of Nunnington, born c. 1632, barrister-at-law. In the late 1660s Mr Jackson was paid by the Thorntons to help acquire the living of Stonegrave for Thomas Comber and is probably the same Mr Jackson referenced in a letter, from Thornton to her husband in 1664, in connection with another legal matter. Thomas Jackson was married to Mary, and they had 11 children (five sons and six daughters), several of whom died as infants. He died three years after his wife on 7 July 1702 and was buried at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave the next day, where there is a memorial tablet to him, now in the south aisle.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xk1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Kendall</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">? Kendall (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Kendall was a wright (carpenter). William Thornton sold him the woods at Newton and Leysthorpe when in Scarborough, probably in 1667. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xk2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Kerney</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Kerney (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Kerney lived in Dublin in the 1640s and 1650s. He had at least one lodger, a clerk. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xl3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Lane</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Lane (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Lane was paid by Thornton to help acquire the living of Stonegrave for Thomas Comber in the late 1660s. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xl4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Langdale</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Philip Langdale (c.1604-1648)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1604~">c.1604</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1648">1648</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Philip Langdale, son of William and Elizabeth Langdale of Langthorpe, was born c.1604. He married Anne Thornton, William Thornton's older half-sister, and was worth about £800 per annum, according to Thornton. They had one son. He died in 1648.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ml1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Lightfoot</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mary Lightfoote (born c.1655)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1655~">c.1655</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Lightfoot, born c.1655, was the daughter of George and Daphne Lightfoot. She was present at the wedding of Thomas Comber and Nally Thornton in November 1668. We have not been able to trace her any further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xl5">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Lister</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth Lister (1605-1688)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1605-09-30">baptised 30 September 1605</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1688-12-14">buried 14 December 1688</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Cousin Lister was living in Ripon in 1669. She was possibly descended from Elizabeth Wandesford (b.1605) and her second husband, Walter Lister. We have not been able to trace her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="cm2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Man</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Charles Man (c.1643-1710)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1643~">c.1643</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1710-03-28">buried 28 March 1710</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles Man was the second son of Charles Man, yeoman, of Helmsley, Yorks, was born c.1643. He attended Helmsley and York schools, matriculating Sidney Sussex College, Cambridge on 1 June 1660, gaining his MA in 1667. He became curate of Dalby in 1664, rector of Dalby in 1667 and rector of Scawton in 1668. He married Philip Markindale of Barnard Castle on 3 September 1668 at All Saints’, Northallerton, and they had a son. In November 1668 Man performed the marriage ceremony of Thomas and Alice Comber at East Newton Hall. In 1676 he became rector of St Agatha’s, Gilling West. He was buried at St Agatha’s, Gilling West on 28 March 1710.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gm2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Masterman</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Masterman (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Masterman lived in Stonegrave, Ryedale and briefly boarded Thomas Comber in 1663. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fm1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Maude</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Frances Maude (1652-1690)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1652?">after 1652</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1690-01-05">5 January 1690</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Frances Maude, born after 1652, was the daughter of Sir Christopher Wandesford, 1st Baronet of Kirklington, and his wife, Eleanor; she was Thornton's niece. She married Robert Maude of West Riddleston and Ripon and they had three children (a son and two daughters). In 1669, as a married woman in Ripon, she heard Anne Danby’s rumours about her aunt Thornton. Robert Maude sold his Yorkshire estates and bought land in Kilkenny and Tipperary, where the family moved. She died on 5 January 1690 and was buried at St Mary’s, Kilkenny.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="sm1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Metcalfe</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Sander Metcalfe (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sander Metcalfe lived in the Yorkshire Dales c.1644. George Wandesford stayed with him for a long time, while hiding from Scottish soldiers. We have not been able to trace him further, although he is possibly the Sander Metcalfe of Burrill whose wife, Anne, was buried at St Gregory’s, Bedale on 7 September 1642.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wm1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Metcalfe</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Metcalfe (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Metcalfe is described by Thornton as both a servant of her uncle, William Wandesford, and his solicitor and agent. It was in the latter capacity that William Thornton hired him to deal with his legal issues in Ireland. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wm2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Mitchell</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Mitchell (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">William Mitchell was involved in a legal settlement between William Thornton and Christopher Wandesford in 1664. We have not been able to trace him any further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xm4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Morrett</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Richard</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Morrett (1618-1669)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1618-01-22">baptised 22 January 1618</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1669-04">buried April 1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is probably Richard Morrett of Harome Hall, Ryedale, son of John and Mary Morrett, baptised 22 January 1618 at St Saviour’s, Harome. Harome Hall was some two miles north of East Newton Hall, and as a neighbour of Thornton he agreed to perform a second appraisal of William Thornton's goods after his death in 1668. He is possibly the Richard Morrett who married Dorothy Freeman at St Mary Castlegate, York, on 14 June 1636. He was buried on 23 April 1669 at All Saints’, Helmsley. His will was proved at York on 10 May that year.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="an1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Norton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anthony Norton (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Anthony Norton was a relative of Thornton’s, who agreed to act as administrator of William Thornton’s estate in 1668. He was married; Alice Wandesford mentions his wife in her will made in 1658.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="fo1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">O'Neill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Phelim Roe O'Neill (c.1604-1653)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1604~">c. 1604</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1653-03-10">10 March 1653</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Phelim Roe O'Neill, eldest son of Sir Turlough Oge O'Neill of Kinnard and his wife, Catherine, was born c.1604. He was raised as a royal ward (and a protestant) after his father's death in 1608. He entered Lincoln's Inn in 1618. Returning to Ireland in 1628, he converted back to catholicism. He was knighted by Thomas Wentworth, Lord Deputy of Ireland, in 1639. In 1641 he was one of the conspirators in the Irish Rebellion. He married three times: first, to a daughter of Lord Iveagh, who died in 1641; second, to Louise Preston; third, to Jean Gordon, with whom he had a son. After a military defeat in 1653 he was captured and executed on 10 March.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="to1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Osborne</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">Earl of Danby</roleName>
                  <roleName type="peerage">Marquess of Carmarthen</roleName>
                  <roleName type="peerage">1st Duke of Leeds</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Osborne (1632-1712)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1632-02-20">20 February 1632</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1712-07-26">26 July 1712</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir Thomas Osborne, son of Sir Edward Osborne of Kiveton and his second wife, Anne, was born on 20 February 1632; he was Thornton’s cousin. He became his father's heir in 1638 when his older brother died in an accident. His father’s property was sequestered after the battle of Marston Moor in 1644 and he was exiled to Europe in the early 1650s. He married Bridget Bertie and they had 11 children (three sons and eight daughters). He became High Sheriff of Yorkshire in 1661 and Lord Treasurer 1673–79. In June 1674 he was made Earl of Danby. Impeached after the 'Popish Plot' in 1678, he spent the next six years in the Tower of London. He was then released on bail and played a key role in the plot against James II, advising William of Orange, who, on becoming king in 1688, made him President of the Privy Council. He was made Marquess of Carmarthen in April 1689 and 1st Duke of Leeds in May 1694. The following year he was involved in a corruption scandal and left the political arena. He died on 26 July 1712 at his daughter Sophia’s house in Easton Neston, Northants. Thornton wrote to him at least three times asking for his help (1673–89). He was buried at All Hallows’, Harthill.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xp2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Palmes</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Eure</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mary Palmes (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Palmes was the daughter of William Eure, sixth Baron Eure of Malton, and his wife, Margaret; she was Margaret Danby’s sister. She married William Palmes, High Sheriff of Rutland (later MP for Malton), on 15 July 1663. They had eight children (four sons and four daughters). She lent Thornton their coach to transport William Thornton’s body back from Malton in September 1668.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jp3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Pape</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Pape (born 1630?)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1630-03-13?">13 March 1630?</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Pape married Barbara Todd, who had been a maid in the service of Anne Danby, on 29 May 1670 at All Saints and St James’s, Nunnington. They had at least one child. We do not know when he died. He was possibly the son of William Pape, born 13 March 1630 at St Leonard’s, New Malton.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mp1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Plewes</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mary Plewes (born 1635?)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1635-05-13?">baptised 13 May 1635?</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mary Plewes was implicated by Thornton is spreading lies about Thomas Comber in the late 1660s. She was perhaps the Mary Plewes, daughter of John Plewes, baptised at St Gregory’s, Bedale on 13 May 1635. We have not been able to trace her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ep1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Poore</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth Poore (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Bess Poore was a servant, first in Alice Wandesford's house at Hipswell, in the 1650s when Thornton and her husband were living there. She then seems to have moved to Lady Wyvill’s service and is there in 1668. A marginal note (‘B. Scarborough’) in Thornton’s ‘Book 3’ indicates that she may have married and changed her name or that she moved to Scarborough. We have not been able to trace her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xp1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Preston</surname>
                  <roleName type="peerage">1st Viscount Tara</roleName>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Preston (1585-1655)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1585">1585</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1655-10-21">21 October 1655</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Preston, second son of Christopher Preston, 4th Viscount Gormanston, and his second wife, Catherine, was born in 1585. Destined for a military career after attending the Irish college at Douai, he became a captain in the regiment of Henry O'Neill and served in the Netherlands. He married twice: first, Clara van der Eycken of Flanders, with whom he had at least two sons, before her death in 1621; second, Marguerite of Namur with whom he probably had two more children, although these could have also been with his first wife. He frequently returned to Ireland in the 1640s and was appointed commander of the army of Leinster in 1642. He was made Viscount Tara and Governor of Waterford in 1650. He returned to Flanders and died there on 21 October 1655.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="wr1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Ryves</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Ryves (died 1648)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1648">1648</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Sir William Ryves was the sixth son of John and Elizabeth Ryves of Blandford, Dorset. He entered Middle Temple in 1593 and was called to the bar in 1600. He became Attorney General of Ireland in November 1619, a position he held until 1636 when he resigned to become justice of the court of King's Bench in Ireland. He was MP for Belturbet, county Cavan, in 1634–35. He was Speaker of the Irish House of Lords in 1641–42. He married twice, first to a woman called Latham or Jackman, with whom he had four sons and four daughters, and second to Dorothy Waldron. He died in Dublin in 1648.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xr3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Roose</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Roose (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Roose came to Holy Trinity, Stonegrave with Gilbert Bennett in 1666 to help him collect tithes. We have not been able to identify him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs7">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Scott</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Scott (c.1634-c.1700)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1634~">c. 1634</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1700~">c. 1700</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is probably George Scott, son of George Scott (rector of St Wilfrid’s, Langton-on-Swale), born c.1634. He attended Giggleswick School and was admitted to Christ's College, Cambridge in 1649, obtaining his BA in 1652 and MA in 1663. He was instituted to the rectory of St Oswald’s, Oswaldkirk in 1663, a position he held until his death c.1700. He was also possibly the rector of St John’s, Kirby Wiske, from 1661–92. He had at least one son and two or more daughters.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gs2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Sheldon</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Gilbert Sheldon (1598-1677)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1598-06-19">19 June 1598</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1677-11-09">9 November 1677</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Gilbert Sheldon, youngest son of Roger Sheldon (bailiff to Gilbert Talbot, the earl of Shrewsbury), was born 19 June 1598. He graduated from Trinity College, Oxford in 1617 and got his MA from Cambridge in 1620. After entering All Souls’, Oxford as a fellow, he was ordained deacon by the Bishop of Oxford at Dorchester and likely ordained priest shortly afterwards. A royalist during the war, he was made Archbishop of Canterbury in 1663, a position he held until his death on 9 November 1677.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs11">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Grace</forename>
                  <surname type="married">Sherwood</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Bond(?)</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Grace Sherwood (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mrs Sherwood was the wife of Elias Sherwood of Petergate, York, who owned lodgings in the late 1660s. Nally and Katherine Thornton, and servant Hannah Ableson, stayed there when the girls were at school in York in 1667. She is perhaps Grace Bond of Breighton who married one Elias Sherwood of York at All Saints’, Bubwith (East Yorks), on 2 November 1665.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs8">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Skinner</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">William Skinner (c.1627-1680)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1627~">c. 1627</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1680-09-19">19 September 1680</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is probably William Skinner, born c.1627, merchant, alderman of Hull and mayor in 1664. He married Jane Foxley, daughter of William Foxley, but she died in 1652. He built a house on the east side of the High Street in 1672, which had 13 hearths; it was later known as Etherington House and was demolished after being damaged in World War Two. He died on 19 September 1680.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs10">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Smithson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Smithson (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Smithson owned a shop in Richmond in 1660. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs5">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Stone</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Christopher Stone (died 1686)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1686-11-26">buried 26 November 1686</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is probably Dr Christopher Stone, ordained deacon in 1635 and priest in 1637 by Thomas Morton, bishop of Durham. He was instituted rector of St Peter’s, Dalby in 1640 and Chancellor of York in 1662. He was rector of St Leonard’s, Beeford, 1669–85. He married Grace Robinson on 24 May 1644 at St John’s, Ousebridge, York and had at least four children (three daughters and a son). He was buried at York Minster on 26 November 1686.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs6">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Stone</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">[unknown] Stone (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is a daughter of Dr Christopher Stone and his wife Grace (Anne, Beatrice, or Margery). She had a portion of £1500 and her father wanted her to marry Thomas Comber c.1668.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="gs1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Straherne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">George Straherne (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">George Straherne witnessed the will of Christopher Wandesford in Dublin in 1640. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Sworre</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Dame Sworre (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dame Sworre helped deliver Thornton’s nephew, Francis, in Thorpe in 1645. She was perhaps a midwife. We have not been able to identify her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt8">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Tancred</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Charles Tancred (c.1631-1711)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1631~">c. 1631</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1711-02-26">26 February 1711</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Charles Tancred, son of William Tancred of Arden, was born c.1631. He married Barbara Dalton and they had 18 children (12 sons and six daughters), of which only three survived to adulthood. His property was sequestered in 1645, due to him supporting the royalist cause. In 1660 he was accused of threatening the peace of the Commonwealth. According to Thornton, Tancred bet her cousin, Lady Mary Yorke, that Thornton would marry Thomas Comber within a month of her husband’s death. He renovated Arden Hall in 1680. Tancred died, aged 80, on 26 February 1711 and was buried at All Saints’, Hawnby in the same grave as his wife, who predeceased him.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="tt2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Thompson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Thomas Thompson (died 1668?)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1668?">after 1668</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Thomas Thompson was named as an appraiser of the late William Thornton’s goods at East Newton in 1668. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt6">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Tirrill</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mrs Tirrill (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mrs Tirrill was the wife of Mr Tirrill of Hoddesdon, Herts. She attended the funeral of John Wandesford in Broxbourne with her husband and servant in 1664. We have not been able to identify her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt9">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Tully</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Tullye (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Tully lived about two miles from Stonegrave in 1663 and briefly boarded Thomas Comber. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xt7">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Thorpe</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Francis Thorpe (1594-1665)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1594-10-01">baptised 1 October 1594</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1665-06-07">buried 7 June 1665</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Francis Thorpe, oldest son of Roger and Elizabeth Thorpe of Birdsall, Yorks, was born in 1594. He was admitted to Gray's Inn in 1611 and graduated from St John's College, Cambridge in 1614. He was called to the bar in 1621 and was elected Recorder of Beverley in 1624. He married the twice-widowed Elizabeth Denton (née Oglethorpe). In 1645 he was elected 'recruiter' MP (filling a vacancy caused by a by-election) for Richmond. During the second English Civil War he played an important role organising parliamentary forces in the north and was appointed serjeant-at-law in 1648. While named commissioner to try the king in January 1649 he took no part in it. In February 1649 he was appointed to ride the northern circuit, which included Yorkshire. He was judge on this circuit for the winter assizes from 1649 (when still a serjeant) to 1653 and the summer assizes 1649–51 and again in 1659. On 1 June 1659 he was made one of the Barons of the Exchequer. He was elected MP for Beverley in 1654 but was prevented from sitting due to his refusing to try fellow Yorkshiremen after Penruddock's rising. He took up his seat in 1659 but his legal career was ended by the restoration of Charles II in 1660. He died intestate and was buried at All Hallows’, Bardsey on 7 June 1665.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jw2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Joyce Wandesford (1618-1620)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1618-06-03">baptised 3 June 1618</birth>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1620-09-11">buried 11 September 1620</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Joyce Wandesford, the third child of Christopher and Alice Wandesford, was baptised at St Michael the Archangel’s, Kirklington on 3 June 1618. According to her younger sister, Thornton, she died aged four years old, but she was buried on 11 September 1620 at St Michael the Archangel’s, Kirklington, so she was in fact two years old.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jw3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Ande</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Wandesford</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Jane Ande (born 1604?)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1604-03-04?">baptised 4 March 1604(?)</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">According to Thornton, her cousin Jane Wandesford married a Mr Ande by the late 1660s and lived in the Ripon area. She may be Jane Wandesford, daughter of Richard and Muriel Wandesford of Pickhill, who was baptised 4 March 1604 at All Saints’, Pickhill.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xw1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Watkinson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Henry Watkinson (1628-1712)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1628-04-24">baptised 24 April 1628</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1712-04-25">25 April 1712</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dr Henry Watkinson, son of Henry Watkinson, was born in Ilkley and baptised on 24 April 1628 at St Peter’s, Leeds. He attended Ilkley School and matriculated at St John's College, Cambridge in 1645, getting his BA in 1649. He obtained his doctorate in law from Padua in 1659. He was made a trustee of a deed of gift for Thornton’s children c.1668/9. He was Chancellor of York 1673–1712. He married Elizabeth Hodgson (née Jennings), and they had a son. He died on 25 April 1712 and was buried at St Cuthbert’s, York.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xw4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Watson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mrs Watson (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mrs Watson was one of the women present when Thornton was in labour at East Newton in 1662. We have not been able to identify her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="aw3">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wellburne</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Nan Wellburne (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Nan Wellburne was a maid in Thornton's Oswaldkirk household in 1661. We have not been able to identify her further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xw3">
               <persName>
                  <forename>Richard</forename>
                  <surname type="birth">Wilson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Richard Wilson (died 1669)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1669">1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">This is possibly Richard Wilson, rector of Holy Trinity, Chester, ordained in 1621. A royalist, he was absent in the early 1640s when he may have moved to St Michael's, Chester, where Thornton recalls that he gave her communion. He died in 1669.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ew1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wollstone</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Ezra Wollstone (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ezra Wollstone witnessed the will of Christopher Wandesford in Dublin in 1640. He is possibly the same gentleman of Newark that married Jane Halwell at St Peter’s, Farndon, Nottinghamshire on 15 February 1643.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xw5">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Wyvill</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Darcy</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Ursula Wyvill (died 1680)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1680">1680</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Lady Ursula Wyvill was the second child of Conyers Darcy, 1st Earl Holderness, and his wife, Grace. She married Sir Christopher Wyvill, 3rd Baronet of Constable Burton, on 12 December 1636 at St Mary’s, Swillington. They had 12 children, six of whom survived to adulthood. She wrote a commonplace book c.1662-72, which has survived. She died in 1680.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="jx2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">John Thornton (1633-1669)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1633-10-05">5 October 1633</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1669-05-22">22 May 1669</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">John Thornton was the son of Robert and Elizabeth Thornton of East Newton; William Thornton's younger brother. He was born on 5 October 1633 and baptised on 10 October at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave. He died on 22 May 1669 and was buried at Stonegrave the next day.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ax1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Langdale</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Thornton</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Anne Langdale (born 1611)</persName>
               <birth type="baptism" when-custom="1611-12-03">baptised 3 December 1611</birth>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Anne Langdale, the third daughter of Robert and Dorothy Thornton of East Newton, was baptised on 3 December 1611 at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave. She was William Thornton's half-sister. She married Philip Langdale of Langthorpe and they had one son. We do not know when she died.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xd8">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Darcy</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Darcy (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Darcy was a man who had heard rumours about Thornton and Thomas Comber. We have not been able to identify him further, although there are other Darcys in Thornton’s Books.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="dt1">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="married">Thornton</surname>
                  <surname type="birth">Metham</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Dorothy Thornton (died 1619)</persName>
               <death type="burial" when-custom="1619-07-14">buried 14 July 1619</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Dorothy Thornton was the daughter of Thomas and Catherine Metham of Metham, East Riding of Yorkshire. A Catholic, she was the first wife of Robert Thornton of East Newton, William Thornton’s father. They had four daughters, one of whom died in infancy. She was buried on 14 July 1619 at Holy Trinity, Stonegrave.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="en2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Nicholson</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Elizabeth Nicholson (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Elizabeth Nicholson was a married woman and a relation of Thornton’s, with connections to the Ripon area. She helped defend Thornton from rumours in 1668–89. Thornton notes she was Catholic. A cousin of Thornton’s distant cousin Thomas Gill, she was probably related to Thornton by marriage, via the Wandesfords of Pickhill.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs9">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Smith</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Smith (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Smith made a copy of Christopher Wandesford’s Book of Advice for Thornton. We have not been able to trace him further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rw4">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Wallis</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Ralph Wallis (died 1677)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1677">1677</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Ralph Wallis of Killenny was Clerk of the Rolls in Ireland. In 1642 he was elected MP for Athboy. He married twice: first, a member of the Talbot of Carton family, with whom he had a son; then, Jane Wilson, with whom he had two more sons. He was a witness to Christopher Wandesford’s will in Dublin 1640 and, c.1647, helped identify the lost will at Mr Kerney’s house. In 1659 he was living in St Catherine’s parish, Dublin, where he was churchwarden. In 1660 he received a lease of lands in Malahide for 21 years. His will was written in 1675 and he died in 1677.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="oc2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Connolly</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Owen Connolly (died 1649)</persName>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1649">1649</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Owen Connolly was born into a Gaelic Irish family, probably in County Monaghan. A member of the household of Sir Hugh Clotworthy and then his son Sir John Clotworthy, he converted to protestantism while in their service at Antrim Castle. He married an unknown English woman and had two children (a son and a daughter). He is best known for reporting the plot of his foster brother, Hugh Og Macmahon, to seize Dublin Castle in 1641 to Sir William Parsons, one of the Lords Justices of Ireland, for which he was awarded £500 and a £200 annual pension by the English Parliament. He remained in Sir John Clotworthy’s service during the 1640s, as well as acting as a messenger for parliament. He became lieutenant colonel, commanding Clotworthy’s regiment in 1646, and was shot in a skirmish with soldiers in August 1649 at Dunadry, co. Antrim. He died of his wounds and was buried at Antrim.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xc5">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Connolly</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mrs Connolly (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mrs Connolly was the wife of Owen Connolly. They had two children (a son and a daughter). We have not been able to trace her any further.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xs13">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Smith</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">Mr Smith (n. d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">Mr Smith was a cleric who took part in Alice Wandesford’s funeral at St Anne’s, Catterick in December 1659. He might be the George Smith instituted as vicar of Thornton Watlass in 1669.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="js2">
               <persName>
                  <surname type="birth">Savile</surname>
               </persName>
               <persName type="label">James Savile (1644-1671)</persName>
               <birth type="birth" when-custom="1644">1644</birth>
               <death type="death" when-custom="1671-10-11">11 October 1671</death>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">James Savile, 2nd Earl of Sussex, was born in 1644 to Thomas Savile, 1st Earl of Sussex, and his wife, Anne. He inherited the earldom aged 15 on his father’s death in 1659. He married Anne Wake before 1661 and they lived at Howley Hall, Morley from 1661. They had one son, who died as an infant in July 1671. Savile died just three months later and was buried on 11 October at All Saints’, Batley. His earldom became extinct on his death. His sister, Frances Brudenell, inherited his estate.</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="xb14">
               <persName/>
               <persName type="label">Mrs Bradley (n.d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">[placeholder]</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="ja2">
               <persName/>
               <persName type="label">Judith Ayscough (n.d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">[placeholder]</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="mc2">
               <persName/>
               <persName type="label">Marmaduke Cholmeley (n.d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">[placeholder]</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="rs2">
               <persName/>
               <persName type="label">Richard Sterne (n.d.)</persName>
               <noteGrp>
                  <note type="bio">[placeholder]</note>
               </noteGrp>
            </person>
         </listPerson>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
